<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akn:akomaNtoso xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><akn:act><akn:meta><akn:identification source="#cosilico"><akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-01" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-01" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-05-01" name="release" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#vermont-legislature" /><akn:FRBRcountry value="us-vt" /><akn:FRBRnumber value="01" /><akn:FRBRname value="Vermont Statutes Annotated" /></akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-01/eng@2023-05-01" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-01/eng@2023-05-01" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-05-01" name="publication" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /><akn:FRBRlanguage language="eng" /></akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRManifestation><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-01/eng@2023-05-01/akn.xml" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-01/eng@2023-05-01/akn.xml" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /></akn:FRBRManifestation></akn:identification><akn:references><akn:TLCOrganization eId="vermont-legislature" href="https://legislature.vermont.gov" showAs="Vermont General Assembly" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico" /></akn:references></akn:meta><akn:body><akn:title eId="title-01"><akn:num>Title 01</akn:num><akn:heading>General Provisions</akn:heading><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-1"><akn:num>Chapter 1</akn:num><akn:heading>Vermont Statutes Annotated</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-3"><akn:num>Chapter 3</akn:num><akn:heading>Construction of Statutes</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-5"><akn:num>Chapter 5</akn:num><akn:heading>Common Law; General Rights</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-7"><akn:num>Chapter 7</akn:num><akn:heading>Legal Holidays; Commemorative Days</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-9"><akn:num>Chapter 9</akn:num><akn:heading>Time</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-11"><akn:num>Chapter 11</akn:num><akn:heading>Flag, Insignia, Seal, etc.</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-13"><akn:num>Chapter 13</akn:num><akn:heading>Jurisdiction of the United States</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-15"><akn:num>Chapter 15</akn:num><akn:heading>New Hampshire-Vermont Boundary</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-17"><akn:num>Chapter 17</akn:num><akn:heading>Vermont Coordinate System</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-19"><akn:num>Chapter 19</akn:num><akn:heading>Meridian Lines for Towns and Cities</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-21"><akn:num>Chapter 21</akn:num><akn:heading>Interstate Cooperation</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-23"><akn:num>Chapter 23</akn:num><akn:heading>Native American Indian People</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-25"><akn:num>Chapter 25</akn:num><akn:heading>Truth and Reconciliation Commission [Repealed effective July 1, 2026]</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-1"><akn:num>Chapter 1</akn:num><akn:heading>Vermont Statutes Annotated</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-1_section-51"><akn:num>Section 51</akn:num><akn:heading>Vermont Statutes Annotated defined</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Vermont Statutes Annotated, Revision of 1959, as published by the Commission to revise the statutory law of Vermont under No. 91 of the Acts of 1957, 1 V.S.A. §§ 1-9, are hereby enacted as positive statute law, exclusive of the prefatory subject matter, analyses, catchlines, notes, annotations, appendixes, tables and indexes contained therein.  They may be cited as —— V.S.A. § —— and they shall not, in any citation of the statutes, be considered as acts of the present year.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-1_section-52"><akn:num>Section 52</akn:num><akn:heading>Vermont Statutes Annotated; time of taking effect</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Vermont Statutes Annotated shall take effect from and after July 1, 1959 except the parts thereof as to which a different provision is expressly made therein.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-1_section-55"><akn:num>Section 55</akn:num><akn:heading>Repeal of Vermont Statutes, Revision of 1947, and session laws not to affect associations and corporations</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The repeal of the Vermont Statutes, Revision of 1947, and acts of the General Assembly shall not affect associations or private corporations organized thereunder, but they may have and exercise the powers conferred thereby.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-1_section-56"><akn:num>Section 56</akn:num><akn:heading>Limitations, how affected</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When a limitation or period of time prescribed in an act repealed, for acquiring a right, or barring a remedy, or for any other purpose, has begun to run and the same or a similar limitation is prescribed in the Vermont Statutes Annotated, the time of limitation shall continue to run, and shall have like effect as if the whole period had begun and ended under the operation of the Vermont Statutes Annotated.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-1_section-57"><akn:num>Section 57</akn:num><akn:heading>Vermont Statutes Annotated, continuation of existing laws</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The provisions of the Vermont Statutes Annotated, so far as they are the same as those of existing laws, shall be construed as a continuation of those laws, and not as new enactments.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-1_section-59"><akn:num>Section 59</akn:num><akn:heading>Certified copy of Vermont Statutes Annotated</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A copy of the Vermont Statutes Annotated shall be kept in the office of the Secretary of State, to which copy that officer shall affix a certificate, under his or her hand and the Seal of the State, that the laws therein contained are the statute laws of the State of Vermont; and that certified copy shall be an authentic record of those laws.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-3"><akn:num>Chapter 3</akn:num><akn:heading>Construction of Statutes</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-101"><akn:num>Section 101</akn:num><akn:heading>Application of chapter</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>In the construction of statutes, the rules set out in this chapter shall be observed, unless such construction is inconsistent with the manifest intent of the General Assembly or repugnant to the context of the same statute.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-111"><akn:num>Section 111</akn:num><akn:heading>Annual meeting</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Annual meeting” when applied to towns shall mean the annual town meeting in March or an adjournment thereof.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-112"><akn:num>Section 112</akn:num><akn:heading>Biennial; biennially</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Biennial” or “biennially” shall mean the year in which a regular session of the General Assembly is held.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-113"><akn:num>Section 113</akn:num><akn:heading>County; town</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“County” or “town” may mean the county or town in which the subject matter referred to is situate, belongs or is cognizable.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-114"><akn:num>Section 114</akn:num><akn:heading>Domestic and foreign corporations</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Domestic” when applied to a corporation, company, association, or copartnership shall mean organized under the laws of this State; “foreign,” when so applied, shall mean organized under the laws of another state, government, or country.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-115"><akn:num>Section 115</akn:num><akn:heading>Fees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Fees” shall mean earnings due for official services, aside from salaries or per diem compensation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-116"><akn:num>Section 116</akn:num><akn:heading>Folio</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Folio” shall mean 100 words.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-117"><akn:num>Section 117</akn:num><akn:heading>General election; local election</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“General election” shall mean any election of State and county officers, Representatives to the General Assembly, U.S. Senators, Representative to Congress, or electors.  “Local election” shall mean any election of town or village officers in towns or villages having more than 4,000 inhabitants.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-118"><akn:num>Section 118</akn:num><akn:heading>Grantor; grantee</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Grantor” may include every person by or from whom an estate or interest in land is passed in or by a deed.  “Grantee” may include every person to whom such estate or interest passes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-119"><akn:num>Section 119</akn:num><akn:heading>Highway; road</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Highway” or “road” shall include bridges thereon and their approaches.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-121"><akn:num>Section 121</akn:num><akn:heading>Issue</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Issue” as applied to the descent of estates shall include the lawful lineal descendants of the ancestor.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-122"><akn:num>Section 122</akn:num><akn:heading>Justice</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Justice” when applied to a person, other than a Justice of the Supreme Court, shall mean a justice of the peace for the county for which he or she is elected or appointed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-123"><akn:num>Section 123</akn:num><akn:heading>Magistrate</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Magistrate” shall mean any Supreme Court Justice, Superior judge, District judge, or Probate judge.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-124"><akn:num>Section 124</akn:num><akn:heading>Month; year</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Month” shall mean a calendar month and “year” shall mean a calendar year and be equivalent to the expression “year of our Lord.”</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-126"><akn:num>Section 126</akn:num><akn:heading>Municipality</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Municipality” shall include a city, town, town school district, incorporated school or fire district or incorporated village, and all other governmental incorporated units.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-127"><akn:num>Section 127</akn:num><akn:heading>Oath; sworn</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Oath” shall include affirmation where by law an affirmation may be substituted.  In like cases, “sworn” shall include affirmed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-128"><akn:num>Section 128</akn:num><akn:heading>Person</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Person” shall include any natural person, corporation, municipality, the State of Vermont or any department, agency, or subdivision of the State, and any partnership, unincorporated association, or other legal entity.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-129"><akn:num>Section 129</akn:num><akn:heading>Personal estate</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Personal estate” shall include all property other than real estate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-130"><akn:num>Section 130</akn:num><akn:heading>Population; inhabitants</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Population” or “inhabitants” shall mean the population of the political division referred to, as ascertained by the national census last completed before the time when such population is a material fact.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-131"><akn:num>Section 131</akn:num><akn:heading>Preceding; following; such; said</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Preceding” and “following” when used by way of reference to a section of the law shall mean the next preceding or following section.  “Such” and “said” when used by way of reference to a person or thing shall apply to the same person or thing last mentioned.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-132"><akn:num>Section 132</akn:num><akn:heading>Land; lands; real estate</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Land,” “lands,” and “real estate” shall include lands, tenements, and hereditaments and all rights thereto and interests therein, and pews or slips in places of public worship shall be treated as real estate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-133"><akn:num>Section 133</akn:num><akn:heading>Seal—Official</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When a seal of a court, public officer, or corporation is required to be affixed to a paper, “seal” shall include an impression of the official seal made upon paper alone or by means of a wafer or wax affixed thereto.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-134"><akn:num>Section 134</akn:num><akn:heading>Private</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When the private seal of a person or corporation is required on an instrument or writing to make such instrument or writing legal and valid, such seal shall consist of an impression as provided in section 133 of this title or of a wafer, wax, or other adhesive substance affixed thereto or of a paper or other similar substance affixed thereto or the word “seal” or the letters “L.S.” opposite the signature.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-134a"><akn:num>Section 134a</akn:num><akn:heading>Registered mail</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Registered mail,” as the words appear in Vermont Statutes Annotated, the Vermont Rules of Civil Procedure and the Vermont Rules of Criminal Procedure, when used solely for the purpose of securing evidence of delivery, shall include any method of mail delivery requiring the signature of the addressee or his or her agent.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-135"><akn:num>Section 135</akn:num><akn:heading>School officers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“School officers” shall include all persons, other than teachers, who have to do with matters pertaining to public schools.  The board of school directors of a town school district or the governing board of an incorporated school district shall constitute the legislative branch of such district.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-136"><akn:num>Section 136</akn:num><akn:heading>State</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“State” when applied to the different parts of the United States may apply to the District of Columbia and any territory and the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-137"><akn:num>Section 137</akn:num><akn:heading>Sworn</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Sworn” when applied to public officers required by the constitution to take certain oaths shall refer to those oaths; when applied to other officers, it shall mean sworn to the faithful discharge of the duties of their offices before a person authorized to administer oaths.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-138"><akn:num>Section 138</akn:num><akn:heading>Time, how computed</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When time is to be reckoned from a day, date, or an act done, such day, date, or day when such act is done shall not be included in the computation, unless otherwise provided.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-139"><akn:num>Section 139</akn:num><akn:heading>Town; town officers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Town” shall include city and wards or precincts therein; “selectboard members” and “board of civil authority” shall extend to and include the mayor and aldermen of cities; “trustees” shall extend to and include bailiffs of incorporated villages; and the laws applicable to the inhabitants and officers of towns shall be applicable to the inhabitants and similar officers of all municipal corporations.  This section shall be so construed as not to conflict with the acts of incorporation of or laws specially applicable to such municipal corporations.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-140"><akn:num>Section 140</akn:num><akn:heading>Village</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Village” shall mean an incorporated village.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-141"><akn:num>Section 141</akn:num><akn:heading>Will</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Will” shall include codicils.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-142"><akn:num>Section 142</akn:num><akn:heading>Written; in writing</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Written” or “in writing” may include printing or other mode of representing words and letters, except where the written signature of a person is required.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-143"><akn:num>Section 143</akn:num><akn:heading>Sexual orientation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The term “sexual orientation” means female or male homosexuality, heterosexuality, or bisexuality. “Sexual orientation” shall not be construed to protect conduct otherwise proscribed by law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-144"><akn:num>Section 144</akn:num><akn:heading>Gender identity</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The term “gender identity” means an individual’s actual or perceived gender identity, or gender-related characteristics intrinsically related to an individual’s gender or gender-identity, regardless of the individual’s assigned sex at birth.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-145"><akn:num>Section 145</akn:num><akn:heading>Include, includes, and including</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The terms “include,” “includes,” and “including” mean that the language following the term is illustrative and not exhaustive, and shall have the same meaning as though the term were followed by the words “but not limited to.”</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-146"><akn:num>Section 146</akn:num><akn:heading>Intellectual disability</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Intellectual disability” or “person with an intellectual disability” shall mean an individual who has significantly subaverage intellectual functioning existing concurrently with deficits in adaptive behavior. “Intellectual disability” replaces what was previously known as “mental retardation.”</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-147"><akn:num>Section 147</akn:num><akn:heading>Psychiatric disability</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Psychiatric disability” means an impairment of thought, mood, perception, orientation, or memory that limits one or more major life activities but does not include intellectual disability.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-148"><akn:num>Section 148</akn:num><akn:heading>Developmental disability</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>“Developmental disability” or “person with developmental disabilities” shall have the same meaning as in 18 V.S.A. § 9302.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-149"><akn:num>Section 149</akn:num><akn:heading>Semiweekly</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Unless a statute provides a more specific definition, “semiweekly” means twice per week.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-171"><akn:num>Section 171</akn:num><akn:heading>Court; officer; board</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When a court, officer, or board is named by official title, such designation shall apply to the court, officer, or board of the county, town, or place within and for which they are qualified to act.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-172"><akn:num>Section 172</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint authority</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When joint authority is given to three or more, the concurrence of a majority of such number shall be sufficient and shall be required in its exercise.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-173"><akn:num>Section 173</akn:num><akn:heading>Minors</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Persons of the age of 18 years shall be considered of age and until they attain that age, shall be minors.  Whenever referred to in the laws of this State, a person who is an adult or who has attained majority shall be a resident or nonresident person of 18 years of age or more.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-174"><akn:num>Section 174</akn:num><akn:heading>Notice by publication</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When a notice is required to be given by publication in a newspaper, it shall mean a newspaper published in the county where the subject matter is situated, pending or to be heard, or a newspaper published within the State which has a general circulation.  In any case, in its discretion, the court may cause such notice to be further published in a newspaper which circulates in the neighborhood of the persons interested. Whenever a notice of any kind is required to be given by publication in a newspaper prior to a certain date for a certain number of weeks successively, it may be given by an insertion prior to such date once a week, for the number of successive weeks required, either in a daily, semiweekly, or weekly newspaper.  If such publication is in a daily or semiweekly newspaper, such notice shall be inserted on the same day of each successive week.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-175"><akn:num>Section 175</akn:num><akn:heading>Number; gender</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Words importing the singular number may extend and be applied to more than one person or thing; words importing the plural number may be applied as if singular and words importing the masculine may extend and be applied to persons of the feminine gender.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-176"><akn:num>Section 176</akn:num><akn:heading>Title; chapter; section</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The words “title,” “chapter,” and “section” when used by way of reference shall mean a title, chapter, or section of Vermont Statutes Annotated.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-177"><akn:num>Section 177</akn:num><akn:heading>Domicile</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Marital status shall not be the sole or determinative factor of a person’s domicile.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-211"><akn:num>Section 211</akn:num><akn:heading>Official acts and resolutions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The acts and resolutions printed or reproduced under 29 V.S.A. § 1115 shall be taken to be the laws and resolutions of the session of the General Assembly at which they were passed, unless the original act and legislative records show otherwise, in which case the original act and legislative records pertaining thereto shall control.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-212"><akn:num>Section 212</akn:num><akn:heading>Effective date of laws</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Laws enacted by the General Assembly shall take effect on July 1 next following the date of their passage, unless it is otherwise specifically provided.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-213"><akn:num>Section 213</akn:num><akn:heading>Pending suits unaffected</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>No act of the General Assembly shall affect a suit begun or pending at the time of its passage, except acts regulating practice in court, relating to the competency of witnesses, or relating to amendments of process or pleadings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-214"><akn:num>Section 214</akn:num><akn:heading>Effect of amendment or repeal</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-214_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The amendment or repeal of an act or of a provision of the Vermont Statutes Annotated shall not revive an act or statutory provision which has been repealed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-214_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The amendment or repeal of an act or statutory provision, except as provided in subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-214_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, shall not:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-214_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>affect the operation of the act or provision prior to the effective date of the amendment or repeal thereof;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-214_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>affect any right, privilege, obligation, or liability acquired, accrued, or incurred prior to the effective date of the amendment or repeal;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-214_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>affect any violation of the act or provision amended or repealed, or any penalty or forfeiture incurred thereunder, prior to the effective date of the amendment or repeal;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-214_subsec-c_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>affect any suit, remedy, or proceeding to enforce or give effect to any right, privilege, obligation, or liability acquired, incurred, or accrued under the amended or repealed provision prior to the effective date of the amendment or repeal; and the suit, remedy, or proceeding may be instituted, prosecuted, or continued as if the act or provision had not been repealed or amended.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-214_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If the penalty or punishment for any offense is reduced by the amendment of an act or statutory provision, the same shall be imposed in accordance with the act or provision as amended unless imposed prior to the date of the amendment.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-3_section-215"><akn:num>Section 215</akn:num><akn:heading>Severability of provisions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The provisions of any act are severable.  If any provision of an act is invalid, or if any application thereof to any person or circumstance is invalid, the invalidity shall not affect other provisions or applications which can be given effect without the invalid provision or application.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-5"><akn:num>Chapter 5</akn:num><akn:heading>Common Law; General Rights</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-271"><akn:num>Section 271</akn:num><akn:heading>Common law adopted</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>So much of the common law of England as is applicable to the local situation and circumstances and is not repugnant to the constitution or laws shall be laws in this State and courts shall take notice thereof and govern themselves accordingly.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-272"><akn:num>Section 272</akn:num><akn:heading>Equality of privilege</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>In cases proper for the cognizance of the civil authority and the courts of judicature in this State, citizens of the United States shall be equally entitled to the privileges of law and justice with citizens of this State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-273"><akn:num>Section 273</akn:num><akn:heading>Eligibility to hold office</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A person shall not be debarred on account of sex from holding any office or position of trust or responsibility under the State, including U.S. Senator and Representative to Congress or any county, town, city, village, town school district, or incorporated fire, lighting, or school district office.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-310"><akn:num>Section 310</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-310_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>no other business of the public body is discussed or conducted; and
(ii) such a communication that results in written or recorded information shall be available for inspection and copying under the Public Records Act as set forth in chapter 5, subchapter 3 of this title.
(C) “Meeting” shall not mean occasions when a quorum of a public body attends social gatherings, conventions, conferences, training programs, press conferences, media events, or otherwise gathers, provided that the public body does not discuss specific business of the public body that, at the time of the exchange, the participating members expect to be business of the public body at a later time.
(D) “Meeting” shall not mean a gathering of a quorum of a public body at a duly warned meeting of another public body, provided that the attending public body does not take action on its business.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-310_subsec-i_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Public body” means any board, council, or commission of the State or one or more of its political subdivisions, any board, council, or commission of any agency, authority, or instrumentality of the State or one or more of its political subdivisions, or any committee of any of the foregoing boards, councils, or commissions, except that “public body” does not include councils or similar groups established by the Governor for the sole purpose of advising the Governor with respect to policy.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-310_subsec-i_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Publicly announced” means that notice is given to an editor, publisher, or news director of a newspaper or radio station serving the area of the State in which the public body has jurisdiction, and to any person who has requested under subdivision 312</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-310_subsec-i_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title to be notified of special meetings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-310_subsec-i_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Quasi-judicial proceeding” means a proceeding which is:
(A) a contested case under the Vermont Administrative Procedure Act; or
(B) a case in which the legal rights of one or more persons who are granted party status are adjudicated, which is conducted in such a way that all parties have opportunity to present evidence and to cross-examine witnesses presented by other parties, which results in a written decision, and the result of which is appealable by a party to a higher authority.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-311"><akn:num>Section 311</akn:num><akn:heading>Declaration of public policy; short title</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-311_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In enacting this subchapter, the legislature finds and declares that public commissions, boards, and councils and other public agencies in this State exist to aid in the conduct of the people’s business and are accountable to them pursuant to Chapter I, Article VI of the Vermont Constitution.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-311_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>This subchapter may be known and cited as the Vermont Open Meeting Law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312"><akn:num>Section 312</akn:num><akn:heading>Right to attend meetings of public agencies</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All meetings of a public body are declared to be open to the public at all times, except as provided in section 313 of this title. No resolution, rule, regulation, appointment, or formal action shall be considered binding except as taken or made at such open meeting, except as provided under subdivision 313</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title. A meeting of a public body is subject to the public accommodation requirements of 9 V.S.A. chapter 139. A public body shall electronically record all public hearings held to provide a forum for public comment on a proposed rule, pursuant to 3 V.S.A. § 840. The public shall have access to copies of such electronic recordings as described in section 316 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Participation in meetings through electronic or other means.
(A) As long as the requirements of this subchapter are met, one or more of the members of a public body may attend a regular, special, or emergency meeting by electronic or other means without being physically present at a designated meeting location.
(B) If one or more members attend a meeting by electronic or other means, such members may fully participate in discussing the business of the public body and voting to take an action, but any vote of the public body that is not unanimous shall be taken by roll call.
(C) Each member who attends a meeting without being physically present at a designated meeting location shall:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>identify himself or herself when the meeting is convened; and
(ii) be able to hear the conduct of the meeting and be heard throughout the meeting.
(D) If a quorum or more of the members of a public body attend a meeting without being physically present at a designated meeting location, the agenda required under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section shall designate at least one physical location where a member of the public can attend and participate in the meeting. At least one member of the public body, or at least one staff or designee of the public body, shall be physically present at each designated meeting location.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Minutes shall be taken of all meetings of public bodies. The minutes shall cover all topics and motions that arise at the meeting and give a true indication of the business of the meeting. Minutes shall include at least the following minimal information:
(A) all members of the public body present;
(B) all other active participants in the meeting;
(C) all motions, proposals, and resolutions made, offered, and considered, and what disposition is made of same; and
(D) the results of any votes, with a record of the individual vote of each member if a roll call is taken.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Minutes of all public meetings shall be matters of public record, shall be kept by the clerk or secretary of the public body, and shall be available for inspection by any person and for purchase of copies at cost upon request after five calendar days from the date of any meeting. Meeting minutes shall be posted no later than five calendar days from the date of the meeting to a website, if one exists, that the public body maintains or has designated as the official website of the body. Except for draft minutes that have been substituted with updated minutes, posted minutes shall not be removed from the website sooner than one year from the date of the meeting for which the minutes were taken.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The time and place of all regular meetings subject to this section shall be clearly designated by statute, charter, regulation, ordinance, bylaw, resolution, or other determining authority of the public body, and this information shall be available to any person upon request. The time and place of all public hearings and meetings scheduled by all Executive Branch State agencies, departments, boards, or commissions shall be available to the public as required under 3 V.S.A. § 2222</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The time, place, and purpose of a special meeting subject to this section shall be publicly announced at least 24 hours before the meeting. Municipal public bodies shall post notices of special meetings in or near the municipal clerk’s office and in at least two other designated public places in the municipality, at least 24 hours before the meeting. In addition, notice shall be given, either orally or in writing, to each member of the public body at least 24 hours before the meeting, except that a member may waive notice of a special meeting.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Emergency meetings may be held without public announcement, without posting of notices, and without 24-hour notice to members, provided some public notice thereof is given as soon as possible before any such meeting. Emergency meetings may be held only when necessary to respond to an unforeseen occurrence or condition requiring immediate attention by the public body.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-c_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any adjourned meeting shall be considered a new meeting, unless the time and place for the adjourned meeting is announced before the meeting adjourns.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-c_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A person may request in writing that a public body notify the person of special meetings of the public body. The request shall apply only to the calendar year in which it is made, unless made in December, in which case it shall apply also to the following year.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>At least 48 hours prior to a regular meeting, and at least 24 hours prior to a special meeting, a meeting agenda shall be:
(A) posted to a website, if one exists, that the public body maintains or designates as the official website of the body; and
(B) in the case of a municipal public body, posted in or near the municipal office and in at least two other designated public places in the municipality.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A meeting agenda shall be made available to a person prior to the meeting upon specific request.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-d_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) Any addition to or deletion from the agenda shall be made as the first act of business at the meeting.
(B) Any other adjustment to the agenda may be made at any time during the meeting.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Nothing in this section or in section 313 of this title shall be construed as extending to the Judicial Branch of the Government of Vermont or of any part of the same or to the Public Utility Commission; nor shall it extend to the deliberations of any public body in connection with a quasi-judicial proceeding; nor shall anything in this section be construed to require the making public of any proceedings, records, or acts which are specifically made confidential by the laws of the United States of America or of this State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A written decision issued by a public body in connection with a quasi-judicial proceeding need not be adopted at an open meeting if the decision will be a public record.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The provisions of this subchapter shall not apply to site inspections for the purpose of assessing damage or making tax assessments or abatements, clerical work, or work assignments of staff or other personnel. Routine, day-to-day administrative matters that do not require action by the public body may be conducted outside a duly warned meeting, provided that no money is appropriated, expended, or encumbered.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-h"><akn:num>(h)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>At an open meeting, the public shall be given a reasonable opportunity to express its opinion on matters considered by the public body during the meeting, as long as order is maintained. Public comment shall be subject to reasonable rules established by the chairperson. This subsection shall not apply to quasi-judicial proceedings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit the Parole Board from meeting at correctional facilities, with attendance at the meeting subject to rules regarding access and security established by the superintendent of the facility.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a"><akn:num>Section 312a</akn:num><akn:heading>Meetings of public bodies; state of emergency</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>As used in this section:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Affected public body” means a public body:
(A) whose regular meeting location is located in an area affected by a hazard; and
(B) that cannot meet in a designated physical meeting location due to a declared state of emergency pursuant to 20 V.S.A. chapter 1.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Hazard” means an “all-hazards” as defined in 20 V.S.A. § 2(1).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notwithstanding subdivisions 312</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title, during a declared state of emergency under 20 V.S.A. chapter 1:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A quorum or more of an affected public body may attend a regular, special, or emergency meeting by electronic or other means without designating a physical meeting location where the public may attend.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The members and staff of an affected public body shall not be required to be physically present at a designated meeting location.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An affected public body of a municipality may post any meeting agenda or notice of a special meeting in two publicly accessible designated electronic locations in lieu of the two designated public places in the municipality, or in a combination of a designated electronic location and a designated public place.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When an affected public body meets electronically under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, the affected public body shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>use technology that permits the attendance and participation of the public through electronic or other means;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>allow the public to access the meeting by telephone; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>post information that enables the public to directly access and participate in meetings electronically and shall include this information in the published agenda for each meeting.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Unless unusual circumstances make it impossible for them to do so, the legislative body of each municipality and each school board shall record any meetings held pursuant to this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An affected public body of a municipality shall continue to post notices and agendas in or near the municipal clerk’s office pursuant to subdivision 312</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-312a_subsec-e_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title and shall provide a copy of each notice or agenda to the newspapers of general circulation for the municipality.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313"><akn:num>Section 313</akn:num><akn:heading>Executive sessions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>No public body may hold an executive session from which the public is excluded, except by the affirmative vote of two-thirds of its members present in the case of any public body of State government or of a majority of its members present in the case of any public body of a municipality or other political subdivision. A motion to go into executive session shall indicate the nature of the business of the executive session, and no other matter may be considered in the executive session. Such vote shall be taken in the course of an open meeting and the result of the vote recorded in the minutes. No formal or binding action shall be taken in executive session except for actions relating to the securing of real estate options under subdivision</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection. Minutes of an executive session need not be taken, but if they are, the minutes shall, notwithstanding subsection 312</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title, be exempt from public copying and inspection under the Public Records Act. A public body may not hold an executive session except to consider one or more of the following:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>after making a specific finding that premature general public knowledge would clearly place the public body or a person involved at a substantial disadvantage:
(A) contracts;
(B) labor relations agreements with employees;
(C) arbitration or mediation;
(D) grievances, other than tax grievances;
(E) pending or probable civil litigation or a prosecution, to which the public body is or may be a party;
(F) confidential attorney-client communications made for the purpose of providing professional legal services to the body;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the negotiating or securing of real estate purchase or lease options;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the appointment or employment or evaluation of a public officer or employee, provided that the public body shall make a final decision to hire or appoint a public officer or employee in an open meeting and shall explain the reasons for its final decision during the open meeting;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a disciplinary or dismissal action against a public officer or employee; but nothing in this subsection shall be construed to impair the right of such officer or employee to a public hearing if formal charges are brought;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313_subsec-b_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a clear and imminent peril to the public safety;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313_subsec-b_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>records exempt from the access to public records provisions of section 316 of this title; provided, however, that discussion of the exempt record shall not itself permit an extension of the executive session to the general subject to which the record pertains;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313_subsec-b_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the academic records or suspension or discipline of students;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313_subsec-b_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>testimony from a person in a parole proceeding conducted by the Parole Board if public disclosure of the identity of the person could result in physical or other harm to the person;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313_subsec-b_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>information relating to a pharmaceutical rebate or to supplemental rebate agreements, which is protected from disclosure by federal law or the terms and conditions required by the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services as a condition of rebate authorization under the Medicaid program, considered pursuant to 33 V.S.A. §§ 1998</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>and 2002</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313_subsec-b_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>security or emergency response measures, the disclosure of which could jeopardize public safety.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Attendance in executive session shall be limited to members of the public body, and, in the discretion of the public body, its staff, clerical assistants and legal counsel, and persons who are subjects of the discussion or whose information is needed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-313_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Senate and House of Representatives, in exercising the power to make their own rules conferred by Chapter II of the Vermont Constitution, shall be governed by the provisions of this section in regulating the admission of the public as provided in Chapter II, § 8 of the Constitution.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314"><akn:num>Section 314</akn:num><akn:heading>Penalty and enforcement</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A person who is a member of a public body and who knowingly and intentionally violates the provisions of this subchapter, a person who knowingly and intentionally violates the provisions of this subchapter on behalf or at the behest of a public body, or a person who knowingly and intentionally participates in the wrongful exclusion of any person or persons from any meeting subject to this subchapter shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and shall be fined not more than $500.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Prior to instituting an action under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, the Attorney General or any person aggrieved by a violation of the provisions of this subchapter shall provide the public body written notice that alleges a specific violation of this subchapter and requests a specific cure of such violation. The public body will not be liable for attorney’s fees and litigation costs under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section if it cures in fact a violation of this subchapter in accordance with the requirements of this subsection.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Upon receipt of the written notice of alleged violation, the public body shall respond publicly to the alleged violation within 10 calendar days by:
(A) acknowledging the violation of this subchapter and stating an intent to cure the violation within 14 calendar days; or
(B) stating that the public body has determined that no violation has occurred and that no cure is necessary.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-d_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Failure of a public body to respond to a written notice of alleged violation within 10 calendar days shall be treated as a denial of the violation for purposes of enforcement of the requirements of this subchapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-d_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Within 14 calendar days after a public body acknowledges a violation under subdivision (2)(A) of this subsection, the public body shall cure the violation at an open meeting by:
(A) either ratifying, or declaring as void, any action taken at or resulting from:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a meeting that was not noticed in accordance with subsection 312</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title; or
(ii) a meeting that a person or the public was wrongfully excluded from attending; or
(iii) an executive session or portion thereof not authorized under subdivisions 313</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-c_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title; and
(B) adopting specific measures that actually prevent future violations.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Following an acknowledgment or denial of a violation and, if applicable, following expiration of the 14-calendar-day cure period for public bodies acknowledging a violation, the Attorney General or any person aggrieved by a violation of the provisions of this subchapter may bring an action in the Civil Division of the Superior Court in the county in which the violation has taken place for appropriate injunctive relief or for a declaratory judgment. An action may be brought under this section no later than one year after the meeting at which the alleged violation occurred or to which the alleged violation relates. Except as to cases the court considers of greater importance, proceedings before the Civil Division of the Superior Court, as authorized by this section and appeals therefrom, take precedence on the docket over all cases and shall be assigned for hearing and trial or for argument at the earliest practicable date and expedited in every way.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The court shall assess against a public body found to have violated the requirements of this subchapter reasonable attorney’s fees and other litigation costs reasonably incurred in any case under this subchapter in which the complainant has substantially prevailed, unless the court finds that:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) the public body had a reasonable basis in fact and law for its position; and
(B) the public body acted in good faith. In determining whether a public body acted in good faith, the court shall consider, among other factors, whether the public body responded to a notice of an alleged violation of this subchapter in a timely manner under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section; or</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the public body cured the violation in accordance with subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-314_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-315"><akn:num>Section 315</akn:num><akn:heading>Statement of policy; short title</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-315_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>It is the policy of this subchapter to provide for free and open examination of records consistent with Chapter I, Article 6 of the Vermont Constitution. Officers of government are trustees and servants of the people and it is in the public interest to enable any person to review and criticize their decisions even though such examination may cause inconvenience or embarrassment. All people, however, have a right to privacy in their personal and economic pursuits, which ought to be protected unless specific information is needed to review the action of a governmental officer. Consistent with these principles, the General Assembly hereby declares that certain public records shall be made available to any person as hereinafter provided. To that end, the provisions of this subchapter shall be liberally construed to implement this policy, and the burden of proof shall be on the public agency to sustain its action.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-315_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The General Assembly finds that public records are essential to the administration of State and local government. Public records contain information that allows government programs to function, provides officials with a basis for making decisions, and ensures continuity with past operations. Public records document the legal responsibilities of government, help protect the rights of citizens, and provide citizens a means of monitoring government programs and measuring the performance of public officials. Public records provide documentation for the functioning of government and for the retrospective analysis of the development of Vermont government and the impact of programs on citizens.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-315_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>This subchapter may be known and cited as the Public Records Act or the PRA.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316"><akn:num>Section 316</akn:num><akn:heading>Access to public records and documents</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any person may inspect or copy any public record of a public agency, as follows:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For any agency, board, department, commission, committee, branch, instrumentality, or authority of the State, a person may inspect a public record on any day other than a Saturday, Sunday, or a legal holiday, between the hours of nine o’clock and 12 o’clock in the forenoon and between one o’clock and four o’clock in the afternoon.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For any agency, board, committee, department, instrumentality, commission, or authority of a political subdivision of the State, a person may inspect a public record during customary business hours.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If copying equipment maintained for use by a public agency is used by the agency to copy the public record or document requested, the agency may charge and collect from the person requesting the copy the actual cost of providing the copy. The agency may also charge and collect from the person making the request, the costs associated with mailing or transmitting the record by facsimile or other electronic means. Nothing in this section shall exempt any person from paying fees otherwise established by law for obtaining copies of public records or documents, but if such fee is established for the copy, no additional costs or fees shall be charged.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Unless otherwise provided by law, in the following instances an agency may also charge and collect the cost of staff time associated with complying with a request for a copy of a public record:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the time directly involved in complying with the request exceeds 30 minutes;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the agency agrees to create a public record; or</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the agency agrees to provide the public record in a nonstandard format and the time directly involved in complying with the request exceeds 30 minutes. The agency may require that requests subject to staff time charges under this subsection be made in writing and that all charges be paid, in whole or in part, prior to delivery of the copies. Upon request, the agency shall provide an estimate of the charge.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of State, after consultation with the Secretary of Administration, shall establish the actual cost of providing a copy of a public record that may be charged by State agencies. The Secretary shall also establish the amount that may be charged for staff time, when such a charge is authorized under this section. To determine “actual cost,” the Secretary shall consider the following only: the cost of the paper or the electronic media onto which a public record is copied, a prorated amount for maintenance and replacement of the machine or equipment used to copy the record, and any utility charges directly associated with copying a record. The Secretary of State shall adopt, by rule, a uniform schedule of public record charges for State agencies.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>After public hearing, the legislative body of a political subdivision shall establish actual cost charges for copies of public records. The legislative body shall also establish the amount that may be charged for staff time, when such a charge is authorized under this section. To determine actual cost charges, the legislative body shall use the same factors used by the Secretary of State. If a legislative body fails to establish a uniform schedule of charges, the charges for that political subdivision shall be the uniform schedule of charges established by the Secretary of State until the local legislative body establishes such a schedule. A schedule of public records charges shall be posted in prominent locations in the town offices.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>State agencies shall provide receipts for all monies received under this section. Notwithstanding any provision of law to the contrary, a State agency may retain monies collected under this section to the extent such charges represent the actual cost incurred to provide copies under this subchapter. Amounts collected by a State agency under this section for the cost of staff time associated with providing copies shall be deposited in the General Fund, unless another disposition or use of revenues received by that agency is specifically authorized by law. Charges collected under this section shall be deposited in the agency’s operating account or the General Fund, as appropriate, on a monthly basis or whenever the amount totals $100.00, whichever occurs first.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A public agency having the equipment necessary to copy its public records shall utilize its equipment to produce copies. If the public agency does not have such equipment, nothing in this section shall be construed to require the public agency to provide or arrange for copying service, to use or permit the use of copying equipment other than its own, to permit operation of its copying equipment by other than its own personnel, to permit removal of the public record by the requesting person for purposes of copying, or to make its own personnel available for making handwritten or typed copies of the public record or document requested.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316_subsec-h"><akn:num>(h)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Standard formats for copies of public records shall be as follows: for copies in paper form, a photocopy of a paper public record or a hard copy print-out of a public record maintained in electronic form; for copies in electronic form, the format in which the record is maintained. Any format other than the formats described in this subsection is a nonstandard format.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If an agency maintains public records in an electronic format, nonexempt public records shall be available for copying in either the standard electronic format or the standard paper format, as designated by the party requesting the records. If requested by the party requesting the records, an agency may, but is not required to, provide copies of public records in a nonstandard format, create a public record, or convert paper public records to electronic format.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316_subsec-j"><akn:num>(j)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A public agency may make reasonable rules to prevent disruption of operations, to preserve the security of public records or documents, and to protect them from damage.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-316_subsec-k"><akn:num>(k)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Information concerning facilities and sites for the treatment, storage, and disposal of hazardous waste shall be made available to the public under this subchapter in substantially the same manner and to the same degree as such information is made available under the Resource Conservation and Recovery Act of 1976, as amended, 42 U.S.C. chapter 82, subchapter 3, and the Federal Freedom of Information Act, 5 U.S.C. section 552 et seq. In the event of a conflict between the provisions of this subchapter and the cited federal laws, federal law shall govern.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317"><akn:num>Section 317</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions; public agency; public records and documents; exemptions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>As used in this subchapter:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Business day” means a day that a public agency is open to provide services.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Public agency” or “agency” means any agency, board, department, commission, committee, branch, instrumentality, or authority of the State or any agency, board, committee, department, branch, instrumentality, commission, or authority of any political subdivision of the State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>As used in this subchapter, “public record” or “public document” means any written or recorded information, regardless of physical form or characteristics, which is produced or acquired in the course of public agency business. Individual salaries and benefits of and salary schedules relating to elected or appointed officials and employees of public agencies shall not be exempt from public inspection and copying.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The following public records are exempt from public inspection and copying:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records that by law are designated confidential or by a similar term.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records that by law may only be disclosed to specifically designated persons.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records that, if made public pursuant to this subchapter, would cause the custodian to violate duly adopted standards of ethics or conduct for any profession regulated by the State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-c_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records that, if made public pursuant to this subchapter, would cause the custodian to violate any statutory or common law privilege other than the common law deliberative process privilege as it applies to the General Assembly and the Executive Branch agencies of the State of Vermont.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-c_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) Records dealing with the detection and investigation of crime, but only to the extent that the production of such records:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>could reasonably be expected to interfere with enforcement proceedings;
(ii) would deprive a person of a right to a fair trial or an impartial adjudication;
(iii) could reasonably be expected to constitute an unwarranted invasion of personal privacy;
(iv) could reasonably be expected to disclose the identity of a confidential source, including a state, local, or foreign agency or authority or any private institution that furnished information on a confidential basis, and, in the case of a record or information compiled by criminal law enforcement authority in the course of a criminal investigation or by an agency conducting a lawful national security intelligence investigation, information furnished by a confidential source;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v"><akn:num>(v)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>would disclose techniques and procedures for law enforcement investigations or prosecutions, or would disclose guidelines for law enforcement investigations or prosecution if such disclosure could reasonably be expected to risk circumvention of the law;
(vi) could reasonably be expected to endanger the life or physical safety of any individual.
(B) Notwithstanding subdivision (A) of this subdivision (5), records relating to management and direction of a law enforcement agency; records reflecting the initial arrest of a person, including any ticket, citation, or complaint issued for a traffic violation, as that term is defined in 23 V.S.A. § 2302; and records reflecting the charge of a person shall be public.
(C) It is the intent of the General Assembly that in construing subdivision (A) of this subdivision (5), the courts of this State will be guided by the construction of similar terms contained in 5 U.S.C. § 552</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(Freedom of Information Act) by the courts of the United States.
(D) It is the intent of the General Assembly that, consistent with the manner in which courts have interpreted subdivision (A) of this subdivision (5), a public agency shall not reveal information that could be used to facilitate the commission of a crime or the identity of a private individual who is a witness to or victim of a crime, unless withholding the identity or information would conceal government wrongdoing. A record shall not be withheld in its entirety because it contains identities or information that have been redacted pursuant to this subdivision.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A tax return and related documents, correspondence, and certain types of substantiating forms that include the same type of information as in the tax return itself filed with or maintained by the Vermont Department of Taxes or submitted by a person to any public agency in connection with agency business.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Personal documents relating to an individual, including information in any files maintained to hire, evaluate, promote, or discipline any employee of a public agency; information in any files relating to personal finances; medical or psychological facts concerning any individual or corporation; provided, however, that all information in personnel files of an individual employee of any public agency shall be made available to that individual employee or his or her designated representative.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Test questions, scoring keys, and other examination instruments or data used to administer a license, employment, or academic examination.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Trade secrets, meaning confidential business records or information, including any formulae, plan, pattern, process, tool, mechanism, compound, procedure, production data, or compilation of information that is not patented, which a commercial concern makes efforts that are reasonable under the circumstances to keep secret, and which gives its user or owner an opportunity to obtain business advantage over competitors who do not know it or use it, except that the disclosures required by 18 V.S.A. § 4632 are not exempt under this subdivision.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Lists of names compiled or obtained by a public agency when disclosure would violate a person’s right to privacy or produce public or private gain; provided, however, that this section does not apply to lists that are by law made available to the public, or to lists of professional or occupational licensees.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Student records, including records of a home study student; provided, however, that such records shall be made available upon request under the provisions of the Federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974, 20 U.S.C. § 1232g, as may be amended.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-12"><akn:num>(12)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records concerning formulation of policy where such would constitute a clearly unwarranted invasion of personal privacy if disclosed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-13"><akn:num>(13)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Information pertaining to the location of real or personal property for public agency purposes prior to public announcement of the project and information pertaining to appraisals or purchase price of real or personal property for public purposes prior to the formal award of contracts thereof.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-14"><akn:num>(14)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records that are relevant to litigation to which the public agency is a party of record, provided all such matters shall be available to the public after ruled discoverable by the court before which the litigation is pending, but in any event upon final termination of the litigation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-15"><akn:num>(15)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records relating specifically to negotiation of contracts, including collective bargaining agreements with public employees.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-16"><akn:num>(16)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any voluntary information provided by an individual, corporation, organization, partnership, association, trustee, estate, or any other entity in the State of Vermont, which has been gathered prior to the enactment of this subchapter, shall not be considered a public document.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-17"><akn:num>(17)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records of interdepartmental and intradepartmental communications in any county, city, town, village, town school district, incorporated school district, union school district, consolidated water district, fire district, or any other political subdivision of the State to the extent that they cover other than primarily factual materials and are preliminary to any determination of policy or action or precede the presentation of the budget at a meeting held in accordance with section 312 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-18"><akn:num>(18)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records of the Office of Internal Investigation of the Department of Public Safety, except as provided in 20 V.S.A. § 1923.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-19"><akn:num>(19)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records relating to the identity of library patrons or the identity of library patrons in regard to library patron registration records and patron transaction records in accordance with 22 V.S.A. chapter 4.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-20"><akn:num>(20)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Information that would reveal the location of archaeological sites and underwater historic properties, except as provided in 22 V.S.A. § 761.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-21"><akn:num>(21)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-22"><akn:num>(22)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-23"><akn:num>(23)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any data, records, or information produced or acquired by or on behalf of faculty, staff, employees, or students of the University of Vermont or the Vermont State Colleges in the conduct of study, research, or creative efforts on medical, scientific, technical, scholarly, or artistic matters, whether such activities are sponsored alone by the institution or in conjunction with a governmental body or private entity, until such data, records, or information are published, disclosed in an issued patent, or publicly released by the institution or its authorized agents. This subdivision applies to, but is not limited to, research notes and laboratory notebooks, lecture notes, manuscripts, creative works, correspondence, research proposals and agreements, methodologies, protocols, and the identities of or any personally identifiable information about participants in research. This subdivision shall not exempt records, other than research protocols, produced or acquired by an institutional animal care and use committee regarding the committee’s compliance with State law or federal law regarding or regulating animal care.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-24"><akn:num>(24)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records of, or internal materials prepared for, the deliberations of any public agency acting in a judicial or quasi-judicial capacity.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-25"><akn:num>(25)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Passwords, access codes, user identifications, security procedures, and similar information, the disclosure of which would threaten the safety of persons or the security of public property.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-26"><akn:num>(26)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Information and records provided to the Department of Financial Regulation by a person for the purposes of having the Department assist that person in resolving a dispute with any person regulated by the Department, and any information or records provided by a person in connection with the dispute.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-27"><akn:num>(27)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Information and records provided to the Department of Public Service or the Public Utility Commission by an individual for the purposes of having the Department or Commission assist that individual in resolving a dispute with a utility regulated by the Department or Commission, or by the utility or any other person in connection with the individual’s dispute.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-28"><akn:num>(28)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records of, and internal materials prepared for, independent external reviews of health care service decisions pursuant to 8 V.S.A. § 4089f and of mental health care service decisions pursuant to 8 V.S.A. § 4089a.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-29"><akn:num>(29)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The records in the custody of the Secretary of State of a participant in the Address Confidentiality Program described in 15 V.S.A. chapter 21, subchapter 3, except as provided in that subchapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-30"><akn:num>(30)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All State-controlled database structures and application code, including the vermontvacation.com website and Travel Planner application, which are known only to certain State departments engaging in marketing activities and which give the State an opportunity to obtain a marketing advantage over any other state, regional, or local governmental or nonprofit quasi-governmental entity, or private sector entity, unless any such State department engaging in marketing activities determines that the license or other voluntary disclosure of such materials is in the State’s best interests.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-31"><akn:num>(31)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records of a registered voter’s month and day of birth, driver’s license or nondriver identification number, telephone number, e-mail address, and the last four digits of his or her Social Security number contained in a voter registration application or the statewide voter checklist established under 17 V.S.A. § 2154 or the failure to register to vote under 17 V.S.A. § 2145a.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-32"><akn:num>(32)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>With respect to publicly owned, managed, or leased structures, and only to the extent that release of information contained in the record would present a substantial likelihood of jeopardizing the safety of persons or the security of public property, final building plans, and as-built plans, including drafts of security systems within a facility, that depict the internal layout and structural elements of buildings, facilities, infrastructures, systems, or other structures owned, operated, or leased by an agency before, on, or after the effective date of this provision; emergency evacuation, escape, or other emergency response plans that have not been published for public use; and vulnerability assessments, operation, and security manuals, plans, and security codes. For purposes of this subdivision, “system” shall include electrical, heating, ventilation, air conditioning, telecommunication, elevator, and security systems. Information made exempt by this subdivision may be disclosed to another governmental entity if disclosure is necessary for the receiving entity to perform its duties and responsibilities; to a licensed architect, engineer, or contractor who is bidding on or performing work on or related to buildings, facilities, infrastructures, systems, or other structures owned, operated, or leased by the State. The entities or persons receiving such information shall maintain the exempt status of the information. Such information may also be disclosed by order of a court of competent jurisdiction, which may impose protective conditions on the release of such information as it deems appropriate. Nothing in this subdivision shall preclude or limit the right of the General Assembly or its committees to examine such information in carrying out its responsibilities or to subpoena such information. In exercising the exemption set forth in this subdivision and denying access to information requested, the custodian of the information shall articulate the grounds for the</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-33"><akn:num>(33)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The account numbers for bank, debit, charge, and credit cards held by an agency or its employees on behalf of the agency.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-34"><akn:num>(34)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Affidavits of income and assets as provided in 15 V.S.A. § 662 and Rule 4 of the Vermont Rules for Family Proceedings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-35"><akn:num>(35)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-36"><akn:num>(36)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Anti-fraud plans and summaries submitted for the purposes of complying with 8 V.S.A. § 4750.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-37"><akn:num>(37)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records provided to the Department of Health pursuant to the Patient Safety Surveillance and Improvement System established by 18 V.S.A. chapter 43a.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-38"><akn:num>(38)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records that include prescription information containing data that could be used to identify a prescriber, except that the records shall be made available upon request for medical research, consistent with and for purposes expressed in 18 V.S.A. § 4622 or 9410, 18 V.S.A. chapter 84 or 84A, and for other law enforcement activities.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-39"><akn:num>(39)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records held by the Agency of Human Services or the Department of Financial Regulation, which include prescription information containing patient-identifiable data, that could be used to identify a patient.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-40"><akn:num>(40)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records of genealogy provided in an application or in support of an application for tribal recognition pursuant to chapter 23 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-v_subsec-41"><akn:num>(41)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Documents reviewed by the Victims Compensation Board for purposes of approving an application for compensation pursuant to 13 V.S.A. chapter 167, except as provided by 13 V.S.A. §§ 5358a</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>and 7043</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-b_subsec-42"><akn:num>(42)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Except as otherwise provided by law, information that could be used to identify a complainant who alleges that a public agency, a public employee or official, or a person providing goods or services to a public agency under contract has engaged in a violation of law, or in waste, fraud, or abuse of authority, or in an act creating a threat to health or safety, unless the complainant consents to disclosure of his or her identity.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-b_subsec-43"><akn:num>(43)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records relating to a regulated utility’s cybersecurity program, assessments, and plans, including all reports, summaries, compilations, analyses, notes, or other cybersecurity information.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>On or before December 1, 2015, the Office of Legislative Counsel shall compile lists of all Public Records Act exemptions found in the Vermont Statutes Annotated, one of which shall be arranged by subject area, and the other in order by title and section number.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>On or before December 1, 2019, the Office of Legislative Counsel shall compile a list arranged in order by title and section number of all Public Records Act exemptions found in the Vermont Statutes Annotated that are repealed or are narrowed in scope on or after January 1, 2019. The list shall indicate:
(A) the effective date of the repeal or narrowing in scope of the exemption; and
(B) whether or not records produced or acquired during the period of applicability of the repealed or narrowed exemption are to remain exempt following the repeal or narrowing in scope.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-d_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Office of Legislative Counsel shall update the lists required under subdivisions</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection no less often than every two years. In compiling and updating these lists, the Office of Legislative Counsel shall consult with the Office of Attorney General. The lists and any updates thereto shall be posted in a prominent location on the websites of the General Assembly, the Secretary of State’s Office, the Attorney General’s Office, and the State Library and shall be sent to the Vermont League of Cities and Towns.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-e_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For any exemption to the Public Records Act enacted or substantively amended in legislation introduced in the General Assembly in 2019 or later, in the fifth year after the effective date of the enactment, reenactment, or substantive amendment of the exemption, the exemption shall be repealed on July 1 of that fifth year except if the General Assembly reenacts the exemption prior to July 1 of the fifth year or if the law otherwise requires.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-e_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Legislation that enacts, reenacts, or substantively amends an exemption to the Public Records Act shall explicitly provide for its repeal on July 1 of the fifth year after the effective date of the exemption unless the legislation specifically provides otherwise.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Unless otherwise provided by law, a record produced or acquired during the period of applicability of an exemption that is subsequently repealed or narrowed in scope shall, if exempt during that period, remain exempt following the repeal or narrowing in scope of the exemption.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317a"><akn:num>Section 317a</akn:num><akn:heading>Management of public records</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317a_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317a_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Public records in general and archival records in particular should be systematically managed to provide ready access to vital information, to promote the efficient and economical operation of government, and to preserve their legal, administrative, and informational value.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317a_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any public agency may seek services from the Statewide Records and Information Management Program, as defined in 3 V.S.A. § 117</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317a_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>and administered by the Vermont State Archives and Records Administration, to establish, maintain, and implement an active and continuing internal records and information management program for the agency.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-317a_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A custodian of public records shall not destroy, give away, sell, discard, or damage any record or records in his or her charge, unless specifically authorized by law or under a record schedule, as defined in 3 V.S.A. § 117</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318"><akn:num>Section 318</akn:num><akn:heading>Procedure</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>As used in this section, “promptly” means immediately, with little or no delay, and, unless otherwise provided in this section, not more than three business days:
(A) from receipt of a request under this subchapter; or
(B) in the case of a reversal on appeal by a head of the agency pursuant to subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, from the date of the determination on appeal.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A custodian or head of the agency who fails to comply with the applicable time limit provisions of this section shall be deemed to have denied the request or the appeal upon the expiration of the time limit.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Upon request, the custodian of a public record shall promptly produce the record for inspection or a copy of the record, except that:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If the record is in active use or in storage and therefore not available for use at the time the person asks to examine it, the custodian shall promptly certify this fact in writing to the applicant and, in the certification, set a date and hour within one calendar week of the request when the record will be available.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If the custodian considers the record to be exempt from inspection and copying under the provisions of this subchapter, the custodian shall promptly so certify in writing. The certification shall:
(A) identify the records withheld;
(B) include the asserted statutory basis for denial and a brief statement of the reasons and supporting facts for denial;
(C) provide the names and titles or positions of each person responsible for denial of the request; and
(D) notify the person of his or her right to appeal to the head of the agency any adverse determination.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If a record does not exist, the custodian shall promptly certify in writing that the record does not exist under the name given to the custodian by the applicant or by any other name known to the custodian.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-b_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In unusual circumstances as herein specified, the time limits prescribed in this section may be extended by written notice to the person making the request setting forth the reasons for the extension and the date on which a determination is expected to be dispatched. No such notice shall specify a date that would result in an extension for more than ten business days from receipt of the request or, in the case of a reversal on appeal by a head of the agency pursuant to subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, from the date of the determination on appeal. As used in this subdivision, “unusual circumstances” means to the extent reasonably necessary to the proper processing of the particular request:
(A) the need to search for and collect the requested records from field facilities or other establishments that are separate from the office processing the request;
(B) the need to search for, collect, and appropriately examine a voluminous amount of separate and distinct records that are demanded in a single request; or
(C) the need for consultation, which shall be conducted with all practicable speed, with another agency having a substantial interest in the determination of the request or among two or more components of the agency having substantial subject matter interest therein, or with the Attorney General.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any denial of access by the custodian of a public record may be appealed to the head of the agency. The head of the agency shall make a written determination on an appeal within five business days after the receipt of the appeal.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If the head of the agency upholds the denial of a request for records, in whole or in part, the written determination shall include:
(A) the asserted statutory basis for upholding the denial;
(B) a brief statement of the reasons and supporting facts for upholding the denial; and
(C) notification of the provisions for judicial review of the determination under section 319 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If the head of the agency reverses the denial of a request for records, the records shall be promptly made available to the person making the request.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In responding to a request to inspect or copy a record under this subchapter, a public agency shall consult with the person making the request in order to clarify the request or to obtain additional information that will assist the public agency in responding to the request and, when authorized by this subchapter, in facilitating production of the requested record for inspection or copying. In unusual circumstances, as that term is defined in subdivision </akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-d_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, a public agency may request that a person seeking a voluminous amount of separate and distinct records narrow the scope of a public records request.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A public agency shall not withhold any record in its entirety on the basis that it contains some exempt content if the record is otherwise subject to disclosure; instead, the public agency shall redact the information it considers to be exempt and produce the record accompanied by an explanation of the basis for denial of the redacted information.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If a person making the request has a disability that requires accommodation to gain equal access to the public record sought, the person shall notify the public agency of the type of accommodation requested. The public agency shall give primary consideration to the accommodation choice expressed by the requestor, but may propose an alternative accommodation so long as it achieves equal access. The public agency shall provide accommodation to the person making the request unless the agency can demonstrate that accommodation would result in a fundamental alteration in the nature of its service, programs, activities, or in undue financial and administrative burden.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of State shall provide municipal public agencies and members of the public information and advice regarding the requirements of the Public Records Act and may utilize informational websites, toll-free telephone numbers, or other methods to provide such information and advice.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-h"><akn:num>(h)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The head of a State agency or department shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-h_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>designate the agency’s or department’s records officer described in 3 V.S.A. § 218, or shall designate some other person, to be accountable for overseeing the processing of requests for public records received by the agency or department in accordance with this section; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-h_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>post on the agency’s or department’s website the name and contact information of the person designated under subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318_subsec-h_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318a"><akn:num>Section 318a</akn:num><akn:heading>Executive Branch Agency Public Records Request System</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318a_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of Administration shall maintain and update the Public Records Request System established pursuant to 2006 Acts and Resolves No. 132, Sec. 3 and 2011 Acts and Resolves No. 59, Sec. 13 with the information furnished under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318a_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section and post System information on the website of the Agency of Administration.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318a_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All public agencies of the Executive Branch of the State:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318a_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>that receive a written request to inspect or copy a record under this subchapter shall catalogue the request in the Public Records Request System established and maintained by the Secretary of Administration by furnishing the following information:
(A) the date the request was received;
(B) the agency that received the request;
(C) the person that made the request, including a contact name;
(D) the status of the request, including whether the request was fulfilled in whole, fulfilled in part, or denied;
(E) if the request was fulfilled in part or denied, the exemption or other grounds asserted as the basis for partial fulfillment or denial;
(F) the estimated hours necessary to respond to the request;
(G) the date the agency closed the request; and
(H) the elapsed time between receipt of the request and the date the agency closed the request; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-318a_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>shall post in a conspicuous location on their respective websites a link to the location on the Agency of Administration’s website where Public Records Request System information is maintained.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-319"><akn:num>Section 319</akn:num><akn:heading>Enforcement</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-319_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any person aggrieved by the denial of a request for public records under this subchapter may apply to the Civil Division of the Superior Court in the county in which the complainant resides, or has his or her personal place of business, or in which the public records are situated, or in the Civil Division of the Superior Court of Washington County, to enjoin the public agency from withholding agency records and to order the production of any agency records improperly withheld from the complainant. In such a case, the court shall determine the matter de novo, and may examine the contents of such agency records in camera to determine whether such records or any part thereof shall be withheld under any of the exemptions set forth in section 317 of this title, and the burden of proof shall be on the public agency to sustain its action.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-319_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Except as to cases the court considers of greater importance, proceedings before the Civil Division of the Superior Court, as authorized by this section, and appeals there from, take precedence on the docket over all cases and shall be assigned for hearing and trial or for argument at the earliest practicable date and expedited in every way.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-319_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If the public agency can show the court that exceptional circumstances exist and that the agency is exercising due diligence in responding to the request, the court may retain jurisdiction and allow the agency additional time to complete its review of the records.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-319_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-319_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Except as provided in subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-319_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection, the court shall assess against the public agency reasonable attorney’s fees and other litigation costs reasonably incurred in any case under this section in which the complainant has substantially prevailed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-319_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The court may, in its discretion, assess against a public agency reasonable attorney’s fees and other litigation costs reasonably incurred in a case under this section in which the complainant has substantially prevailed provided that the public agency, within the time allowed for service of an answer under V.R.C.P. 12</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-319_subsec-d_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The court may assess against the complainant reasonable attorney’s fees and other litigation costs reasonably incurred in any case under this section when the court finds that the complainant has violated V.R.C.P. 11.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-320"><akn:num>Section 320</akn:num><akn:heading>Penalties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-320_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Whenever the court orders the production of any public agency records, improperly withheld from the complainant and assesses against the agency reasonable attorney’s fees and other litigation costs, and the court additionally issues a written finding that the circumstances surrounding the withholding raise questions whether the agency personnel acted arbitrarily or capriciously with respect to the withholding, the Department of Human Resources if applicable to that employee, shall promptly initiate a proceeding to determine whether disciplinary action is warranted against the officer or employee who was primarily responsible for the withholding. The Department, after investigation and consideration of the evidence submitted, shall submit its findings and recommendations to the administrative authority of the agency concerned and shall send copies of the findings and recommendations to the officer or employee or his or her representative. The administrative authority shall take the corrective action that the Department recommends.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-320_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In the event of noncompliance with the order of the court, the Civil Division of the Superior Court may punish for contempt the responsible employee or official, and in the case of a uniformed service, the responsible member.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-320_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A person who willfully destroys, gives away, sells, discards, or damages a public record without having authority to do so shall be fined at least $50.00 but not more than $1,000.00 for each offense.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-331"><akn:num>Section 331</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-331_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Person who is deaf or hard of hearing” means any person who has such difficulty hearing, even with amplification, that he or she cannot rely on hearing for communication.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-331_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Proceeding” means any judicial proceeding, contested case under 3 V.S.A. chapter 25, or other hearing before an administrative agency not included under 3 V.S.A. chapter 25.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-331_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Qualified interpreter” means an interpreter for a person who is deaf or hard of hearing who meets standards of competency established by the national or Vermont Registry of Interpreters for the Deaf as amended, by rule, by the Vermont Commission of the Deaf and Hard of Hearing.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-332"><akn:num>Section 332</akn:num><akn:heading>Right to interpreter; assistive listening equipment</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-332_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any person who is deaf or hard of hearing who is a party or witness in any proceeding shall be entitled to be provided with a qualified interpreter for the duration of the person’s participation in the proceeding.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-332_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any person who is deaf or hard of hearing shall be entitled to be provided with a qualified interpreter upon five working days’ notice that the person has reasonable need to do any of the following:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-332_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>transact business with any State board or agency;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-332_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>participate in any State-sponsored activity, including public hearings, conferences, and public meetings;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-332_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>participate in any official State legislative activities.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-332_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If a person who is deaf or hard of hearing is unable to use or understand sign language, the presiding officer or State board or agency or State legislative official shall, upon five working days’ notice, make available appropriate assistive listening equipment for use during the proceeding or activity.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-333"><akn:num>Section 333</akn:num><akn:heading>Appointment of interpreter</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-333_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The presiding officer in a proceeding shall appoint an interpreter after making a preliminary determination that the interpreter is able to readily communicate with the person who is deaf or hard of hearing, to accurately interpret statements or communications from the person who is deaf or hard of hearing, and to interpret the proceedings to the person who is deaf or hard of hearing.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-333_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The presiding officer shall make findings when appointing an interpreter not designated as a qualified interpreter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-333_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>It shall be a rebuttable presumption that the requirements of this section are met if the interpreter proposed for appointment is a qualified interpreter.  It shall also be a rebuttable presumption that the requirements of this section are not met if the interpreter proposed for appointment is not a qualified interpreter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-334"><akn:num>Section 334</akn:num><akn:heading>Waiver</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>No privilege recognized by law may be deemed waived or made inapplicable by reason that a communication was made through an interpreter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-335"><akn:num>Section 335</akn:num><akn:heading>Compensation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>An interpreter appointed under section 332 of this title is entitled to receive a reasonable fee for services, together with reimbursement of actual and necessary expenses, including travel and lodging expenses.  In civil proceedings, the Court may order that costs of the interpreter be paid by a party, as justice may require, or it may order that the costs be paid by the State.  In criminal proceedings, costs of the interpreter shall be paid by the State.  An interpreter used in connection with administrative proceedings, transacting State business or State-sponsored activities shall be provided at the expense of the agency involved.  An interpreter used in connection with official State legislative activities shall be provided at the expense of the legislature.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-336"><akn:num>Section 336</akn:num><akn:heading>Rules; information; list of interpreters</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-336_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Vermont Commission of the Deaf and Hard of Hearing shall, by rule, establish factors to be considered by the presiding officer under section 333 of this title before appointing an interpreter who is not a qualified interpreter. Such factors shall encourage the widest availability of interpreters in Vermont while at the same time ensuring that the interpreter:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-336_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>is able to communicate readily with the person who is deaf or hard of hearing;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-336_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>is able to interpret accurately statements or communications by the person who is deaf or hard of hearing;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-336_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>is able to interpret the proceedings to the person who is deaf or hard of hearing;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-336_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>shall maintain confidentiality;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-336_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>shall be impartial with respect to the outcome of the proceeding;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-336_subsec-a_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>shall not exert any influence over the person who is deaf or hard of hearing; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-336_subsec-a_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>shall not accept assignments the interpreter does not feel competent to handle.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-336_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Rules established by the Vermont Commission of the Deaf and Hard of Hearing pursuant to subdivision 331</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-336_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title amending the standards of competency established by the national or Vermont Registry of the Deaf shall be limited to the factors set forth in subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-336_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-336_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Vermont Commission of the Deaf and Hard of Hearing shall prepare an explanation of the provisions of this subchapter which shall be distributed to all State agencies and courts.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-336_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Department of Disabilities, Aging, and Independent Living shall maintain a list of qualified interpreters in Vermont and, where such information is available, in surrounding states. The list shall be distributed to all State agencies and courts.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-337"><akn:num>Section 337</akn:num><akn:heading>Review</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-337_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A decision, order, or judgment of a court or administrative agency may be reversed on appeal if the court or agency finds that a person who is deaf or hard of hearing who was a party or a witness in the proceeding was deprived of an opportunity to communicate effectively, and that the deprivation was prejudicial.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-337_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any person denied a qualified interpreter under subsection 332</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-337_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title, may appeal the denial through the administrative appeals process for the agency involved or, where no such administrative appeals process exists, through the Superior Court in the county in which the denial occurred or in Washington Superior Court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-338"><akn:num>Section 338</akn:num><akn:heading>Admissions; confessions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-338_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An admission or confession by a person who is deaf or hard of hearing made to a law enforcement officer or any other person having a prosecutorial function may only be used against the person in a criminal proceeding if:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-338_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The admission or confession was made knowingly, voluntarily, and intelligently and is not subject to alternative interpretations resulting from the person’s habits and patterns of communication.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-338_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The admission or confession, if made during a custodial interrogation, was made after reasonable steps were taken, including the appointment of a qualified interpreter, to ensure that the defendant understood his or her constitutional rights.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-338_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The provisions of subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-338_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section supplement the constitutional rights of the person who is deaf or hard of hearing.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-339"><akn:num>Section 339</akn:num><akn:heading>Communications made to interpreters; prohibition on disclosure</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-339_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An interpreter, whether or not the interpreter is a qualified interpreter, shall not disclose or testify to:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-339_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a communication made by a person to an interpreter acting in his or her capacity as an interpreter for a person who is deaf or hard of hearing or a person with limited English proficiency; or</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-339_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>any information obtained by the interpreter while acting in his or her capacity as an interpreter for a person who is deaf or hard of hearing or a person with limited English proficiency.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-339_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There is no prohibition on disclosure under this section if the services of the interpreter were sought or obtained to enable or aid anyone to commit or plan to commit what the person who is deaf or hard of hearing or the person with limited English proficiency knew or reasonably should have known to be a crime or fraud.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-339_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-339_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>This section shall not be construed to limit or expand the effect of section 334 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-339_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>This section shall not be construed to alter or affect the mandatory reporting requirements of 33 V.S.A. § 4913.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-5_section-339_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>As used in this section, “person with limited English proficiency” means a person who does not speak English as his or her primary language and who has a limited ability to read, write, speak, or understand English.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-7"><akn:num>Chapter 7</akn:num><akn:heading>Legal Holidays; Commemorative Days</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-371"><akn:num>Section 371</akn:num><akn:heading>Legal holidays</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-371_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The following shall be legal holidays:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-371_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>New Year’s Day, January 1;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-371_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Martin Luther King, Jr.’s Birthday, the third Monday in January;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-371_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Presidents’ Day, the third Monday in February;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-371_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Town Meeting Day, the first Tuesday in March;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-371_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Memorial Day, the last Monday in May;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-371_subsec-a_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Independence Day, July 4;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-371_subsec-a_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Bennington Battle Day, August 16;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-371_subsec-a_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Labor Day, the first Monday in September;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-371_subsec-a_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Indigenous Peoples’ Day, the second Monday in October;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-371_subsec-a_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Veterans’ Day, November 11;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-371_subsec-a_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Thanksgiving Day, the fourth Thursday in November;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-371_subsec-a_subsec-12"><akn:num>(12)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Christmas Day, December 25.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-371_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All State departments, agencies and offices shall observe any legal holiday which falls on a Saturday on the preceding Friday and any legal holiday which falls on a Sunday on the following Monday; however, all other conditions of employment related to legal holidays, including decisions such as the closing or opening of State offices and compensation for work performed on such a day, shall be proper matters for collective bargaining pursuant to 3 V.S.A. § 904.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-371_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The provisions of this section shall not affect any collective bargaining agreement in existence on the effective date hereof.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-372"><akn:num>Section 372</akn:num><akn:heading>Arbor Day</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The first Friday in the month of May of each year is hereby designated as “Arbor Day.”</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-373"><akn:num>Section 373</akn:num><akn:heading>American History Month</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>That February of each year is hereby designated as American History Month, and the Governor of the State of Vermont is requested and authorized to issue annually a proclamation inviting the people of the State of Vermont to observe such month in schools, churches, and other suitable places with appropriate ceremonies and activities.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-374"><akn:num>Section 374</akn:num><akn:heading>POW-MIA Recognition Day</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The third Friday in the month of September is designated as “POW-MIA Recognition Day.”</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-375"><akn:num>Section 375</akn:num><akn:heading>Juneteenth</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The third Saturday of the month of June is designated as “Juneteenth National Freedom Day.”</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-376"><akn:num>Section 376</akn:num><akn:heading>Health Care Career Awareness Month</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>October of each year is designated as Health Care Career Awareness Month.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-377"><akn:num>Section 377</akn:num><akn:heading>Green Up Day; River Cleanup Month</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-377_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The first Saturday in the month of May is designated as Green Up Day.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-7_section-377_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>September of each year is designated as River Cleanup Month.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-9"><akn:num>Chapter 9</akn:num><akn:heading>Time</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-9_section-431"><akn:num>Section 431</akn:num><akn:heading>Standard time; daylight saving time</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-9_section-431_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The standard time within the State of Vermont shall be based on the mean astronomical time of 75° of longitude west from Greenwich, known and designated as “U.S. Eastern Standard Time,” except as provided in 15 U.S.C. § 260a, when standard time shall be advanced one hour. The period of time so advanced may be called “daylight saving time.”</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-9_section-431_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Governor is authorized to shorten or lengthen the period specified in subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-9_section-431_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section by proclamation, if necessary to make the time accord with the time in effect in any of the states whose boundaries adjoin Vermont.  This proclamation shall be issued at least 10 days before it takes effect.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-9_section-432"><akn:num>Section 432</akn:num><akn:heading>Use as to laws and contracts</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>In all laws, statutes, orders, decrees, rules, and regulations relating to the time of performance of any act by any officer or department of this State, including the Legislative, Executive, and Judicial Branches of the State government, or of any county, city, town, or district thereof, or relating to the time in which any rights shall accrue or determine, or within which any act shall or shall not be performed by any person subject to the jurisdiction of this State and in all the public schools and institutions of the State, or of any county, city, town, or district thereof, and in all contracts or choses in action made or to be performed in this State, it shall be understood and intended that the time shall be the time designated in section 431 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-11"><akn:num>Chapter 11</akn:num><akn:heading>Flag, Insignia, Seal, etc.</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-491"><akn:num>Section 491</akn:num><akn:heading>Coat of Arms; Crest; Motto and Badge</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-491_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Coat of Arms.   Green, a landscape occupying half of the shield; on the right and left, in the background, high mountains, blue; the sky, yellow.  From near the base and reaching nearly to the top of the shield, arises a pine tree of the natural color and between three erect sheaves, yellow, placed diagonally on the right side and a red cow standing on the left side of the field.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-491_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Motto and Badge.   On a scroll beneath the shield, the motto: Vermont; Freedom and Unity.  The Vermonter’s badge: two pine branches of natural color, crossed between the shield and scroll.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-491_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Crest.   A buck’s head, of natural color, placed on a scroll, blue and yellow.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-492"><akn:num>Section 492</akn:num><akn:heading>Design of Coat of Arms</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of State shall keep in the archives of his or her office a representation of the Coat of Arms according to the foregoing description.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-493"><akn:num>Section 493</akn:num><akn:heading>State Seal</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Seal shall be the Great Seal of the State, a faithful reproduction, cut larger and deeper, of the original seal, designed by Ira Allen, cut by Reuben Dean of Windsor and accepted by resolution of the General Assembly, dated February 20, 1779.  The Seal shall be kept by the Secretary of Civil and Military Affairs.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-494"><akn:num>Section 494</akn:num><akn:heading>Use of State Seal</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Vermont Development Board may, with the prior written consent of the Governor, reproduce the seal of the State of Vermont in any State-sponsored publication whether or not advertising is included in such publication.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-495"><akn:num>Section 495</akn:num><akn:heading>State Flag</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Flag of the State shall be blue with the Coat of Arms of the State thereon.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-496"><akn:num>Section 496</akn:num><akn:heading>State Flags, purchase, distribution</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of State shall obtain, through the Department of Buildings and General Services, State Flags. The Secretary may, on terms that he or she finds appropriate, distribute these State Flags to other states; to State officials, departments, and agencies; and to other persons the Secretary may determine should receive them.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-496a"><akn:num>Section 496a</akn:num><akn:heading>Bennington Battle Flag</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of State shall obtain, through the Department of Buildings and General Services, two copies of the Bennington Battle Flag, one for delivery to the Sergeant at Arms to be flown at the State House in Montpelier, under the U.S. Flag, on the 15th, 16th, and 17th days of August each year to commemorate the Battle of Bennington, and a second for delivery to the Vermont Division for Historic Preservation, along with one Vermont State Flag, to be flown at the Bennington Battle Monument Area.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-496b"><akn:num>Section 496b</akn:num><akn:heading>Green Mountain Boys Flag</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of State shall obtain, through the Department of Buildings and General Services, a copy of the Green Mountain Boys Flag for delivery to the Sergeant at Arms to be flown at the State House in Montpelier, under the U.S. Flag, on the 15th day of January each year to commemorate Vermont’s independence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-496c"><akn:num>Section 496c</akn:num><akn:heading>POW-MIA flag; flying on State flagpoles</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State of Vermont shall fly on State-owned flagpoles, where practicable, the National League of Families Prisoner of War and Missing in Action Flag, as designated in 36 U.S.C. § 902, provided the flag is donated.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-496d"><akn:num>Section 496d</akn:num><akn:heading>Flag protocol</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Department of Buildings and General Services shall adopt and update as necessary a protocol for the flying of any flag on a State-owned flagpole and on municipally owned flagpoles if statutorily directed. The protocol shall incorporate any existing flag-flying policies or protocols that the Department has previously adopted.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-496e"><akn:num>Section 496e</akn:num><akn:heading>Honor and Remember Flag</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Honor and Remember Flag is designated as the flag that recognizes those Vermonters who died during or as the result of serving on active duty in the U.S. Armed Forces. This designation will recognize their bravery and educate Vermonters about the sacrifices their fellow citizens have made to protect our nation. The Department of Buildings and General Services shall establish a protocol for the flying of the Honor and Remember Flag and may accept donations of the flag to be flown on State-owned flagpoles. The Honor and Remember Flag may be flown on State-owned and municipally owned flagpoles, including those at military facilities, war memorials, and veterans cemeteries on such days as the Department of Buildings and General Services shall designate in the protocol.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-497"><akn:num>Section 497</akn:num><akn:heading>State Bird</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Bird shall be the hermit thrush.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-498"><akn:num>Section 498</akn:num><akn:heading>State Flower</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Flower shall be the red clover.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-499"><akn:num>Section 499</akn:num><akn:heading>State Tree</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Tree shall be the sugar maple.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-500"><akn:num>Section 500</akn:num><akn:heading>State Animal</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Animal shall be the Morgan horse.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-501"><akn:num>Section 501</akn:num><akn:heading>State Fish</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Cold Water Fish shall be the brook trout (salvelinus fontinalis) and the State Warm Water Fish shall be the walleye pike (sander vitreus).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-502"><akn:num>Section 502</akn:num><akn:heading>State Insect</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Insect shall be the honeybee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-503"><akn:num>Section 503</akn:num><akn:heading>State Beverage</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Beverage shall be milk.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-504"><akn:num>Section 504</akn:num><akn:heading>State Soil</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Soil shall be the Tunbridge soil series.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-505"><akn:num>Section 505</akn:num><akn:heading>State Butterfly</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Butterfly shall be the monarch.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-506"><akn:num>Section 506</akn:num><akn:heading>State Gem</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Gem shall be the grossular garnet.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-507"><akn:num>Section 507</akn:num><akn:heading>State Rocks</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Rocks shall be marble, granite, and slate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-508"><akn:num>Section 508</akn:num><akn:heading>State Mineral</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Mineral shall be talc.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-509"><akn:num>Section 509</akn:num><akn:heading>State Fossils</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-509_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The State Marine Fossil shall be the white whale fossilized skeleton at the University of Vermont’s Perkins Geology Museum.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-509_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The State Terrestrial Fossil shall be the Mount Holly mammoth tooth and tusk at the Mount Holly Community Historical Museum.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-510"><akn:num>Section 510</akn:num><akn:heading>State Flavor</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Flavor shall be maple from the Vermont sugar maple tree.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-511"><akn:num>Section 511</akn:num><akn:heading>State Amphibian</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Amphibian shall be the northern leopard frog.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-512"><akn:num>Section 512</akn:num><akn:heading>State Pie</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Pie shall be apple pie.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-513"><akn:num>Section 513</akn:num><akn:heading>State Fruit</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Fruit shall be the apple.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-514"><akn:num>Section 514</akn:num><akn:heading>State Song</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Song shall be “These Green Mountains.”</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-515"><akn:num>Section 515</akn:num><akn:heading>State Heritage Livestock Breed</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Randall Lineback breed of cattle shall be an official State Heritage breed of livestock.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-516"><akn:num>Section 516</akn:num><akn:heading>State Sports</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Winter Sports shall be skiing and snowboarding.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-517"><akn:num>Section 517</akn:num><akn:heading>State Fly-Fishing Fly</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Fly-Fishing Fly shall be the Governor Aiken bucktail streamer.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-518"><akn:num>Section 518</akn:num><akn:heading>State Latin Motto</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Latin Motto shall be Stella quarta decima fulgeat (May the 14th star shine bright).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-11_section-519"><akn:num>Section 519</akn:num><akn:heading>State Vegetable</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State Vegetable shall be the Gilfeather turnip.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-13"><akn:num>Chapter 13</akn:num><akn:heading>Jurisdiction of the United States</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-13_section-551"><akn:num>Section 551</akn:num><akn:heading>Concurrent jurisdiction reserved</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When, pursuant to U.S. Const. Art. 1, § 8, cl. 17, consent to purchase is given and exclusive jurisdiction ceded to the United States in respect to and over any lands within this State which shall be acquired by the United States for the purposes described in such clause of the Constitution, such jurisdiction shall continue so long as the lands are held and occupied by the United States for public purposes; but concurrent jurisdiction is reserved for the execution upon such lands of all process, civil or criminal, issued by the courts of the State and not incompatible with the cession, and for the enforcement of State law in the federal enclave along the border of Canada and Vermont by law enforcement officers certified under 20 V.S.A. § 2358. The deed or other conveyance of such land to the United States shall contain a description of such lands by metes and bounds and shall be recorded in the town clerk’s office of the town in which such lands lie or an accurate map or plan and description by metes and bounds of such lands shall be filed in such clerk’s office.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-13_section-552"><akn:num>Section 552</akn:num><akn:heading>Consent to purchase</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Subject to the provisions of section 551 of this title, consent to purchase is hereby given and exclusive jurisdiction is ceded to the United States in respect to and over so much land as the United States has or may acquire for the purposes described in U.S. Const. Art. 1, § 8, cl. 17.  However, with respect to land hereafter sought to be acquired by the United States for flood control purposes or for other needful buildings as specified in such clause of the Constitution of the United States, the consent of the State shall not be deemed to have been given unless and until such land has been acquired by the State and conveyed to the United States in the manner provided by 29 V.S.A. chapter 15 with respect to public works projects and with the written approval of the Governor and the approval of the General Assembly.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-13_section-553"><akn:num>Section 553</akn:num><akn:heading>Federal Geological Survey</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>For the purpose of making the surveys required of the Federal Geological Survey by acts of Congress, it shall be lawful for the persons employed in making the same to enter upon the lands within the boundaries of this State, but this section shall not be construed as authorizing any unnecessary interference with private rights.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-13_section-554"><akn:num>Section 554</akn:num><akn:heading>National forest lands</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The consent of the State of Vermont is hereby given to the acquisition by the United States, by purchase, gift, or condemnation with adequate compensation, of such lands in Vermont with the approval of a Board consisting of the Governor, Lieutenant Governor, Attorney General, Commissioner of Forests, Parks and Recreation, and Secretary of Agriculture, Food and Markets in the following towns: Bristol, Lincoln, Warren, Ripton, Granville, Hancock, Rochester, Pittsfield, Chittenden, Goshen, Middlebury, Salisbury, Leicester, Brandon, Mendon, Stockbridge, Winhall, Londonderry, Peru, Dorset, Danby, Landgrove, Weston, Wallingford, Mt. Holly, Mt. Tabor, Stratton, Wardsboro, Dover, Wilmington, Whitingham, Readsboro, Searsburg, Sunderland, Manchester, Woodford, Stamford, Jamaica, Bennington, Pownal, Shaftsbury, Arlington, and Killington, and the unorganized towns of Glastenbury and Somerset, which in the opinion of the federal government and the State may be needed for the establishment, consolidation, and extension of national forests in the State. Land in the Town of Rupert and the Town of Sandgate may be considered by the Board for classification within boundaries of areas of the State in which the United States may acquire lands as National Forest lands, provided that the legislative body of the town has voted to allow such consideration after having been advised to do so by a majority of town residents voting in an advisory referendum on the question.  Such Board shall act on a specific parcel only after it has the written approval of the legislative body or selectboard members of the town or supervisors of an unorganized town or gore wherein such land, or a part thereof is located.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-13_section-555"><akn:num>Section 555</akn:num><akn:heading>Jurisdiction of United States over national forests</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The United States shall have jurisdiction to make and enforce such laws, rules, and regulations as the United States shall deem necessary for the administration, protection, and management of national forests in the State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-13_section-556"><akn:num>Section 556</akn:num><akn:heading>Jurisdiction of State over national forests</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>In all other respects, the jurisdiction over persons and property within the territory of national forests in the State shall not be affected nor changed by reason of the acquisition of title to such lands by the United States.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-13_section-557"><akn:num>Section 557</akn:num><akn:heading>Disposition of monies from national forests and forest products</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-13_section-557_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Funds from national forests under the provisions of the Weeks Law shall first be apportioned by the State Treasurer among the several school districts in which such national forest is or may be situated, in proportion to the area of such national forest in each, as determined by the forest service of the U. S. Department of Agriculture. For purposes of this section, “school district” means a town, city, independent, or unified school district.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-13_section-557_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Funds from the sale of forest products pursuant to 10 U.S.C. § 2665 shall be apportioned by the State Treasurer among the several towns in a manner proportional to the area in each town of the military installation or facility from which the forest products were produced.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-13_section-557_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The several sums so apportioned to each school district or town shall be paid over by the State Treasurer, within 60 days after receipt thereof, to the treasurer of such school district or town. Such sums shall be expended for the benefit of the public schools of such school district or for the benefit of the public roads on the part of the recipient town, in addition to the sums required by law to be raised for such purposes, in such manner as may be determined by appropriations duly made by town meetings in such town or school district.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-15"><akn:num>Chapter 15</akn:num><akn:heading>New Hampshire-Vermont Boundary</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-15_section-611"><akn:num>Section 611</akn:num><akn:heading>Perambulation, renewal</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The boundary line between the State of New Hampshire and the State of Vermont shall be perambulated and markers and bounds renewed wherever necessary once in every seven years forever by the Attorney General of this State in conjunction with the Attorney General of the State of New Hampshire or by such person as the Attorney General shall in writing appoint for that purpose.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-15_section-612"><akn:num>Section 612</akn:num><akn:heading>Return</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A return of the perambulation shall be made, particularly describing the marks and monuments of such line and their location, which shall be signed by the Attorney General or the person making the same and recorded with the Secretary of State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-15_section-613"><akn:num>Section 613</akn:num><akn:heading>Notice</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Attorney General of this State shall give notice to the Attorney General of New Hampshire of the time and place of the meeting for such perambulation 30 days before the day of the meeting.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-15_section-614"><akn:num>Section 614</akn:num><akn:heading>Expenses of perambulation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>All expenses incurred by representation of this State incidental to such perambulation shall be paid by the State, including one-half of the cost of renewing markers or monuments. The Commissioner of Finance and Management is hereby authorized to draw his or her warrant therefor out of any money in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-15_section-615"><akn:num>Section 615</akn:num><akn:heading>Monuments; notice of construction affecting</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>No person, firm, or corporation shall begin or attempt to begin any alteration or improvement of the banks or bed of the Connecticut River, the erection of any building, dam, or other structure upon the banks or bed of such river or any other operations which will affect the waters or flow of such river so as to make the ascertaining of the location of the boundary line between the State of New Hampshire and the State of Vermont difficult without first giving notice thereof to the Attorney General of this State and the Attorney General of New Hampshire.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-15_section-616"><akn:num>Section 616</akn:num><akn:heading>Inspection</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Upon receipt of such notice, the Attorney General of this State shall communicate with the Attorney General of New Hampshire concerning the subject matter thereof, shall arrange for a joint inspection by such Attorneys General or their representatives of the premises described therein to determine the need of the erection of monuments to permanently mark the location of the boundary line in the area to be affected.  If required, such Attorneys General or their representatives shall erect such markers as are necessary.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-15_section-617"><akn:num>Section 617</akn:num><akn:heading>Permit</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Upon determination of need for or lack of need for a marking of the boundary, the Attorney General of this State shall certify the determination made to the person, firm, or corporation giving notice, and issue a permit that the work upon such alteration, improvement, building, dam, structure, or operation affecting the waters or flow of such river may be begun upon a day certain.  Such date shall be fixed as will give a reasonable time for the erection of monuments for the marking of the boundary if a need for such monuments has been determined; otherwise, so as to inconvenience the giver of the notice as little as possible.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-15_section-618"><akn:num>Section 618</akn:num><akn:heading>Penalty</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Any person, firm, or corporation who shall have failed to give the notice described in section 615 of this title or who, without having received from the Attorney General of this State the certificate and permit described in section 617, shall begin or attempt to begin any alteration or improvement of the banks or bed of the Connecticut River, the erection of any building, dam, or other structure upon the banks or bed of such river or any other operation which will affect the waters or flow of such river shall be fined not more than $5,000.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-17"><akn:num>Chapter 17</akn:num><akn:heading>Vermont Coordinate System</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-17_section-671"><akn:num>Section 671</akn:num><akn:heading>Vermont Coordinate Systems defined</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The systems of plane coordinates which have been established by the National Ocean Service/National Geodetic Survey (formerly the U. S. Coast and Geodetic Survey) or its successors for defining and stating the horizontal positions or locations of points on the surface of the earth within the State of Vermont are hereafter to be known and designated as the “Vermont Coordinate System 1927 and the Vermont Coordinate System 1983.” The term “Vermont Coordinate System” is synonymous with the term “Vermont State Plane Coordinate System.”</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-17_section-672"><akn:num>Section 672</akn:num><akn:heading>Coordinates defined</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The plane coordinate values for a point on the earth’s surface, used to express the horizontal position or location of such point on the Vermont Coordinate Systems, shall consist of two distances, expressed in U.S. Survey feet and decimals of a foot when using the Vermont Coordinate System 1927 and expressed in meters and decimals of a meter, or U.S. Survey feet and decimals of a foot when using the Vermont Coordinate System 1983. One of these distances, to be known as the “x-coordinate,” shall give the position in an east-and-west direction; the other, to be known as the “y-coordinate,” shall give the position in a north-and-south direction. These coordinates shall be made to depend upon and conform to plane rectangular coordinate values for the monumented points of the National Spatial Reference System established by the U. S. Coast and Geodetic Survey, its predecessor, or its successors.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-17_section-673"><akn:num>Section 673</akn:num><akn:heading>Additional definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-17_section-673_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For purposes of more precisely defining the Vermont Coordinate System 1927, the following definition by the U. S. Coast and Geodetic Survey (now the National Ocean Service/National Geodetic Survey) is adopted:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-17_section-673_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Vermont Coordinate System 1927 is a transverse Mercator projection of the Clarke spheroid of 1866, having a central meridian 72 degrees 30 minutes west of Greenwich, on which meridian the scale is set one part in 28,000 too small.  The origin of coordinates is at the intersection of the meridian 72 degrees 30 minutes west of Greenwich and the parallel 42 degrees 30 minutes north latitude.  This origin is given the coordinates: x = 500,000 feet and y = 0 feet.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-17_section-673_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For purposes of defining the Vermont Coordinate System 1983, the following definition by the National Ocean Service/National Geodetic Survey is adopted. The Vermont Coordinate System 1983 is a transverse Mercator projection of the GRS 80 ellipsoid, having a central meridian 72 degrees 30 minutes west of Greenwich, on which meridian the scale is set one part in 28,000 too small. The origin of coordinates is at the intersection of the meridian 72 degrees 30 minutes west of Greenwich and the parallel 42 degrees 30 minutes north latitude. This origin is given the coordinates: x = 500,000 meters and y = 0 meters.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-17_section-673_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The position of the Vermont Coordinate System 1983 shall be marked on the ground by existing or future survey stations established in conformity with standards adopted by the National Geodetic Survey or its successors for first-order or second-order work, or both, whose geodetic positions have been rigidly adjusted to the North American Datum 1983 (NAD 1983).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-17_section-674"><akn:num>Section 674</akn:num><akn:heading>Record</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Coordinates based on either Vermont Coordinate System, purporting to define the position of a point on a land boundary, presented to be recorded in any public land records or deed records shall be accompanied by a specific statement as to their basis and a description of the survey method used to determine them on the record plat or description of the survey.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-17_section-675"><akn:num>Section 675</akn:num><akn:heading>Restriction</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The use of the terms “Vermont Coordinate System 1927” or “Vermont Coordinate System 1983” on any map, report of survey, or other document shall be limited to coordinates based on the Vermont Coordinate Systems as defined in this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-17_section-676"><akn:num>Section 676</akn:num><akn:heading>Description</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>For the purposes of describing the location of any survey station or land boundary corner in the State of Vermont, it shall be considered a complete, legal, and satisfactory description of such location to give the position of such survey station or land boundary corner on the system of plane coordinates as defined in this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-17_section-677"><akn:num>Section 677</akn:num><akn:heading>Construction</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Nothing contained in this chapter shall require any purchaser or mortgagee of real property to rely solely on a description, any part of which depends entirely upon the Vermont Coordinate Systems.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-17_section-678"><akn:num>Section 678</akn:num><akn:heading>Severability</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>If any provision of this chapter shall be declared invalid, such invalidity shall not affect any other portion of this chapter which can be given effect without the invalid provision; and to this end, the provisions of this chapter are declared severable.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-17_section-679"><akn:num>Section 679</akn:num><akn:heading>Transition</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Vermont Coordinate System 1927 shall not be used for projects commenced after January 1, 2000; the Vermont Coordinate System 1983 will be the sole system for projects commenced after this date.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-19"><akn:num>Chapter 19</akn:num><akn:heading>Meridian Lines for Towns and Cities</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-19_section-731"><akn:num>Section 731</akn:num><akn:heading>Establishment of meridian lines</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Governor shall appoint one or more competent persons, one of whom, on application of the selectboard members, shall set out and establish a true meridian line, not less than 100 feet in length, at some convenient place in a town or city, to be selected, provided, and kept by such selectboard members for the free use of all persons.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-19_section-732"><akn:num>Section 732</akn:num><akn:heading>Markers; record; compensation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Under the direction of the person so appointed, the selectboard members shall erect suitable stone or iron posts at the extremities of such meridian line, setting the same firmly in the ground, the north post to be marked with the letter M, and the south post with the initial letter or letters of such town or city.  The person so appointed shall make a written description of the same, so that it can be readily known, and cause the same to be recorded in the office of the town or city clerk.  Such person shall receive for his or her services from the treasurer of such town or city $8.00 a day and his or her necessary expenses.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-21"><akn:num>Chapter 21</akn:num><akn:heading>Interstate Cooperation</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-821"><akn:num>Section 821</akn:num><akn:heading>Declaration of policy</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State of Vermont recognizes that intergovernmental cooperation is an essential factor in resolving problems affecting this State and that the interchange of personnel between governmental agencies at the same or different levels of government is a significant factor in achieving that cooperation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-822"><akn:num>Section 822</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-822_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Sending agency” means any department or agency of the federal government or a state government which sends any employee thereof to another government agency under this subchapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-822_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Receiving agency” means any department or agency of the federal government or a state government which receives an employee of another government under this subchapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-823"><akn:num>Section 823</akn:num><akn:heading>Authority to interchange employees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-823_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any department, agency, or instrumentality of the State may participate in a program of interchange of employees with departments, agencies, or instrumentalities of the federal government, or another state, as a sending or receiving agency.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-823_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The period of individual assignment or detail under an interchange program shall be subject to approval of the Commissioner of Human Resources for Executive departments, the Court Administrator for the Judiciary, and the Joint Rules Committee for the Legislature. Details relating to any matter covered in this subchapter may be the subject of an agreement between the sending and receiving agencies. Elected officials shall not be assigned from a sending agency nor detailed to a receiving agency.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-824"><akn:num>Section 824</akn:num><akn:heading>Status of employees of this State</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-824_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Employees of a sending agency participating in an exchange of personnel as authorized in section 823 of this title may be considered during that participation to be on detail to regular work assignment of the sending agency.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-824_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Employees who are on detail are entitled to the same salary and benefits to which they would otherwise be entitled and shall remain employees of the sending agency for all other purposes except that the supervision of their duties during the period of detail may be governed by agreement between the sending agency and the receiving agency.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-824_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any employee who participates in an exchange under the terms of this section who has a disability or dies as a result of personal injury arising out of and in the course of an exchange, or sustained in performance of duties in connection therewith, shall be treated, for the purposes of the sending agency’s employee compensation program, as an employee, as defined in the law creating that program, who has sustained the injury in the performance of his or her duty, but shall not receive benefits under that law for any period for which he or she is entitled to and elects to receive similar benefits under the receiving agency’s employee compensation program.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-825"><akn:num>Section 825</akn:num><akn:heading>Travel expenses of employees of this State</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A sending agency in this State may, in accordance with the travel regulations of the agency, pay the travel expenses of employees assigned to a receiving agency on either a detail or leave basis, but shall not pay the travel expenses of those employees incurred in connection with their work assignments at the receiving agency.  During the period of assignment, the sending agency may pay a daily allowance to the employee on assignment or detail.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-826"><akn:num>Section 826</akn:num><akn:heading>Status of employees of other governments</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-826_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When any unit of government of this State acts as a receiving agency, employees of the sending agency who are assigned under this subchapter may be considered to be on detail to the receiving agency.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-826_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Appointments of persons so assigned may be made without regard to the laws or regulations governing the selection of employees of the receiving agency.  Such a person shall be in the unclassified service of the State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-826_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Employees who are detailed to the receiving agency shall not by virtue of that detail be considered to be employees thereof, except as provided in subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-826_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, nor shall they be paid a salary or wage by the receiving agency during the period of their detail.  The supervision of the duties of those employees during the period of detail may be governed by agreement between the sending agency and the receiving agency.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-826_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any employee of a sending agency assigned in this State who has a disability or dies as a result of personal injury arising out of and in the course of that assignment, or sustained in the performance of duties in connection therewith, shall be treated for the purpose of the receiving agency’s employee compensation program, as an employee, as defined in its law, who has sustained the injury in the performance of that duty, but shall not receive benefits under that law for any period for which he or she elects to receive similar benefits as an employee under the sending agency’s employee compensation program.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-21_section-827"><akn:num>Section 827</akn:num><akn:heading>Travel expenses of employees of other governments</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A receiving agency in this State may, in accordance with the travel regulations of the agency, pay travel expenses of persons assigned thereto under this subchapter during the period of those assignments on the same basis as if they were regular employees of the receiving agency.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-23"><akn:num>Chapter 23</akn:num><akn:heading>Native American Indian People</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-851"><akn:num>Section 851</akn:num><akn:heading>Findings</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-851_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>At least 1,700 Vermonters claim to be direct descendants of the several indigenous Native American peoples, now known as Western Abenaki tribes, who originally inhabited all of Vermont and New Hampshire, parts of western Maine, parts of southern Quebec, and parts of upstate New York for hundreds of years, beginning long before the arrival of Europeans.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-851_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There is ample archaeological evidence that demonstrates that the Missisquoi and Cowasuck Abenaki were indigenous to and farmed the river floodplains of Vermont at least as far back as the 1100s A.D.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-851_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Western Abenaki, including the Missisquoi, have a very definite and carefully maintained oral tradition that consistently references the Champlain valley in western Vermont.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-851_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>State recognition confers official acknowledgment of the long-standing existence in Vermont of Native American Indians who predated European settlement and enhances dignity and pride in their heritage and community.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-851_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Many contemporary Abenaki families continue to produce traditional crafts and intend to continue to pass on these indigenous traditions to the younger generations. In order to create and sell Abenaki crafts that may be labeled as Indian- or Native American-produced, the Abenaki must be recognized by the State of Vermont.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-851_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>According to a public affairs specialist with the U.S. Bureau of Indian Affairs (BIA), State recognition of Indian tribes plays a very small role with regard to federal recognition. The only exception is when a state recognized a tribe before 1900.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-851_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>At least 15 other states have recognized their resident indigenous people as Native American Indian tribes without any of those tribes previously or subsequently acquiring federal recognition.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-851_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>State-recognized Native American Indian tribes and their members will continue to be subject to all laws of the State, and recognition shall not be construed to create any basis or authority for tribes to establish or promote any form of prohibited gambling activity or to claim any interest in land or real estate in Vermont.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-852"><akn:num>Section 852</akn:num><akn:heading>Vermont Commission on Native American Affairs established; authority</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-852_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In order to recognize the historic and cultural contributions of Native Americans to Vermont, to protect and strengthen their heritage, and to address their needs in State policy, programs, and actions, there is hereby established the Vermont Commission on Native American Affairs (the “Commission”).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-852_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission shall be composed of nine members appointed by the Governor for staggered two-year terms from a list of candidates compiled by the Division for Historic Preservation. The Governor shall appoint members who have been residents of Vermont for a minimum of three years and reflect a diversity of affiliations and geographic locations in Vermont. A member may serve for no more than two consecutive terms, unless there are insufficient eligible candidates. The Division shall compile a list of candidates from the following:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-852_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Recommendations from Native American communities residing in Vermont. Once a Native American Indian tribe has been recognized under this chapter, a qualified candidate recommended by that tribe shall have priority for appointment to fill the next available vacancy on the Commission.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-852_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Individuals who apply to the Division for Historical Preservation. Candidates shall indicate their residence and Native American affiliation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-852_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-852_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>elect a chair each year;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-852_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>provide technical assistance and an explanation of the process to applicants for State recognition;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-852_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>compile and maintain a list of professionals and scholars for appointment to a review panel;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-852_subsec-c_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>appoint a three-member panel acceptable to both the applicant and the Commission to review supporting documentation of an application for recognition and advise the Commission of its accuracy and relevance;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-852_subsec-c_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>review each application, supporting documentation and findings of the review panel, and make recommendations for or against State recognition to the legislative committees;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-852_subsec-c_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>assist Native American Indian tribes recognized by the State to:
(A) secure assistance for social services, education, employment opportunities, health care, and housing;
(B) develop and market Vermont Native American fine and performing arts, craft work, and cultural events; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-852_subsec-c_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>develop policies and programs to benefit Vermont’s Native American Indian population within the scope of the Commission’s authority.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-852_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>During fiscal year 2011, the Commission shall meet at least three times a year and at any other times at the request of the Chair and Commission members shall receive a per diem pursuant to 32 V.S.A. § 1010. In fiscal year 2012 and thereafter, the Commission shall meet as needed but members shall receive a per diem pursuant to 32 V.S.A. § 1010 no more than six times a year. The Division for Historic Preservation within the Agency of Commerce and Community Development shall provide administrative support to the Commission, including providing communication and contact resources.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-852_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission may seek and receive funding from federal and other sources to assist with its work.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853"><akn:num>Section 853</akn:num><akn:heading>Criteria and process for State recognition of Native American Indian tribes</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For the purposes of this section:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Applicant” means a group or band seeking formal State recognition as a Native American Indian tribe.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Legislative committees” means the House Committee on General, Housing and Military Affairs and the Senate Committee on Economic Development, Housing and General Affairs.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Recognized” or “recognition” means acknowledged as a Native American Indian tribe by the Vermont General Assembly.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Tribe” means an assembly of Native American Indian people who are related to each other by kinship and who trace their ancestry to a kinship group that has historically maintained an organizational structure that exerts influence and authority over its members.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The State recognizes all individuals of Native American Indian heritage who reside in Vermont as an ethnic minority. This designation does not confer any status to any collective group of individuals.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In order to be eligible for recognition, an applicant must file an application with the Commission and demonstrate compliance with subdivisions</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>through</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-c_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection which may be supplemented by subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-c_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A majority of the applicant’s members currently reside in a specific geographic location within Vermont.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A substantial number of the applicant’s members are related to each other by kinship and trace their ancestry to a kinship group through genealogy or other methods. Genealogical documents shall be limited to those that show a descendency from identified Vermont or regional native people.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The applicant has a connection with Native American Indian tribes and bands that have historically inhabited Vermont.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-c_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The applicant has historically maintained an organizational structure that exerts influence and authority over its members that is supported by documentation of the structure, membership criteria, the names and residential addresses of its members, and the methods by which the applicant conducts its affairs.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-c_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The applicant has an enduring community presence within the boundaries of Vermont that is documented by archaeology, ethnography, physical anthropology, history, folklore, or any other applicable scholarly research and data.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-c_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The applicant is organized in part:
(A) to preserve, document, and promote its Native American Indian culture and history, and this purpose is reflected in its bylaws;
(B) to address the social, economic, political, or cultural needs of the members with ongoing educational programs and activities.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-c_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The applicant can document traditions, customs, oral stories, and histories that signify the applicant’s Native American heritage and connection to their historical homeland.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-c_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The applicant has not been recognized as a tribe in any other state, province, or nation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-c_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Submission of letters, statements, and documents from:
(A) municipal, State, or federal authorities that document the applicant’s history of tribe-related business and activities;
(B) tribes in and outside Vermont that attest to the Native American Indian heritage of the applicant.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission shall consider the application pursuant to the following process which shall include at least the following requirements:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission shall:
(A) provide public notice of receipt of the application and supporting documentation;
(B) hold at least one public hearing on the application; and
(C) provide written notice of completion of each step of the recognition process to the applicant.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Established appropriate time frames that include a requirement that the Commission and the review panel shall complete a review of the application and issue a determination regarding recognition within one year after an application and all the supporting documentation have been filed, and if a recommendation is not issued, the Commission shall provide written explanation to the applicant and the legislative committees of the reasons for the delay and the expected date that a decision will be issued.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-d_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A process for appointing a three-member review panel for each application to review the supporting documentation and determine its sufficiency, accuracy, and relevance. The review panel shall provide a detailed written report of its findings and conclusions to the Commission, the applicant, and legislative committees. Members of each review panel shall be appointed cooperatively by the Commission and the applicant from a list of professionals and academic scholars with expertise in cultural or physical anthropology, Indian law, archaeology, Native American Indian genealogy, history, or another related Native American Indian subject area. If the applicant and the Commission are unable to agree on a panel, the State Historic Preservation Officer shall appoint the panel. No member of the review panel may be a member of the Commission or affiliated with or on the tribal rolls of the applicant.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-d_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission shall review the application, the supporting documentation, the report from the review panel, and any other relevant information to determine compliance with subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section and make a determination to recommend or deny recognition. The decision to recommend recognition shall require a majority vote of all eligible members of the Commission. A member of the Commission who is on the tribal roll of the applicant is ineligible to participate in any action regarding the application. If the Commission denies recognition, the Commission shall provide the applicant and the legislative committees with written notice of the reasons for the denial, including specifics of all insufficiencies of the application.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-b_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The applicant may file additional supporting documentation for reconsideration within one year after receipt of the notice of denial.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-b_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An applicant may withdraw an application any time before the Commission issues a recommendation, and may not file a new application for two years following withdrawal. A new application and supporting documentation shall be considered a de novo filing, and the Commission shall not consider the withdrawn application or its supporting documentation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-b_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-b_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All proceedings, applications, and supporting documentation shall be public except material exempt pursuant to subdivision 317</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-b_subsec-40"><akn:num>(40)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title. Any documents relating to genealogy submitted in support of the application shall be available only to the three-member review panel.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An applicant for recognition shall be recognized as follows:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-e_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>by approval of the General Assembly;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-e_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>two years after a recommendation to recognize a tribe by the Commission is filed with the legislative committees, provided the General Assembly took no action on the recommendation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A decision by the Commission to recommend denial of recognition is final unless an applicant or a successor of interest to the applicant that has previously applied for and been denied recognition under this chapter provides new and substantial documentation and demonstrates that the new documentation was not reasonably available at the time of the filing of the original application.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Vermont Native American Indian bands and tribes and individual members of those bands and tribes remain subject to all the laws of the State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853_subsec-h"><akn:num>(h)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Recognition of a Native American Indian tribe shall not be construed to create, extend, or form the basis of any right or claim to land or real estate in Vermont or right to conduct any gambling activities prohibited by law, but confers only those rights specifically described in this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853a"><akn:num>Section 853a</akn:num><akn:heading>Recognition of Elnu Abenaki tribe</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-853a_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title and is hereby recognized by the State of Vermont as a Native American Indian tribe.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-854"><akn:num>Section 854</akn:num><akn:heading>Recognition of Nulhegan Band of the Coosuk Abenaki Nation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-854_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title and is hereby recognized by the State of Vermont as a Native American Indian tribe.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-855"><akn:num>Section 855</akn:num><akn:heading>Recognition of Koasek Abenaki of the Koas</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-855_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title and is hereby recognized by the State of Vermont as a Native American Indian tribe.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-856"><akn:num>Section 856</akn:num><akn:heading>Recognition of Missisquoi, St. Francis-Sokoki band</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-23_section-856_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title and is hereby recognized by the State of Vermont as a Native American Indian tribe.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-01_chapter-25"><akn:num>Chapter 25</akn:num><akn:heading>Truth and Reconciliation Commission [Repealed effective July 1, 2026]</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-901"><akn:num>Section 901</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions [Repealed effective July 1, 2026]</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-901_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Commission” means the Vermont Truth and Reconciliation Commission, including its commissioners, committees, and staff.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-901_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Consultation” means a meaningful and timely process of seeking, discussing, and considering carefully the views of others in a manner that is cognizant of all parties’ cultural values.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-901_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Panel” means the Selection Panel established pursuant to section 904 of this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-901_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Record” means any written or recorded information, regardless of physical form or characteristics.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-902"><akn:num>Section 902</akn:num><akn:heading>Vermont Truth and Reconciliation Commission; establishment; organization [Repealed effective July 1, 2026]</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-902_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There is created and established a body corporate and politic to be known as the Vermont Truth and Reconciliation Commission to carry out the provisions of this chapter. The Truth and Reconciliation Commission is constituted a public instrumentality exercising public and essential government functions and the exercise by the Commission of the power conferred by this chapter shall be deemed and held to be the performance of an essential governmental function.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-902_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-902_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission shall consist of three commissioners appointed pursuant to section 905 of this chapter and shall include one or more committees established by the commissioners to examine institutional, structural, and systemic discrimination caused or permitted by State laws and policies experienced by each of the following populations and communities in Vermont:
(A) individuals who identify as Native American or Indigenous;
(B) individuals with a physical, psychiatric, or mental condition or disability and the families of individuals with a physical, psychiatric, or mental condition or disability;
(C) Black individuals and other individuals of color;
(D) individuals with French Canadian, French-Indian, or other mixed ethnic or racial heritage; and
(E) in the commissioners’ discretion, other populations and communities that have experienced institutional, structural, and systemic discrimination caused or permitted by State laws and policies.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-902_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) Each committee shall consist of the commissioners and members appointed by the commissioners in consultation with the populations and communities identified pursuant to subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-902_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-902_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter.

(D)</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-902_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Except as otherwise provided pursuant to subdivision (ii) of this subdivision (2)(D), committee members shall be entitled to per diem compensation and reimbursement of expenses as permitted under 32 V.S.A. § 1010 for not more than eight meetings per calendar year. These payments shall be made from monies appropriated to the Commission.
(ii) The commissioners may authorize committee members to receive per diem compensation and reimbursement of expenses as permitted under 32 V.S.A. § 1010 for additional meetings in each calendar year. Payments for additional meetings shall be made from grants or additional funding received by the Commissioners pursuant to subdivision 906</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-902_subsec-i_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter. In no event shall the per diem compensation and reimbursement of expenses for any additional meetings exceed the amounts permitted pursuant to 32 V.S.A. § 1010.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-902_subsec-i_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to require the Commission to examine institutional, structural, and systemic discrimination experienced by the populations and communities identified in subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-902_subsec-i_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection in isolation or separately from each other.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-903"><akn:num>Section 903</akn:num><akn:heading>Commissioners [Repealed effective July 1, 2026]</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-903_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Commissioners shall be full-time State employees and shall be exempt from the State classified system.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-903_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The commissioners shall receive compensation equal to one-half that of a Superior Court Judge.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-903_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The term of each commissioner shall begin on the date of appointment and end on July 1, 2026.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904"><akn:num>Section 904</akn:num><akn:heading>Selection panel; membership; duties [Repealed effective July 1, 2026]</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Selection Panel shall be composed of seven members selected on or before September 1, 2022 by a majority vote of the following:
(A) the Executive Director of Racial Equity or designee;
(B) the Executive Director of the Vermont Center for Independent Living or designee;
(C) an individual, who shall not be a current member of the General Assembly, appointed by the Speaker of the House;
(D) an individual, who shall not be a current member of the General Assembly, appointed by the Committee on Committees; and
(E) an individual appointed by the Chief Justice of the Vermont Supreme Court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The individuals identified in subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection:
(A) shall hold their first meeting on or before August 1, 2022 at the call of the individual appointed by the Chief Justice of the Vermont Supreme Court; and
(B) are encouraged to appoint individuals to the Selection Panel who include members of the populations and communities identified pursuant to subdivisions 902</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Individuals selected pursuant to subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection who are not employees of the State of Vermont and who are not otherwise compensated or reimbursed for their attendance shall be entitled to per diem compensation and reimbursement of expenses pursuant to 32 V.S.A. § 1010 for not more than two meetings. These payments shall be made from amounts appropriated to the Truth and Reconciliation Commission.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Selection Panel shall select and appoint the commissioners of the Truth and Reconciliation Commission as provided pursuant to section 905 of this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>To enable it to carry out its duty to select and appoint the commissioners of the Truth and Reconciliation Commission as provided pursuant to section 905 of this chapter, the Panel may:
(A) adopt procedures as necessary to carry out the duties set forth in section 905 of this chapter;
(B) establish and maintain a principal office;
(C) meet and hold hearings at any place in this State; and
(D) hire temporary staff to provide administrative assistance during the period from September 1, 2022 through January 15, 2023, provided that if the Panel extends the time to select commissioners pursuant to subdivision 905</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter, it may retain staff to provide administrative assistance through March 31, 2023.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The term of each member of the Panel shall begin on the date of appointment and end on January 15, 2023, except if the Panel extends the time to select commissioners pursuant to subdivision 905</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter, the term of the Panel members shall end on March 31, 2023.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Panel shall select a chair and a vice chair from among its members.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-e_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Meetings shall be held at the call of the Chair or at the request of four or more members of the Panel.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-e_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A majority of the current membership of the Panel shall constitute a quorum, and actions of the Panel may be authorized by a majority of the members present and voting at a meeting of the Panel.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-904_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Members of the Panel shall be entitled to per diem compensation and reimbursement of expenses pursuant to 32 V.S.A. § 1010 for not more than 20 meetings during fiscal year 2023. These payments shall be made from amounts appropriated to the Truth and Reconciliation Commission.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-905"><akn:num>Section 905</akn:num><akn:heading>Selection of commissioners [Repealed effective July 1, 2026]</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-905_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-905_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Except as otherwise provided pursuant to subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-905_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, the Selection Panel shall, on or before December 31, 2022, select three individuals to serve as the commissioners of the Vermont Truth and Reconciliation Commission.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-905_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In carrying out its duty to select the commissioners, the Panel shall:
(A) Establish a public, transparent, and simple process for candidates to apply to serve as a commissioner.
(B) Publicize the application process, deadlines, and requirements to serve as a commissioner through media outlets, civil society organizations, and any other forms of public outreach that the Panel determines to be appropriate.
(C) Solicit nominations for individuals to serve as commissioners from civil society organizations in Vermont whose work relates to the mission of the Commission.
(D) Invite Vermont residents to submit applications to serve as commissioners.
(E) Hold one or more public hearings to provide an opportunity for members of the public to meet and ask questions of the finalists to serve as a commissioner.
(F) Hold private interviews with each individual selected by the Panel as a finalist for selection as a commissioner.
(G) Conduct criminal history record checks for finalists, provided that the Panel shall only consider felony convictions or convictions for crimes involving untruthfulness or falsification. A finalist who has been convicted of a felony or a crime involving untruthfulness or falsification shall be afforded an opportunity to explain the information and the circumstances regarding the conviction, including postconviction rehabilitation.
(H) Take any other actions that the Panel deems appropriate or necessary to carry out its duties in relation to the selection of commissioners.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-905_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The three commissioners selected by the Panel shall:
(A) be residents of Vermont;
(B) not be members of the Selection Panel;
(C) have knowledge of the problems and challenges facing the populations and communities identified pursuant to subdivisions 902</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-905_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Not later than five days after selecting the commissioners pursuant to subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-905_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, the Panel shall submit a brief report to the Governor and the General Assembly identifying the commissioners. The names of the commissioners shall be made available to the public on the same day that the report is submitted.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-905_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-905_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If the Panel is unable to identify three suitable applicants on or before December 31, 2022, the Panel may by a majority vote extend the time to select commissioners to March 31, 2023.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-905_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If the Panel extends the time to select commissioners pursuant to this subsection, the Panel shall, on or before January 5, 2023, submit a brief written report to the House Committee on General, Housing, and Military Affairs and the Senate Committee on Government Operations providing notice of its decision to extend the time to select commissioners and its reasons for doing so and identifying any changes to the provisions of this chapter that may be necessary to enable the Panel to successfully identify and select commissioners.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906"><akn:num>Section 906</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers and duties of the commissioners [Repealed effective July 1, 2026]</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Duties.    The commissioners shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>establish, in consultation with the populations and communities identified pursuant to subdivision 902</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter and other interested parties in the commissioners’ discretion, committees to examine institutional, structural, and systemic discrimination caused or permitted by State laws and policies that have been experienced by the populations and communities identified pursuant to subdivision 902</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>determine, in consultation with the populations and communities identified pursuant to subdivision 902</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter, historians, social scientists, experts in restorative justice, and other interested parties in the commissioners’ discretion, the scope and objectives of the work to be carried out by each committee established pursuant to subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>develop and implement a process for each committee established pursuant to subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection to fulfill the objectives established pursuant to subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>work with the committees and Commission staff to carry out research, public engagement, and other work necessary to:
(A) identify and examine historic and ongoing institutional, structural, and systemic discrimination against members of the populations and communities identified pursuant to subdivision 902</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter that has been caused or permitted by State laws and policies;
(B) determine the current status of members of the populations and communities identified pursuant to subdivision 902</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter; and
(C) satisfy the scope of work and the objectives established pursuant to subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>work with the committees and Commission staff to identify potential programs and activities to create and improve opportunities for or to eliminate disparities experienced by the populations and communities that are the subject of the committees’ work;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>work with the committees and Commission staff to identify potential educational programs related to historic and ongoing institutional, structural, and systemic discrimination against members of the populations and communities that are the subject of the committees’ work;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>work in consultation with the populations and communities identified pursuant to subdivision 902</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter, experts in restorative justice, and, in the commissioners’ discretion, other interested parties to ensure that the work of the Commission is open, transparent, inclusive, and meaningful; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>supervise the work of the Executive Director of the Commission.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Powers.    To carry out its duties pursuant to this chapter, the commissioners may:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Adopt rules in accordance with 3 V.S.A. chapter 25 as necessary to implement the provisions of this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Adopt procedures as necessary to carry out the duties set forth in subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Establish and maintain a principal office.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Meet and hold hearings at any place in this State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Consult with local, national, and international experts on issues related to discrimination, truth and reconciliation, and restorative justice.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Interview and take statements from members of the populations and communities identified pursuant to subdivision 902</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter; members of the public; and persons with knowledge of the institutional, structural, and systemic discrimination experienced by such populations and communities.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Study, research, investigate, and report on the impact of State laws and policies on populations and communities identified pursuant to subdivision 902</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter. If the Commission determines that particular laws or policies caused or permitted institutional, structural, and systemic discrimination against a population or community, regardless of whether the discrimination was intentional or adversely impacted the population or community, the Commission may propose legislative or administrative action to the General Assembly or Governor, as appropriate, to remedy the impacts on the population or community.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Enter into cooperative agreements with private organizations or individuals or with any agency or instrumentality of the United States or of this State to carry out the provisions of this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Make and execute legal documents necessary or convenient for the exercise of its powers and duties under this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Hire consultants and independent contractors to assist the Commission in carrying out the provisions of this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Seek grants or funding other than annual State appropriations to further the work of the Commission.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-906_subsec-a_subsec-12"><akn:num>(12)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Take any other actions necessary to carry out the provisions of this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-907"><akn:num>Section 907</akn:num><akn:heading>Executive Director; duties [Repealed effective July 1, 2026]</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-907_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commissioners shall appoint an Executive Director. The Executive Director shall be a full-time State employee, shall be exempt from the State classified system, and shall serve at the pleasure of the commissioners.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-907_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Executive Director shall be responsible for the following:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-907_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>supervising and administering the implementation of the provisions of this chapter on behalf of the commissioners;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-907_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>assisting the commissioners in carrying out their duties;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-907_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>ensuring that the Commission has the resources and staff assistance necessary to collect historical materials, take statements from individuals, hold public hearings and events, and prepare and publish reports and other documents;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-907_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>facilitating communications between the Commission and members of the populations and communities identified pursuant to subdivision 902</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-907_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter, interested parties, and members of the public;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-907_subsec-b_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>hiring staff, including researchers and administrative and legal professionals, as necessary to carry out the duties of the Commission; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-907_subsec-b_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>preparing an annual budget for submission to the commissioners.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-908"><akn:num>Section 908</akn:num><akn:heading>Reports [Repealed effective July 1, 2026]</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-908_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>On or before January 15, 2024, the Commission shall submit to the Governor and General Assembly an interim report on the Commission’s progress to date, the committees established pursuant to subdivision 906</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-908_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter and the scope and objectives of their work, emerging themes and issues that the Commission has identified, and, if available, any preliminary findings and recommendations for legislative or other action that the Commission believes should be prioritized to address instances of institutional, structural, and systemic discrimination identified by the Commission.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-908_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-908_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>On or before June 15, 2026, the Commission shall submit a final report incorporating the findings and recommendations of each committee. Each report shall detail the findings and recommendations of the relevant committee and shall include recommendations for actions that can be taken to eliminate ongoing instances of institutional, structural, and systemic discrimination and to address the harm caused by historic instances of institutional, structural, and systemic discrimination.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-908_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission shall, on or before January 15, 2026, make a draft of the final report publicly available and provide copies of the draft to interested parties from the populations and communities identified pursuant to subdivision 902</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-908_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter and other interested parties. The Commission shall provide the interested parties and members of the public with not less than 60 days to review the draft and provide comments on it. The Commission shall consider fully all comments submitted in relation to the draft and shall include with the final version of the report a summary of all comments received and a concise statement of the reasons why the Commission decided to incorporate or reject any proposed changes. Comments submitted in relation to the final report shall be made available to the public in a manner that complies with the requirements of section 910 of this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-908_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission may, in its discretion, issue additional reports to the Governor, General Assembly, and public.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-909"><akn:num>Section 909</akn:num><akn:heading>Access to information; confidentiality [Repealed effective July 1, 2026]</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-909_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Access to State records and information.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-909_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission shall have access to and the right to copy any record or other information held by all executive, administrative, and judicial agencies and departments and all instrumentalities of the State. All executive, administrative, and judicial agencies and departments and all instrumentalities of the State shall cooperate with the Commission with respect to any request for access to any record or other information and shall provide all records or other information requested by the Commission to the extent permitted by law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-909_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission shall keep confidential any information received from an executive, administrative, or judicial agency or department or an instrumentality of the State that is confidential or is exempt from the Public Records Act.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-909_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Confidentiality requirements.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-909_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Except as otherwise provided pursuant to subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-909_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, information and records acquired by or provided to the Commission that would in any manner reveal an individual’s identity shall be kept confidential and shall be exempt from public inspection and copying under the Public Records Act.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-909_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission shall not include the personally identifying information of any individual in any report that it produces without the express, written consent of the individual.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-909_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Exceptions.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-909_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Except as provided in subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-909_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection, information and records acquired by or provided to the Commission shall only be available to the public in an anonymized form that does not reveal the identity of any individual.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-909_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Information or records acquired by or provided to the Commission may be disclosed in a manner that would reveal the identity of an individual if that individual has provided their express, written consent to the disclosure of the information or record in a manner that would reveal their identity.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-909_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Private proceedings.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-909_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission shall permit any individual who is interviewed by the Commission to elect to have their interview conducted in a manner that protects the individual’s privacy and to have any recording of the interview kept confidential by the Commission. Any other record or document produced in relation to an interview conducted pursuant to this subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-909_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>shall only be available to the public in an anonymized form that does not reveal the identity of any individual.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-909_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission shall adopt procedures and safeguards to ensure to the greatest extent possible that it does not conduct any interview in a manner that is open to the public if the interview will reveal the identities of individuals other than the interviewee without the express, written consent of those individuals.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-910"><akn:num>Section 910</akn:num><akn:heading>Establishment of positions  [Repealed effective July 1, 2026]</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-910_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>one Executive Director;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-910_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>one Staff Attorney;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-910_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>one Researcher; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-01_chapter-25_section-910_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>one Administrative Assistant.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter></akn:title></akn:body></akn:act></akn:akomaNtoso>