<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akn:akomaNtoso xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><akn:act><akn:meta><akn:identification source="#cosilico"><akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-02" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-02" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-05-01" name="release" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#vermont-legislature" /><akn:FRBRcountry value="us-vt" /><akn:FRBRnumber value="02" /><akn:FRBRname value="Vermont Statutes Annotated" /></akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-02/eng@2023-05-01" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-02/eng@2023-05-01" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-05-01" name="publication" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /><akn:FRBRlanguage language="eng" /></akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRManifestation><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-02/eng@2023-05-01/akn.xml" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-02/eng@2023-05-01/akn.xml" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /></akn:FRBRManifestation></akn:identification><akn:references><akn:TLCOrganization eId="vermont-legislature" href="https://legislature.vermont.gov" showAs="Vermont General Assembly" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico" /></akn:references></akn:meta><akn:body><akn:title eId="title-02"><akn:num>Title 02</akn:num><akn:heading>Legislature</akn:heading><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-1"><akn:num>Chapter 1</akn:num><akn:heading>General Assembly</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-2"><akn:num>Chapter 2</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint Legislative Management Committee</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-3"><akn:num>Chapter 3</akn:num><akn:heading>Sergeant at Arms</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-5"><akn:num>Chapter 5</akn:num><akn:heading>Board of Legislative Draftsmen</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-7"><akn:num>Chapter 7</akn:num><akn:heading>Legislative Reference Bureau</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-9"><akn:num>Chapter 9</akn:num><akn:heading>Uniform Legislation</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-11"><akn:num>Chapter 11</akn:num><akn:heading>Registration of Lobbyists</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-13"><akn:num>Chapter 13</akn:num><akn:heading>Office of Legislative Counsel</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-14"><akn:num>Chapter 14</akn:num><akn:heading>Office of Human Resources</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-15"><akn:num>Chapter 15</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint Fiscal Committee; Joint Fiscal Office</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-16"><akn:num>Chapter 16</akn:num><akn:heading>Office of Legislative Operations</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-17"><akn:num>Chapter 17</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint Carbon Emissions Reduction Committee</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-18"><akn:num>Chapter 18</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint Information Technology Oversight Committee</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-19"><akn:num>Chapter 19</akn:num><akn:heading>Legislative Advisory Committee on the State House</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-20"><akn:num>Chapter 20</akn:num><akn:heading>Health Reform Oversight Committee</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-21"><akn:num>Chapter 21</akn:num><akn:heading>Office of Legislative Information Technology</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-22"><akn:num>Chapter 22</akn:num><akn:heading>Legislative Information Technology Committee</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-23"><akn:num>Chapter 23</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint Legislative Justice Oversight Committee</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-24"><akn:num>Chapter 24</akn:num><akn:heading>Health Care Oversight Committee</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-25"><akn:num>Chapter 25</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint Legislative Commission on Health Care Reform</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-26"><akn:num>Chapter 26</akn:num><akn:heading>National Legislative Association on Prescription Drug Prices</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-28"><akn:num>Chapter 28</akn:num><akn:heading>Government Accountability Committee</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-30"><akn:num>Chapter 30</akn:num><akn:heading>Capitol Complex Security Advisory Committee</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-31"><akn:num>Chapter 31</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint Public Pension Oversight Committee</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-1"><akn:num>Chapter 1</akn:num><akn:heading>General Assembly</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-1"><akn:num>Section 1</akn:num><akn:heading>Place of holding sessions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The sessions of the General Assembly shall be held in the State House in Montpelier; except that, in case that Montpelier, in the opinion of the Governor, shall ever become an unsafe place because of an enemy attack or threatened attack upon the United States or Canada, such sessions, while such unsafe condition shall continue, shall be held elsewhere in a building or buildings to be designated from time to time by him or her.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-2"><akn:num>Section 2</akn:num><akn:heading>Use of hall and Senate chamber</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Representatives’ hall and the Senate chamber shall not be used for purposes other than legislation or business connected therewith, except as the two houses may by joint rule or resolution provide.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-3"><akn:num>Section 3</akn:num><akn:heading>Senate certificates; oaths; Secretary; canvassing committee</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The members-elect of the Senate shall deliver their certificates of election to the President of the Senate before 10 o’clock in the forenoon of the first Wednesday next after the first Monday of January, following their election; at which time, the Senate shall be called to order by its President and the names of the Senators who have presented their certificates shall be called.  When a quorum appears, the members shall take and subscribe the oath of allegiance and the oath prescribed for Representatives to the General Assembly and shall then elect a Secretary, who shall appoint an Assistant Secretary, for whose acts he or she shall be responsible.  The Senate shall then appoint a committee, consisting of one Senator from each district, to join such committee as the House of Representatives appoints, to canvass the votes for Governor, Lieutenant Governor, State Treasurer, Secretary of State, Auditor of Accounts, and Attorney General.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-4"><akn:num>Section 4</akn:num><akn:heading>Senate vacancy</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>If a vacancy occurs in the Senate, the Governor shall appoint some person from the district wherein the vacancy occurs to fill the unexpired term, and shall transmit to the person so appointed a certificate of his or her appointment, and cause a certified copy thereof to be sent to the President of the Senate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-6"><akn:num>Section 6</akn:num><akn:heading>House roll; election of Speaker</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of State shall make a roll, by districts, of members whose credentials have been received in the form of a certificate from the canvassing committee or a superseding court order, and at 10 o’clock in the forenoon of the first Wednesday next after the first Monday of January, as presiding officer, shall call the House to order and call the names of the members on the roll.  When a quorum of the House appears, he or she shall direct the House to a choice of Speaker by ballot. When a Speaker is elected, he or she shall take the chair and the duties of the Secretary of State in the organization of the House shall cease.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-7"><akn:num>Section 7</akn:num><akn:heading>House Clerk; canvassing committee</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The House shall then elect a Clerk and on the nomination of the Speaker shall appoint a committee, consisting of three members from each district, to join such committee as the Senate appoints, to canvass the votes for Governor, Lieutenant Governor, State Treasurer, Secretary of State, Auditor of Accounts, and Attorney General.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-8"><akn:num>Section 8</akn:num><akn:heading>Assistant Clerks of House</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Clerk shall appoint two assistants for whose acts he or she shall be responsible.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-9"><akn:num>Section 9</akn:num><akn:heading>House vacancy</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>If a vacancy occurs in the Office of Representative to the General Assembly, the Governor shall appoint some person from the district wherein the vacancy occurs to fill the unexpired term, and shall transmit to the person so appointed a certificate of his or her appointment, and cause certified copies thereof to be sent to the Secretary of State and to the clerk of the district wherein the vacancy occurs.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-10"><akn:num>Section 10</akn:num><akn:heading>Election of State and judicial officers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-10_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>At 10 o’clock and 30 minutes, forenoon, on the seventh Thursday after their biennial meeting and organization, the Senate and House of Representatives shall meet in joint assembly and proceed therein to elect the State officers, except judicial officers, whose election by the Constitution and laws devolves in the first instance upon them in joint assembly, including the Sergeant at Arms and legislative trustees of the University of Vermont and State Agricultural College. In case election of all such officers shall not be made on that day, they shall meet in joint assembly at 10 o’clock and 30 minutes, forenoon, on each succeeding day, Saturdays and Sundays excepted, and proceed in such election, until all such officers are elected.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-10_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>At 10 o’clock and 30 minutes, forenoon, on the 11th Thursday after their biennial meeting and organization, and on the 11th Thursday of the second year of the biennial session, when necessary, the Senate and House of Representatives shall meet in joint assembly and proceed therein to elect the judicial officers whose election by the Constitution and laws devolves in the first instance upon them in joint assembly, including Justices of the Supreme Court and judges of all subordinate courts, except assistant judges and judges of probate. In case election of all such officers shall not be made on that day, they shall meet in joint assembly at 10 o’clock and 30 minutes, forenoon, on each succeeding day, Saturdays and Sundays excepted, and proceed in such election, until all such officers are elected.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-10_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>At 10 o’clock and 30 minutes, forenoon, on the seventh Thursday of the second year of the biennial session, the Senate and House of Representatives shall meet in joint assembly and proceed therein to elect the State Officers, whose election by the Constitution and laws devolves in the first instance upon them in joint assembly, including the legislative trustees of the Vermont State Colleges Corporation and the Adjutant and Inspector General. In case election of all such officers shall not be made on that day, they shall meet in joint assembly at 10 o’clock and 30 minutes, forenoon, on each succeeding day, Saturdays and Sundays excepted, and proceed in such election, until all such officers are elected.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-11"><akn:num>Section 11</akn:num><akn:heading>Vacancies in office</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The General Assembly shall fill all vacancies in office existing or occurring while it is in session, where the incumbents are by law elected by the General Assembly, and such officers so elected shall hold their respective offices during the unexpired term.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-12"><akn:num>Section 12</akn:num><akn:heading>Legislative elections; uniform ballots</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-12_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Whenever there is a known contested election for Speaker of the House of Representatives, President Pro Tempore of the Senate, and in elections by the joint assembly of the Legislature, the Secretary of State shall prepare a ballot for each office, listing the names of the known candidates for the office in the alphabetical order of their surnames and leaving thereon sufficient blank spaces to take care of any nominations from the floor.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-12_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A candidate for office shall, not later than one week preceding the election, notify the Secretary of State in writing of his or her candidacy, naming the particular office.  If he or she fails so to notify the Secretary of State, his or her name shall not be printed on the ballot.  No ballot may be used other than the official ballot provided by the Secretary of State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-13"><akn:num>Section 13</akn:num><akn:heading>Daily journals</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-13_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>At the close of each legislative day, the Secretary of the Senate and Clerk of the House of Representatives shall prepare a daily copy of the journal of their respective bodies for such day.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-13_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Such journals shall contain all motions, votes, orders, and proceedings, but shall not contain any remark of a member or words spoken for or against a pending question.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-14"><akn:num>Section 14</akn:num><akn:heading>Stenographic assistance for journals</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Such Secretary and Clerk shall procure stenographic and other clerical assistance as they respectively deem necessary to ensure the proper, efficient, and expeditious performance of the work required by section 13 of this title.  Compensation for stenographic and other clerical assistance shall be determined by the Rules Committee of the House or Senate, as the case may be, and the Commissioner of Finance and Management shall issue his or her warrant in payment therefor.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-15"><akn:num>Section 15</akn:num><akn:heading>Daily calendar</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>At the close of each legislative day such Secretary and Clerk shall prepare a calendar of the measures in their files for consideration by their respective bodies on the following legislative day.  A sufficient number of copies of each calendar shall be printed.  They shall place one copy of such calendar on the desk of each member of their respective bodies before the opening of the morning session of the following legislative day.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-16"><akn:num>Section 16</akn:num><akn:heading>Printing and distribution of daily calendar, journal, and bills</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-16_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Calendars.   One copy of the daily House calendar shall be placed on the desk of each member of the House and one copy of the daily Senate calendar shall be placed on the desk of each member of the Senate.  An additional number of copies of both the daily House and Senate calendars shall be made available to House and Senate members in their respective chambers upon the request of a member.  Calendars shall also be published on the State legislative webpage.  The number of copies required shall be determined by staff of the Legislative Council based on their demand.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-16_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Journals and bills.   The daily House and Senate journals and bills shall be published on the State legislative webpage.  Copies of bills shall be made upon request to House and Senate members.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-16_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-19"><akn:num>Section 19</akn:num><akn:heading>Compensation to chaplains</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Chaplains serving the Legislature, other than members of the Legislature, shall receive $5.00 a day to defray expenses for each day served and such sums shall be paid by the Commissioner of Finance and Management from the legislative appropriation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-20"><akn:num>Section 20</akn:num><akn:heading>Limitation on distribution and duration of agency reports</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-20_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Unless otherwise provided by law, whenever it is required by statute, rule, or otherwise that an agency submit an annual, biennial, or other periodic report to the General Assembly, that requirement shall be met by submission by January 15 of copies of the report for activities in the preceding fiscal year to the Clerk of the House, the Secretary of the Senate, the Office of Legislative Counsel, and such individual members of the General Assembly or committees that specifically request a copy of the report. To the extent practicable, reports shall also be placed on the agency’s Internet website. No general distribution or mailing of such reports shall be made to members of the General Assembly.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-20_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For the purposes of this section, “agency” means each State agency, board, commission, or department or any division thereof.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-20_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of the Senate and the Clerk of the House shall each publish a list of reports that have been submitted to them in the calendars of their respective houses within five days of their receipt or within the first five legislative days of the biennial and adjourned sessions of the General Assembly, whichever is later.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-20_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>It is the intent of the General Assembly that, except for reports required by interstate compacts and except as otherwise provided by law, whenever an agency is required by law to submit an annual, biennial, or other periodic report to the General Assembly, that requirement shall no longer be required after five years or after five years from the last date that the statutory or session law section containing the report was amended, whichever date is later. In each biennial session, the Office of Legislative Counsel shall prepare for the General Assembly’s review a list of the reports subject to this subsection. A report requirement shall only expire pursuant to legislative enactment.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-21"><akn:num>Section 21</akn:num><akn:heading>Employees; subpoena prohibited</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-21_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>No employee or former employee of the General Assembly may be compelled to give testimony or to appear and produce documentary evidence in a judicial or quasi-judicial proceeding if:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-21_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the testimony or documentary evidence sought relates to a legislative duty or act performed by the employee; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-21_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>neither a member of the General Assembly nor the employee is a party in the proceeding.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-21_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any order or subpoena purporting to compel testimony or the production of evidence that is prohibited under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-21_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section shall be unenforceable.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-21_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Official documents, as defined in subdivision 403</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-21_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title, shall be admissible under V.R.C.P. 44.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-22"><akn:num>Section 22</akn:num><akn:heading>Complaint filed in the Superior Court to compel testimony or production of evidence</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If a person does not comply with a legislative subpoena, a Superior Court may compel the attendance of the person, the giving of testimony, and the production of papers or other evidence, as required by the subpoena.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A person may refuse to comply with a legislative subpoena on the grounds of a valid privilege.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The General Assembly, by a majority vote of those present in either house, or any committee of the General Assembly having subpoena authority by a majority vote of its membership, may initiate proceedings under this section by filing a complaint with the court asking that the witness be so compelled.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The failure of any witness to comply with an order of the court issued under this section shall constitute contempt of court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-23"><akn:num>Section 23</akn:num><akn:heading>Standing committees; authority to meet; out-of-state business</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>During adjournment of the General Assembly, any standing committee or subcommittee of a standing committee may with the appropriate approval of the Speaker or the President Pro Tempore meet at the call of its chair to conduct legislative business within the State.  For attendance at such a meeting or for attendance at a meeting of a special committee or joint committee, a committee member shall be entitled to per diem compensation and expense reimbursement as follows:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>daily compensation at the rate then in effect for members of the General Assembly during a special session;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>actual mileage traveled at the rate paid State employees;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>receipted lodging costs and actual meal costs;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>other actual expenses, as reasonable and necessary.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For attending to official duties out of the State, a member shall be entitled to the same per diem compensation as provided for attendance at sessions of the General Assembly. Reimbursement of necessary and actual expenses for official duties out of the State shall be made from the legislative appropriation to any member of the General Assembly or its staff.  Such reimbursement and per diem compensation shall be in lieu of any other expenses payable by the State to that person during the period he or she is out of the State and shall be contingent upon:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>prior approval of the out-of-state duties by the Speaker of the House in the case of a House member or employee or by the President Pro Tempore of the Senate in the case of a Senator or Senate employee; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>certification of the expense voucher to the Commissioner of Finance and Management by either the Speaker of the House or President Pro Tempore of the Senate in the appropriate case or designee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All per diem and expense claims for attendance at authorized committee meetings shall be submitted with the approval of the committee chair.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-2"><akn:num>Chapter 2</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint Legislative Management Committee</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-41"><akn:num>Section 41</akn:num><akn:heading>Creation of committee; purpose</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-41_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Creation.   There is created the Joint Legislative Management Committee. The Committee shall provide general oversight and management across the offices of the General Assembly and shall coordinate the operations of the Office of Legislative Operations in its delivery of shared administrative services to the legislative offices and the General Assembly.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-41_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Membership.   The Committee shall be composed of the following members:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-41_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>four members of the House, which shall include representation from the Joint Fiscal Committee and the House Rules Committee, and shall consist of:
(A) the Speaker of the House; and
(B) three members of the House appointed by the Speaker, not all from the same political party; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-41_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>four members of the Senate, which shall include representation from the Joint Fiscal Committee and the Senate Rules Committee, and shall consist of:
(A) the President Pro Tempore; and
(B) three members of the Senate appointed by the Committee on Committees, not all from the same political party.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-41_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Appointments and terms.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-41_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Appointments shall be made biennially at the same time as standing committees.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-41_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Members shall serve a term of two years or until their successors are appointed. The term of a member shall end upon his or her ceasing to be a member of the General Assembly.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-41_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Interim vacancies may be filled by appointment by the Committee on Committees or the Speaker of the House in the same manner as in subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-41_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-41_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Meetings.   The Committee shall meet immediately following the appointment of its membership to elect a chair and a vice chair and to organize and conduct its business. The Committee may meet as often as it deems necessary and a majority of the members shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of business. Meetings may be called by the Chair or by a majority of the members.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-41_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Compensation; reimbursement.   For attending a meeting of the Committee when he or she is not receiving compensation as a member of the General Assembly, a member of the Committee shall be entitled to the same per diem compensation and reimbursement for necessary expenses as provided members of standing committees under section 23 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-42"><akn:num>Section 42</akn:num><akn:heading>Oversight and management functions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-42_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Joint Legislative Management Committee shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-42_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>prepare a proposed budget for the Legislative Branch that includes a budget for each legislative office;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-42_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>approve requests for new, permanent positions in staff offices as appropriate, for inclusion in the proposed Legislative Branch budget;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-42_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>approve the reallocation of existing positions among staff offices, as appropriate;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-42_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>approve and adopt policies that apply across the Legislative Branch, including compensation and benefits plans, personnel policies, and policies relating to information technology; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-42_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>attend to other relevant management and oversight matters.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-2_section-42_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Joint Legislative Management Committee shall have access to legal, financial, administrative, information technology, and other services from legislative offices as needed to serve the needs of the Legislative Branch.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-3"><akn:num>Chapter 3</akn:num><akn:heading>Sergeant at Arms</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-61"><akn:num>Section 61</akn:num><akn:heading>Election</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A Sergeant at Arms shall be elected biennially by the Senate and House of Representatives in joint assembly.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62"><akn:num>Section 62</akn:num><akn:heading>Legislative duties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Sergeant at Arms shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>execute orders of either house, the Joint Legislative Management Committee, the Committee on Joint Rules, or the House or Senate Committee on Rules;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>maintain order among spectators and take measures to prevent interruption of either house or any committee thereof;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>arrange for special meetings and conferences at the State House;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>provide for the distribution of mail to all legislators;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>schedule the time for the use of rooms for committee meetings and hearings;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-a_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>maintain the State House and its furnishings in good repair in consultation with the State Curator;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-a_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>provide for the establishment of a cafeteria and supervise its operation;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-a_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>provide security for the State House, pursuant to the responsibilities set forth in 29 V.S.A. § 171; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-a_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>perform such other duties for the benefit of the legislators as may be required by any duly authorized committee thereof.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Sergeant at Arms or any person employed by the Sergeant at Arms shall not accept any compensation or gift for the services of the Sergeant at Arms or any of the employee’s services other than the Sergeant at Arms’ or the employee’s salary, respectively. Any person who violates this provision shall be fined $25.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Sergeant at Arms shall not be responsible for:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>structural repairs or capital improvements to the State House building;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the maintenance of the State House building;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>curating the historic State House and its collections; or</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-c_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the use, upkeep, or maintenance of the State House grounds.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-62_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Sergeant at Arms and employees of the Sergeant at Arms shall seek guidance from and operate in accordance with policies adopted by the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-64"><akn:num>Section 64</akn:num><akn:heading>Employment of assistants; Capitol Police</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-64_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Sergeant at Arms may employ assistants, custodians, doorkeepers, guides, messengers, mail and room assignment clerks, security personnel, pages, and other staff as needed to carry out the Sergeant at Arms’ duties, except that requests for new, permanent positions shall be subject to the approval of the Joint Legislative Management Committee. The Sergeant at Arms shall also appoint Capitol Police officers as set forth in section 70 of this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-64_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All individuals employed by the Sergeant at Arms shall be subject to the personnel policies adopted by the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-64_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The provisions of 3 V.S.A. chapter 13 (classification of State personnel) shall not apply to employees of the Sergeant at Arms unless this exception is partially or wholly waived by the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-67"><akn:num>Section 67</akn:num><akn:heading>Deputy Sergeant at Arms</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The chief doorkeeper of the House of Representatives shall be ex officio Deputy Sergeant at Arms.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-68"><akn:num>Section 68</akn:num><akn:heading>Budget</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Sergeant at Arms shall propose a budget for the Office of Sergeant at Arms to the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-70"><akn:num>Section 70</akn:num><akn:heading>Capitol Police Department</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-70_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Creation.   The Capitol Police Department is created within the Office of the Sergeant at Arms. The Sergeant at Arms shall appoint and may remove, at his or her pleasure, individuals as Capitol Police officers, one of whom shall be appointed to serve as Chief. All such positions shall be exempt State employees. The Chief shall supervise the officer force under the direction of the Sergeant at Arms. Such appointments and all oaths or affirmations shall be in writing and filed with the Sergeant at Arms. An officer shall also serve as a Deputy Sergeant at Arms and as a notary public pursuant to 24 V.S.A. § 442.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-70_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Powers; training.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-70_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A Capitol Police officer shall have all the same powers and authority as sheriffs and other law enforcement officers anywhere in the State, which shall include the authority to arrest persons and enforce the civil and criminal laws, keep the peace, provide security, and serve civil and criminal process. For this purpose, a Capitol Police officer shall subscribe to the same oaths required for sheriffs.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-70_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notwithstanding any other provision of law to the contrary, a Capitol Police officer shall be a Level II or Level III law enforcement officer certified by the Vermont Criminal Justice Council pursuant to the provisions of 20 V.S.A. chapter 151, except that the Chief of the Capitol Police shall be a Level III certified law enforcement officer.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-70_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Coordination of Capitol Complex security.   The Capitol Police Department shall provide security within the State House and assist the Commissioner of Buildings and General Services in providing security and law enforcement services within the Capitol Complex, pursuant to the memorandum of understanding required by 29 V.S.A. § 171</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-70_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Training; equipment.   At State expense and with the approval of the Sergeant at Arms, Capitol Police officers shall be provided with training and furnished uniforms and equipment necessary in the performance of their duties, and such items shall remain the property of the State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-3_section-70_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Strategic plan.   The Sergeant at Arms, in consultation with the Chief, shall prepare, maintain, and update, at least biennially, a strategic plan for the Capitol Police Department, which shall be subject to review and approval by the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-5"><akn:num>Chapter 5</akn:num><akn:heading>Board of Legislative Draftsmen</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-7"><akn:num>Chapter 7</akn:num><akn:heading>Legislative Reference Bureau</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-9"><akn:num>Chapter 9</akn:num><akn:heading>Uniform Legislation</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-9_section-201"><akn:num>Section 201</akn:num><akn:heading>Commission; appointment; term; vacancy</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission heretofore created for the promotion of uniformity of legislation shall consist of four lawyers, to be appointed by the Governor, each of whom shall serve for the term of five years commencing on the first day of February following his or her appointment.  In the month of January, the Governor shall appoint one commissioner to succeed the commissioner whose term so expires.  A vacancy in such office shall be filled by the Governor.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-9_section-202"><akn:num>Section 202</akn:num><akn:heading>Duties; meetings</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission shall examine the subjects of civil marriage and divorce, insolvency, the form of notarial certificates, the descent and distribution of property, the acknowledgment of deeds, the execution and probate of wills, the law of incorporation of business corporations, and other subjects upon which uniformity is desired, and shall confer with the commissioners appointed for the same purpose by other states in drafting uniform laws to be submitted for approval and adoption by the several states.  It shall meet annually with the Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws for the promotion of uniformity of legislation in the United States and join with it in such measures as may be deemed by such Commission expedient to advance the object of such conference.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-9_section-204"><akn:num>Section 204</akn:num><akn:heading>Expenses and funding</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The members of the Commission shall receive necessary expenses incurred in the performance of their duties. Funding to support activities of the Commission shall be provided by the Legislature.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-9_section-205"><akn:num>Section 205</akn:num><akn:heading>Standing committees; administrative rulemaking delegation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-9_section-205_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Whenever a standing committee introduces or amends proposed legislation which delegates rulemaking authority to a State agency, the committee shall express in the legislation and, to the greatest extent possible, the intent of the legislation and the scope of the rulemaking authority being delegated. For all such proposed legislation, the committee shall make a determination, and express such determination in the legislation, as to whether such rulemaking delegation contemplates the adoption of routine technical rules or major substantive rules.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-9_section-205_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For the purposes of this section:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-9_section-205_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Major substantive rules” means rules that require the exercise of significant agency discretion or interpretation in drafting, or, because of their subject matter or anticipated impact, are reasonably expected to result in a significant increase in the cost of doing business, a significant reduction in property values, the loss or significant reduction of government benefits or services, the imposition of State mandates on units of local governments, or other serious burdens on the public or units of local government.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-9_section-205_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Routine technical rules” means procedural rules that establish standards of practice or procedure for the conduct of business with or before an agency, and any other rules that are not major substantive rules. Routine technical rules include forms prescribed by an agency, but do not include fees established by an agency, except fees established or amended by agency rule that are below a cap or within a range established by statute.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-11"><akn:num>Chapter 11</akn:num><akn:heading>Registration of Lobbyists</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-261"><akn:num>Section 261</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-261_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a political contribution;
(ii) anything of value, tangible or intangible, that is bestowed for less than adequate consideration, including travel expenses such as travel fare, room and board, and other expenses associated with travel;
(iii) a meal or alcoholic beverage;
(iv) a ticket, fee, or expenses for or to any sporting, recreational, or entertainment events;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-261_subsec-v"><akn:num>(v)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a speaking fee or honorarium, except actual and reasonable travel expenses;
(vi) a loan made on terms more favorable than those made generally available to the public in the normal course of business.
(B) “Gift” does not mean:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-261_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>anything given between immediate family members;
(ii) printed educational material such as books, reports, pamphlets, or periodicals;
(iii) a gift which is not used and which, within 30 days after receipt, is returned to the donor or for which the donor is reimbursed for its fair market value; and
(iv) a devise or inheritance.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-261_subsec-i_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Legislator” means any member or member-elect of the General Assembly.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-261_subsec-i_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Legislative action” means any action by a legislator with regard to introduction of a bill, resolution, or amendment or with regard to any bill, resolution, amendment, report, appointment, recommendation, nomination, election, proposed or final proposed rule, or other matter proposed for consideration by or pending in the General Assembly or in any committee of the General Assembly.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-261_subsec-i_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Lobby” or “lobbying” means:
(A) to communicate orally or in writing with any legislator or administrative official for the purpose of influencing legislative or administrative action;
(B) solicitation of others to influence legislative or administrative action;
(C) an attempt to obtain the goodwill of a legislator or administrative official by communications or activities with that legislator or administrative official intended ultimately to influence legislative or administrative action; or
(D) activities sponsored by an employer or lobbyist on behalf of or for the benefit of the members of an interest group, if a principal purpose of the activity is to enable such members to communicate orally with one or more legislators or administrative officials for the purpose of influencing legislative or administrative action or to obtain their goodwill.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-261_subsec-i_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Lobbyist” means a person who receives or is entitled to receive, either by employment or contract, $500.00 or more in monetary or in-kind compensation in any calendar year for engaging in lobbying, either personally or through his or her agents, or a person who expends more than $500.00 on lobbying in any calendar year.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-261_subsec-i_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“State officer” means the Governor, Lieutenant Governor, Attorney General, Secretary of State, State Treasurer, and Auditor of Accounts.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-261_subsec-i_subsec-12"><akn:num>(12)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Lobbying firm” means a sole proprietorship, partnership, corporation, limited liability corporation, or unincorporated association which receives or is entitled to receive $500.00 or more in monetary or in-kind compensation for engaging in lobbying, either personally or through its agents, in any calendar year and employs more than one individual lobbyist, contracts with at least one other lobbyist, or is affiliated with at least one other lobbyist.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-261_subsec-i_subsec-13"><akn:num>(13)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Immediate family” means a person’s spouse or civil union partner, parent, sibling, child, or in-law, including a parent, sibling, or child of a spouse or civil union partner.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-262"><akn:num>Section 262</akn:num><akn:heading>Exempted persons</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-262_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a person who engages in lobbying solely by testifying before committees of the General Assembly and agencies, departments, divisions, offices, boards, and commissions of State government and providing information requested by legislators or administrative officials;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-262_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a duly-elected or appointed official or employee of the United States, the State of Vermont, or of any instrumentality, agency, or governmental subdivision of the foregoing, when acting solely in connection with matters relating to the person’s office or public duties. However, if one of the foregoing individuals or entities contracts with a lobbyist, that person or entity, as well as that lobbyist, shall comply with the provisions of this chapter;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-262_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the government of the United States, of the State of Vermont, or of any instrumentality, agency, or political subdivision of the foregoing;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-262_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a person who owns, publishes, or is employed by any news medium while engaged solely in the acquisition or dissemination of news on behalf of the news medium.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263"><akn:num>Section 263</akn:num><akn:heading>Registration of lobbyists and employers; fees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>On forms provided by the Secretary of State, every lobbyist shall register with the Secretary of State before, or within 48 hours of, commencing lobbying activities. A lobbyist shall file a separate registration statement for each of the lobbyist’s employers.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>On forms provided by the Secretary of State, every employer shall register with the Secretary of State before, or within 48 hours of, engaging a lobbyist.  If an employer engages an additional lobbyist, the employer shall file a supplemental registration statement.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A registration statement filed by a lobbyist shall be signed by the lobbyist and shall contain the following information:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The name, mailing address, and telephone number of the lobbyist.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The name of the employer and date of employment for the biennium.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A description of the matters for which lobbying has been engaged by the employer.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-c_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If a lobbyist is compensated, in whole or in part, by an employer for the purpose of lobbying on behalf of another person or group or coalition, the lobbyist shall provide the name of the employer, the name of the person, group, or coalition on whose behalf he or she lobbies, and a description of the matters for which lobbying has been engaged by the employer.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-c_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A current passport-type photograph of the lobbyist.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-c_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All subject areas for which lobbying is performed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A registration statement filed by an employer shall be signed by the employer and shall contain the following information:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the name of the employer;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the trade name, if any, of the employer;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-d_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the mailing address and the telephone number of the employer;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-d_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the contact person for the employer;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-d_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the name and mailing address of each lobbyist engaged by the employer and the date of employment or contract for the biennium.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A registration shall be valid from the date of filing to December 31 of the second year of a biennium, except that a registration may be made in December of an even-numbered year for the ensuing biennium.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Every employer and every lobbyist shall pay an initial registration fee of $60.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An employer shall pay a fee of $15.00 for each lobbyist engaged by the employer. A lobbyist shall pay a fee of $15.00 for each employer represented.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-h"><akn:num>(h)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A person who fails to file on time a statement required by this section shall pay a late registration fee of $25.00 for each day the statement is late, not to exceed $350.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A registration shall be terminated by the Secretary of State upon written notification by the employer or lobbyist that lobbying has ceased by or on behalf of the employer or lobbyist and that the registrant has filed a final disclosure report under section 264 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-263_subsec-j"><akn:num>(j)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of State shall prepare a list of names and addresses of lobbyists and their employers, and the list shall be published at the end of the second legislative week of each regular or adjourned session. Supplemental lists shall be published monthly during the remainder of the legislative session. On or before March 15 of the first year of each legislative biennium, the Secretary of State shall publish no fewer than 500 booklets containing an alphabetical listing of all registered lobbyists, including, at a minimum, a current passport-type photograph of the lobbyist, the lobbyist’s business address, telephone and fax numbers, a list of the lobbyist’s clients, and a subject matter index.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264"><akn:num>Section 264</akn:num><akn:heading>Reports of expenditures, compensation, and gifts; employers; lobbyists</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Every employer and every lobbyist registered or required to be registered under this chapter shall file disclosure reports with the Secretary of State as follows:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>on or before January 15, for the preceding period beginning on September 1 and ending with December 31;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>on or before February 15, for the preceding period beginning on January 1 and ending with January 31;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>on or before March 15, for the preceding period beginning on February 1 and ending with the last day of February;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>on or before April 15, for the preceding period beginning on March 1 and ending with March 31;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>on or before May 15, for the preceding period beginning on April 1 and ending with April 30;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-a_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>on or before June 15, for the preceding period beginning on May 1 and ending with May 31; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-a_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>on or before September 15, for the preceding period beginning on June 1 and ending with August 31.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An employer shall disclose for the period of the report the following information:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A total of all lobbying expenditures made by the employer in each of the following categories:
(A) Advertising, including television, radio, print, and electronic media.
(B) Expenses incurred for telemarketing, polling, or similar activities if the activities are intended, designed, or calculated, directly or indirectly, to influence legislative or administrative action. The report shall specify the amount, the person to whom the amount was paid, and a brief description of the activity.
(C) Contractual agreements in excess of $100.00 per year or direct business relationships that are in existence or were entered into within the previous 12 months between the employer and:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a legislator or administrator;
(ii) a legislator’s or administrator’s spouse; or
(iii) a legislator’s or administrator’s dependent household member.
(D) The total amount of any other lobbying expenditures.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-i_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The total amount of compensation paid to lobbyists or lobbying firms for lobbying. The employer shall report the name and address of each lobbyist or lobbying firm to which the employer pays compensation. It shall be sufficient to include a prorated amount based on the value of the time devoted to lobbying where compensation is to be included for a lobbyist or lobbying firm whose activities under this chapter are incidental to regular employment or other responsibilities to the employer.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-i_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An itemized list of every gift the value of which is greater than $15.00, made by or on behalf of the employer to or at the request of one or more legislators or administrative officials or a member of a legislator’s or administrative official’s immediate family. With respect to each gift, the employer shall report the date the gift was made, the nature of the gift, the value of the gift, the identity of any legislators or administrative officials who requested the gift, and the identity of any recipients of the gift. Monetary gifts, other than political contributions, shall be prohibited.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-i_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A lobbyist shall disclose for the period of the report the following information:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A total of all lobbying expenditures made by the lobbyist in each of the following categories:
(A) Advertising, including television, radio, print, and electronic media.
(B) Expenses incurred for telemarketing, polling, or similar activities if the activities are intended, designed, or calculated, directly or indirectly, to influence legislative or administrative action. The report shall specify the amount, the person to whom the amount was paid, and a brief description of the activity.
(C) Contractual agreements in excess of $100.00 per year or direct business relationships that are in existence or were entered into within the previous 12 months between the lobbyist and:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a legislator or administrator;
(ii) a legislator’s or administrator’s spouse; or
(iii) a legislator’s or administrator’s dependent household member.
(D) The total amount of any other lobbying expenditures.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-i_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The total amount of compensation paid to a lobbyist, who is not employed by, subcontracted by, or affiliated with a lobbying firm, for lobbying, including the name and address of each registered employer who engaged the services of the lobbyist reporting. It shall be sufficient to include a prorated amount based on the value of the time devoted to lobbying where compensation is to be included for a lobbyist whose activities under this chapter are incidental to other responsibilities to the employer. A lobbyist who is employed by, subcontracted by, or affiliated with a lobbying firm shall not report individual compensation. The total compensation paid to the lobbying firm shall be reported pursuant to section 264b of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-i_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An itemized list of every gift, the value of which is greater than $15.00, made by or on behalf of a lobbyist to or at the request of one or more legislators or administrative officials or a member of the legislator’s or administrative official’s immediate family. With respect to each gift, the lobbyist shall report the date the gift was made, the nature of the gift, the value of the gift, the identity of any legislators or administrative officials who requested the gift, and the identity of any recipients of the gift. Monetary gifts, other than political contributions, shall be prohibited.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-i_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Reports for the period July 1 through December 31 shall include, in addition to the totals for the period of the report, totals for the calendar year.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>At the same time a report itemizing gifts is filed, the employer or lobbyist shall mail or deliver a copy of the report to the legislators and administrative officials identified in the report.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If an unsolicited gift is given to a legislator or administrative official by a lobbyist or employer and the recipient does not use it and returns it to the donor within 30 days or the donor is reimbursed for its fair market value, it shall not be considered a “gift” and shall not be required to be reported as such by the donor to the Secretary of State. If the item has already been reported as a gift, the lobbyist or employer shall file an amended report with the Secretary of State.
</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A lobbyist, lobbying firm, or employer who fails to file a disclosure report on time shall pay a late reporting fee of $25.00 for each day the disclosure report is late, not to exceed $350.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264_subsec-j"><akn:num>(j)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A gift from a member of an interest group to, or for the benefit of, a legislator or administrative official, which is made in connection with lobbying as defined in subdivision 261(9)(D) of this title, shall be deemed to be made on behalf of the employer or lobbyist who sponsored the activity and shall be reported and itemized.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264b"><akn:num>Section 264b</akn:num><akn:heading>Lobbying firm listings; reports of expenditures, compensation, and gifts; lobbying firms</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264b_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>On forms provided by the Secretary of State, every lobbying firm shall file a listing of all lobbyists who are employed by, subcontracted by, members of, or affiliated with the lobbying firm within 48 hours of any such lobbyists commencing lobbying activities. The lobbying firm shall file an updated listing within 48 hours of any changes to the listing. Every lobbying firm shall pay an initial listing fee of $150.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264b_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Every lobbying firm shall file a disclosure report on the same day as lobbyist disclosure reports are due under subsection 264</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264b_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title, which shall include:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264b_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A total of all lobbying expenditures made by the lobbying firm in each of the following categories:
(A) Advertising, including television, radio, print, and electronic media.
(B) Expenses incurred for telemarketing, polling, or similar activities if the activities are intended, designed, or calculated, directly or indirectly, to influence legislative or administrative action. The report shall specify the amount, the person to whom the amount was paid, and a brief description of the activity.
(C) Contractual agreements in excess of $100.00 per year or direct business relationships that are in existence or were entered into within the previous 12 months between the lobbying firm and:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264b_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a legislator or administrator;
(ii) a legislator’s or administrator’s spouse; or
(iii) a legislator’s or administrator’s dependent household member.
(D) The total amount of any other lobbying expenditures.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264b_subsec-i_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The total amount of compensation paid to a lobbying firm for lobbying with the name and address of each registered employer who engaged the services of the lobbying firm reporting. It shall be sufficient to include a prorated amount based on the value of the time devoted to lobbying where compensation is to be included for a lobbying firm whose activities under this chapter are incidental to other responsibilities to the employer.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264b_subsec-i_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An itemized list of every gift the value of which is greater than $15.00, made by or on behalf of the lobbying firm to or at the request of one or more legislators or administrative officials or a member of a legislator’s or administrative official’s immediate family. With respect to each gift, the lobbying firm shall report the date the gift was made, the nature of the gift, the value of the gift, the identity of any legislators or administrative officials who requested the gift, and the identity of any recipients of the gift. Monetary gifts, other than political contributions, shall be prohibited.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264b_subsec-i_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c"><akn:num>Section 264c</akn:num><akn:heading>Identification in and report of certain lobbying advertisements</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Identification.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An advertisement that is intended, designed, or calculated to influence legislative action or to solicit others to influence legislative action and that is made at any time prior to final adjournment of a biennial or adjourned legislative session shall contain the name of any lobbyist, lobbying firm, or lobbyist employer that made an expenditure for the advertisement and language that the advertisement was paid for, or paid in part, by the lobbyist, lobbying firm, or lobbyist employer; provided, however:
(A) if there are more than three such names, only the three lobbyists, lobbying firms, or lobbyist employers that made the largest expenditures for the advertisement shall be required to be identified; and
(B) if a lobbyist or lobbying firm made the expenditure on behalf of a lobbyist employer, the identification information set forth in subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection shall be in the name of that lobbyist employer.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>This identification information shall appear prominently and in a manner such that a reasonable person would clearly understand by whom the expenditure has been made.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Report.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In addition to any other reports required to be filed under this chapter, a lobbyist, lobbying firm, or lobbyist employer shall file an advertisement report with the Secretary of State if he, she, or it makes an expenditure or expenditures:
(A) for any advertisement that is described in subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section and that has a cost totaling $1,000.00 or more; or
(B) for any advertising campaign that contains advertisements described in subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section and that has a cost totaling $1,000.00 or more.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The report shall be made for each advertisement or advertising campaign described in subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection and shall identify the lobbyist, lobbying firm, or lobbyist employer that made the expenditure; the amount and date of the expenditure and to whom it was paid; and a brief description of the advertisement or advertising campaign.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The report shall be filed within 48 hours of the expenditure or the advertisement or advertising campaign, whichever occurs first.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If a lobbyist or lobbying firm made an expenditure described in subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection on behalf of a lobbyist employer and that lobbyist or lobbying firm filed the report required by this subsection, the report shall specifically identify the employer on whose behalf the expenditure was made.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Definitions.   As used in this section:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Advertisement” means a notice that appears in any of the following public media: radio, television, newspapers or other periodicals, or Internet websites.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-264c_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Advertising campaign” means advertisements substantially similar in nature, regardless of the media in which they are placed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-265"><akn:num>Section 265</akn:num><akn:heading>Submission of and access to lobbying disclosures</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-265_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of State shall provide on his or her website an online database of the lobbying disclosures required under this chapter.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-265_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In this database, the Secretary shall provide digital access to each form he or she shall provide to enable a person to file the statements or reports required under this chapter. Digital access shall enable such a person to file these lobbying disclosures by completing and submitting the disclosure to the Secretary of State online.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-265_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary shall maintain on the online database all disclosures that have been filed digitally on it so that any person may have direct machine-readable electronic access to the individual data elements in each disclosure and the ability to search those data elements as soon as a disclosure is filed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-265_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any person required to file a disclosure with the Secretary of State under this chapter shall sign it, declare that it is made under the penalties of perjury, and file it digitally on the online database.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-266"><akn:num>Section 266</akn:num><akn:heading>Prohibited conduct</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-266_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>It shall be prohibited conduct:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-266_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>to employ a lobbyist or lobbying firm, or accept employment as a lobbyist or lobbying firm, for compensation that is dependent on a contingency;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-266_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>for a legislator or administrative official to solicit a gift, other than a contribution, from a registered employer or registered lobbyist or a lobbying firm engaged by an employer, except that charitable contributions for nonprofit organizations qualified under 26 U.S.C. § 501</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-266_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>may be solicited from registered employers and registered lobbyists or lobbying firms engaged by an employer; or</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-266_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>when the General Assembly is in session, until adjournment sine die:
(A) for a legislator, a legislator’s candidate’s committee, a legislative leadership political committee, or an administrative official to solicit a contribution from a registered lobbyist, a registered employer, or a lobbying firm engaged by an employer; or
(B) for a registered lobbyist, registered employer, or a lobbying firm engaged by an employer to make or promise a contribution to a legislator, a legislator’s candidate’s committee, or a legislative leadership political committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-266_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-266_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A legislator or an Executive officer, for one year after leaving office, shall not be a lobbyist in this State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-266_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The prohibition set forth in subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-266_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection shall not apply to a lobbyist exempted under section 262 of this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-266_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>As used in this section:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-266_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Candidate’s committee,” “contribution,” and “legislative leadership political committee” shall have the same meanings as in 17 V.S.A. chapter 61 (campaign finance).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-266_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Executive officer” means:
(A) the Governor, Lieutenant Governor, Treasurer, Secretary of State, Auditor of Accounts, or Attorney General; or
(B) under the Office of the Governor, an agency secretary or deputy or a department commissioner or deputy.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-267a"><akn:num>Section 267a</akn:num><akn:heading>Investigations</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Attorney General shall investigate, on his or her own initiative or in response to a complaint filed in writing with the Attorney General, whether a violation of this chapter has occurred. The Attorney General may administer oaths, require filing of a statement under oath, take evidence, and require the production, by subpoena or otherwise, of financial records, books, papers, correspondence, and other documents and records the Attorney General considers to be relevant and material to the investigation. The Attorney General shall make a determination of each complaint filed and, at the time of resolution of a complaint which is found to have merit, shall post on the website of the Office of the Attorney General a brief summary of the complaint and resolution.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-268"><akn:num>Section 268</akn:num><akn:heading>Penalties; enforcement</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-268_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Attorney General shall enforce the provisions of this chapter, and may bring an action in Superior Court to ensure compliance and to obtain civil penalties in the amounts described in subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-268_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-268_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Court may grant temporary and permanent injunctive relief, and may:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-268_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Enjoin future activities.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-268_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Order remedial actions to be taken to effect all registration and disclosure required by this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-268_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Order reimbursement from any lobbyist or employer found to be in violation of this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-11_section-268_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Levy a civil penalty as provided in this subdivision. A civil penalty of not more than $10,000.00 may be levied for each violation. In addition, in the case of a continuing violation, a penalty of not more than $1,000.00 may be imposed for each day the violation continues.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-13"><akn:num>Chapter 13</akn:num><akn:heading>Office of Legislative Counsel</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-401"><akn:num>Section 401</akn:num><akn:heading>Creation and purpose</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Office of Legislative Counsel is created as a permanent agency to serve the General Assembly with nonpartisan legislative drafting, research, and other professional legal and editorial services.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-402"><akn:num>Section 402</akn:num><akn:heading>Director and Chief Counsel; employees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-402_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Joint Legislative Management Committee shall employ an individual to be the Director and Chief Counsel of the Office of Legislative Counsel. The Committee may conduct the hiring process itself or it may delegate this duty to a special hiring committee comprising an equal number of members from the House and Senate, not all of whom shall be from the same political party; however, the Joint Legislative Management Committee shall make the final hiring decision.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-402_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-402_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Director and Chief Counsel shall employ legal, editorial, and other professional staff as needed to carry out the duties of the Office of Legislative Counsel, except that requests for new, permanent positions shall be subject to the approval of the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-402_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All individuals employed by the Office of Legislative Counsel shall be subject to the personnel policies adopted by the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-402_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The provisions of 3 V.S.A. chapter 13 (classification of State personnel) shall not apply to employees of the Office of Legislative Counsel.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-403"><akn:num>Section 403</akn:num><akn:heading>Functions; confidentiality</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-403_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Office of Legislative Counsel shall provide legal services to the General Assembly and its staff, including:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-403_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>drafting bills, resolutions, amendments, and other legal documents;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-403_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>providing legal research and analysis in relation to current or anticipated legislative matters;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-403_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>providing policy analysis of current or anticipated legislative matters;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-403_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>maintaining a reference library;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-403_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>maintaining confidential documents and other confidential materials provided to or generated by the Office in the course of business;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-403_subsec-a_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>providing contracting and other legal services to the Joint Legislative Management Committee and other legislative offices; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-403_subsec-a_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>furnishing such other information and legal assistance with respect to legislative matters as may be required by a member, member-elect, committee or similar entity of the General Assembly, a chamber of the General Assembly, or the General Assembly as a whole, in the performance of its duties.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-403_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-403_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All requests for legal assistance, information, and advice from the Office of Legislative Counsel; all information received in connection with research or drafting; and all confidential materials provided to or generated by the Office shall remain confidential unless the party requesting or providing the information or material designates that it is not confidential.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-403_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Recordings and minutes of committee meetings, bills and amendments that have been approved for printing or introduction, and material appearing in the journals or calendars of either house are official documents and materials and shall not be confidential under this subsection.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-404"><akn:num>Section 404</akn:num><akn:heading>Budget</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Director and Chief Counsel shall propose a budget for the Office of Legislative Counsel to the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-405"><akn:num>Section 405</akn:num><akn:heading>Intergovernmental cooperation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>For the purposes of carrying out its duties, the Office of Legislative Counsel shall have access to and the right to copy any public record of all executive, administrative, and judicial departments of the State, except income and franchise tax returns and other documents classified as confidential by law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-421"><akn:num>Section 421</akn:num><akn:heading>Office of Legislative Counsel; statutory publication and revision duties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-421_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Office of Legislative Counsel shall continuously maintain and update a formal topical revision of existing permanent statutory law to be known as the Vermont Statutes Annotated. The topical revision shall be arranged in a systematic and annotated form that is consolidated into the smallest practical number of volumes and indexes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-421_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Office of Legislative Counsel, on behalf of the State of Vermont, shall hold the copyright to the Vermont Statutes Annotated.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-422"><akn:num>Section 422</akn:num><akn:heading>Contract for preparation of Vermont Statutes Annotated</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-422_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Office of Legislative Counsel shall contract with a competent legal publisher to revise and publish the Vermont Statutes Annotated.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-422_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The contract for publishing the Vermont Statutes Annotated shall provide for the annual editing and publishing of cumulative pocket part supplements after each biennial and adjourned legislative session for the duration of the contract. The cumulative pocket part supplements shall include all codified laws enacted during the concluded biennial or adjourned session of the General Assembly, and during any special session that has occurred since the last annual publication. Each edition of the cumulative pocket part supplements to the Vermont Statutes Annotated shall include all annotations of constructions of the Vermont Supreme Court and all federal courts of the United States, available at the closing date of each edition of the pocket parts.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-422_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The contracted publisher shall, as provided in the contract, publish replacement volumes of existing titles, or separate volumes of new titles, of the Vermont Statutes Annotated.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-423"><akn:num>Section 423</akn:num><akn:heading>Acceptance as evidence of law</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-423_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Office of Legislative Counsel shall require the contracted publisher to deliver the cumulative pocket parts and separate supplements to the Vermont Statutes Annotated prior to the convening of the next session of the General Assembly, which shall include a certificate of authenticity that the Office of Legislative Counsel shall issue. The certificate shall entitle the statutes contained in the cumulative pocket parts and separate supplements to admission in all the courts of Vermont as prima facie evidence of the law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-423_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Office of Legislative Counsel shall require the contracted publisher to deliver new and replacement volumes of the Vermont Statutes Annotated with a certificate of authenticity that the Office of Legislative Counsel shall issue. The certificate shall entitle the statutes contained in the new and replacement volumes to admission in all the courts of Vermont as prima facie evidence of the law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-423_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A certificate of authority issued by the Statutory Revision Commission pursuant to the authority of the former 1 V.S.A. § 4 shall continue to entitle a cumulative pocket part and separate supplement, or a new and replacement volume, for which it was issued to admission in all the courts of Vermont as prima facie evidence of the law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-423_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Vermont Statutes Annotated may be cited as “V.S.A.”</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-424"><akn:num>Section 424</akn:num><akn:heading>Office of Legislative Counsel; revision authority</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-424_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>renumber and rearrange sections or parts of sections;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-424_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>transfer sections or divide sections so as to give separate section numbers to distinct subject matters, but without changing the meaning;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-424_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>insert or change the wording of headnotes;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-424_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>change reference numbers to agree with renumbered chapters or sections;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-424_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>substitute the proper section or chapter number for the terms “this act,” “the preceding section,” and similar terms;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-424_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>strike out figures where they are merely a repetition of written words and vice versa;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-424_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>change capitalization, effect gender neutrality, and make other grammatical corrections for the purpose of conformity with the style of the Vermont Statutes Annotated;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-424_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>correct manifest typographical and grammatical errors;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-424_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>make any changes in any of the forms provided as guides that may be necessitated by changes in the substantive law;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-424_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>correct the names of agencies, departments, and similar units of State government; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-424_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>make any other purely formal or clerical changes in keeping with the purposes of revision.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-425"><akn:num>Section 425</akn:num><akn:heading>Statutory databases</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Office of Legislative Counsel, in collaboration with the Office of Legislative Information Technology, shall maintain computerized databases of the Vermont Statutes Annotated, which shall be posted on the General Assembly’s website. The databases shall include the enactment history of a codified statutory section, but shall not maintain the revisor’s notes, the judicial annotations added by the publisher, or the Acts and Resolves.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-13_section-426"><akn:num>Section 426</akn:num><akn:heading>Annual statutory revision legislation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Annually, on or before February 1, the Office of Legislative Counsel may prepare and submit to the General Assembly a bill that proposes recommendations of any additions, repeals, or amendments to the existing statutes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-14"><akn:num>Chapter 14</akn:num><akn:heading>Office of Human Resources</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-461"><akn:num>Section 461</akn:num><akn:heading>Creation and purpose</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Office of Human Resources is created as a permanent agency to service the members and employees of the General Assembly with nonpartisan human resources services.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-462"><akn:num>Section 462</akn:num><akn:heading>Director; employees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-462_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Joint Legislative Management Committee shall employ an individual with experience and expertise in human resources management to be the Director of Human Resources. The Committee may conduct the hiring process itself or may delegate this duty to a special hiring committee comprising an equal number of members from the House and Senate, not all of whom shall be from the same political party; however, the Joint Legislative Management Committee shall make the final hiring decision.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-462_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-462_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Director of Human Resources shall employ human resources and other professional staff as needed to carry out the duties of the Office of Human Resources, except that requests for new, permanent positions shall be subject to the approval of the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-462_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All individuals employed by the Office of Human Resources shall be subject to the personnel policies adopted by the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-462_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The provisions of 3 V.S.A. chapter 13 (classification of State personnel) shall not apply to employees of the Office of Human Resources.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-463"><akn:num>Section 463</akn:num><akn:heading>Functions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-463_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>developing, in consultation with the heads of the other legislative offices, compensation and benefits plans and personnel policies for legislative offices and employees for Joint Legislative Management Committee approval and providing advice, guidance, and technical assistance in the administration of these plans and policies;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-463_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>providing training on topics such as the prevention of harassment and discrimination, implicit bias, time management, and other workplace issues;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-463_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>providing job recruitment services to other legislative offices;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-463_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>providing performance evaluation services to other legislative offices;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-463_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>providing advice and guidance to legislative employees, supervisors, and members of the General Assembly regarding labor and employment laws, policies, and practices;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-463_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>coordinating legislative internship opportunities, including registering legislative interns and developing and implementing internship policies and procedures;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-463_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>developing processes for investigating and resolving disputes and other interpersonal issues involving members of the General Assembly or legislative employees, or both;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-463_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>investigating and resolving, and providing guidance and assistance with investigating and resolving, employee disputes and other personnel matters; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-463_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>providing guidance and assistance with investigating and resolving conflicts involving members of the General Assembly.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-464"><akn:num>Section 464</akn:num><akn:heading>Budget</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Director of Human Resources shall propose a budget for the Office of Human Resources to the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-14_section-465"><akn:num>Section 465</akn:num><akn:heading>Intergovernmental cooperation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>For the purposes of carrying out its duties, the Office of Human Resources shall have access to and the right to copy any public record of all executive, administrative, and judicial departments of the State, except income and franchise tax returns and other documents classified as confidential by law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-15"><akn:num>Chapter 15</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint Fiscal Committee; Joint Fiscal Office</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-501"><akn:num>Section 501</akn:num><akn:heading>Creation of Committee; purpose</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-501_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There is created a Joint Fiscal Committee whose membership shall be appointed on or before January 15 of each biennial session of the General Assembly. The Committee shall consist of five Representatives and five Senators as follows:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-501_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Chair of the House Committee on Appropriations;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-501_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Chair of the House Committee on Ways and Means;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-501_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Chair of the Senate Committee on Appropriations;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-501_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Chair of the Senate Committee on Finance;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-501_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>two members of the House, not both from the same political party, appointed by the Speaker of the House;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-501_subsec-a_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>two members of the Senate, not both from the same political party, appointed by the Committee on Committees; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-501_subsec-a_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>one member of the Senate to be appointed by the Committee on Committees and one member of the House to be appointed by the Speaker.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-501_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Joint Fiscal Committee shall meet immediately following the appointment of its membership to organize and conduct its business. The Committee shall elect a chair, vice chair, and clerk and shall adopt rules of procedure. The Committee may meet at any time at the call of the Chair or a majority of the members of the Committee. A majority of the membership shall constitute a quorum.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-501_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For attendance at a meeting when the General Assembly is not in session, members of the Joint Fiscal Committee shall be entitled to the same per diem compensation and reimbursement for actual and necessary expenses as provided members of standing committees under section 23 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-503"><akn:num>Section 503</akn:num><akn:heading>Functions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-503_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>hire the Chief Fiscal Officer;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-503_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>carry on a continuing review of the fiscal operations of the State, including revenues, budgeting, and expenditures;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-503_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>accept grants and approve any related limited service positions, gifts, loans, or any other thing of value, approved by the Governor, under the provisions of 32 V.S.A. § 5;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-503_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>establish prioritization for the work of the Joint Fiscal Office; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-503_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>keep minutes of its meetings and maintain a file thereof.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-521"><akn:num>Section 521</akn:num><akn:heading>Creation and purpose</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Joint Fiscal Office is created as a permanent agency to provide the General Assembly with services relating to the fiscal operations of the State, including revenues, budgeting, and expenditures.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-522"><akn:num>Section 522</akn:num><akn:heading>Chief Fiscal Officer; employees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-522_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-522_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Joint Fiscal Committee shall employ an individual to be the Chief Fiscal Officer of the Joint Fiscal Office.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-522_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Chief Fiscal Officer shall employ fiscal, research, and other professional staff as needed to carry out the duties of the Joint Fiscal Office, except that requests for new, permanent positions shall be subject to the approval of the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-522_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All individuals employed by the Joint Fiscal Office shall be subject to the personnel policies adopted by the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-522_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The provisions of 3 V.S.A. chapter 13 (classification of State personnel) shall not apply to employees of the Joint Fiscal Office unless this exception is partially or wholly waived by the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-523"><akn:num>Section 523</akn:num><akn:heading>Functions; confidentiality</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-523_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Joint Fiscal Office shall furnish:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-523_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>nonpartisan research and administrative services of a fiscal nature to the Joint Fiscal Committee and, at the direction of the Joint Fiscal Committee, to the House and Senate Committees on Appropriations, the Senate Committee on Finance, the House Committee on Ways and Means, the House and Senate Committees on Transportation, the House Committee on Corrections and Institutions, and the Senate Committee on Institutions;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-523_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>nonpartisan research and administrative services of a fiscal nature to other legislative committees and members of the General Assembly, to the extent practicable; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-523_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>fiscal and budget assistance to the Joint Legislative Management Committee and to the other legislative offices.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-523_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-523_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All requests for assistance, information, and advice from the Joint Fiscal Office, all information received in connection with fiscal research or related drafting, and all confidential materials provided to or generated by the Joint Fiscal Office shall remain confidential unless the party requesting or providing the information designates that it is not confidential.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-523_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Recordings and minutes of committee meetings and material appearing in the journals or calendars of either house are official documents and materials and shall not be confidential under this subsection.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-524"><akn:num>Section 524</akn:num><akn:heading>Budget</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Chief Fiscal Officer shall propose a budget for the Joint Fiscal Office to the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-525"><akn:num>Section 525</akn:num><akn:heading>Intergovernmental cooperation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>For the purposes of carrying out its duties, the Joint Fiscal Office shall have access to and the right to copy any public record of all executive, administrative, and judicial departments of the State, except income and franchise tax returns and other documents classified as confidential by law unless permitted under 32 V.S.A. § 3102.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-526"><akn:num>Section 526</akn:num><akn:heading>Basic needs budget and livable wage; report</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-526_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For the purposes of this section:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-526_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Basic needs” means the essentials needed to run a household, including food, housing, transportation, child care, utilities, health and dental care, taxes, rental and life insurance, personal expenses, and savings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-526_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Basic needs budget” is the amount of money needed by a Vermont household to maintain a basic standard of living, calculated using current State and federal data sources for the costs of basic needs.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-526_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Livable wage” means the hourly wage required for a full-time worker to pay for one-half of the basic needs budget for a two-person household with no children and employer-assisted health insurance averaged for both urban and rural areas.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-526_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>On or before January 15 of each new legislative biennium, beginning in 2009, the Joint Fiscal Office shall report the calculated basic needs budgets of various representative household configurations and the calculated livable wage for the previous year. This calculation may serve as an additional indicator of wage and other economic conditions in the State and shall not be considered official State guidance on wages or other forms of compensation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-526_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The methodology for calculating basic needs budgets shall be built on methodology described in the November 9, 1999 Livable Income Study Committee report, modified as appropriate by any statutory changes made by the General Assembly and subsequent modifications adopted by the Joint Fiscal Committee under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-526_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-526_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Joint Fiscal Committee may adopt modifications to the methodology used to determine the basic needs budget calculations under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-15_section-526_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section to account for public policy changes, data availability, or any other factors that have had an impact on any aspects of the methodology. Changes or revisions in methodology adopted by the Committee shall be effective no later than November in the year preceding the release of the report.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-16"><akn:num>Chapter 16</akn:num><akn:heading>Office of Legislative Operations</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-16_section-551"><akn:num>Section 551</akn:num><akn:heading>Creation and purpose</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Office of Legislative Operations is created as a permanent agency to serve the members and employees of the General Assembly with nonpartisan operational, financial, committee support, and other administrative services and to support the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-16_section-552"><akn:num>Section 552</akn:num><akn:heading>Director; employees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-16_section-552_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Joint Legislative Management Committee shall employ an individual with experience and expertise in administration or management to be the Director of Legislative Operations. The Committee may conduct the hiring process itself or it may delegate this duty to a special hiring committee comprising an equal number of members from the House and Senate, not all of whom shall be from the same political party; however, the Joint Legislative Management Committee shall make the final hiring decision.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-16_section-552_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-16_section-552_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Director of Legislative Operations shall employ administrative, committee services, and other professional staff as needed to carry out the duties of the Office of Legislative Operations, except that requests for new, permanent positions shall be subject to the approval of the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-16_section-552_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All individuals employed by the Office of Legislative Operations shall be subject to the personnel policies adopted by the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-16_section-552_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The provisions of 3 V.S.A. chapter 13 (classification of State personnel) shall not apply to employees of the Office of Legislative Operations.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-16_section-553"><akn:num>Section 553</akn:num><akn:heading>Functions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-16_section-553_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>administrative support to the Joint Legislative Management Committee;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-16_section-553_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>administrative support to other standing and interim legislative committees;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-16_section-553_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>payroll, billing, and expense reimbursement services to members of the General Assembly and, as needed, to other legislative offices and legislative employees; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-16_section-553_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>other administrative and operational services as needed to support members of the General Assembly, legislative offices, and legislative employees.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-16_section-554"><akn:num>Section 554</akn:num><akn:heading>Budget</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Director of Legislative Operations shall propose a budget for the Office of Legislative Operations to the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-16_section-555"><akn:num>Section 555</akn:num><akn:heading>Intergovernmental cooperation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>For the purposes of carrying out its duties, the Office of Legislative Operations shall have access to and the right to copy any public record of all executive, administrative, and judicial departments of the State, except income and franchise tax returns and other documents classified as confidential by law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-17"><akn:num>Chapter 17</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint Carbon Emissions Reduction Committee</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-17_section-601"><akn:num>Section 601</akn:num><akn:heading>Creation of Committee</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-17_section-601_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There is created a Joint Carbon Emissions Reduction Committee whose membership shall be appointed each biennial session of the General Assembly. The Committee shall consist of five Representatives, at least one from the Committees on Appropriations, on Commerce and Economic Development, on Energy and Technology, and on Transportation, to be appointed by the Speaker of the House, and five members of the Senate, at least one from the Committees on Appropriations, on Finance, on Natural Resources and Energy, and on Transportation, to be appointed by the Committee on Committees.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-17_section-601_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee shall elect a chair and vice chair. The Chair shall rotate biennially between the House and the Senate members. The Committee may meet during a session of the General Assembly at the call of the Chair and with the approval of the Speaker of the House and the President Pro Tempore of the Senate. The Committee may meet up to five times during adjournment. A majority of the membership shall constitute a quorum.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-17_section-601_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Office of Legislative Counsel and the Office of Legislative Operations shall provide legal, professional, and administrative assistance to the Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-17_section-601_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For attendance at a meeting when the General Assembly is not in session, members of the Committee shall be entitled to the same per diem compensation and expense reimbursement as provided members of standing committees pursuant to section 23 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-17_section-603"><akn:num>Section 603</akn:num><akn:heading>Duties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Joint Carbon Emissions Reduction Committee shall provide oversight when the General Assembly is not in session of State policies and activities concerning and affecting carbon emissions from Vermont’s electric, residential and commercial buildings, and transportation sectors.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-18"><akn:num>Chapter 18</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint Information Technology Oversight Committee</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-18_section-614"><akn:num>Section 614</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint Information Technology Oversight Committee</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-18_section-614_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Creation.   There is created the Joint Information Technology Oversight Committee to oversee investments in and use of information technology in Vermont and to provide periodic advice on legislative information technology issues.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-18_section-614_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Membership.   The Committee shall be composed of six members as follows:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-18_section-614_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>three members of the House of Representatives, not all of whom shall be from the same political party, who shall be appointed by the Speaker of the House; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-18_section-614_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>three members of the Senate, not all of whom shall be from the same political party, who shall be appointed by the Committee on Committees.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-18_section-614_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Powers and duties.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-18_section-614_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee shall oversee, evaluate, and make recommendations on the following:
(A) the State’s current deployment, management, and oversight of information technology in the furtherance of State governmental activities, including data processing systems, telecommunications networks, and related technologies, particularly with regard to issues of compatibility among existing and proposed technologies;
(B) issues related to the storage of, maintenance of, access to, privacy of, and restrictions on use of computerized records;
(C) issues of public policy related to the development and promotion of the private, commercial, and nonprofit information infrastructure in the State, its relationship to the State government information infrastructure, and its integration with national and international information networks; and
(D) cybersecurity.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-18_section-614_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee may provide advice to the Director of Legislative Information Technology and the Joint Legislative Management Committee as appropriate regarding matters related to legislative information technology.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-18_section-614_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Assistance.   The Committee shall have the administrative, technical, and legal assistance of the Office of Legislative Counsel, the Office of Legislative Operations, and the Joint Fiscal Office.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-18_section-614_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Meetings.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-18_section-614_subsec-e_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee shall elect a chair and vice chair from among its members and shall adopt rules of procedure. The Chair shall rotate biennially between the House and Senate members.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-18_section-614_subsec-e_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A majority of the membership shall constitute a quorum.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-18_section-614_subsec-e_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee may meet when the General Assembly is not in session or at the call of the Chair.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-18_section-614_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Reimbursement.   For attendance at meetings during adjournment of the General Assembly, members of the Committee shall be entitled to per diem compensation and reimbursement of expenses pursuant to section 23 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-19"><akn:num>Chapter 19</akn:num><akn:heading>Legislative Advisory Committee on the State House</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-651"><akn:num>Section 651</akn:num><akn:heading>Legislative Advisory Committee on the State House</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-651_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Legislative Advisory Committee on the State House is created.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-651_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee shall be composed of 12 members:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-651_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>three members of the House of Representatives, appointed biennially by the Speaker of the House;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-651_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>three members of the Senate, appointed biennially by the Committee on Committees;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-651_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Chair of the Board of Trustees of the Friends of the Vermont State House;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-651_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Director of the Vermont Historical Society;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-651_subsec-b_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Director of the Vermont Arts Council;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-651_subsec-b_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Commissioner of Buildings and General Services or designee;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-651_subsec-b_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Sergeant at Arms; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-651_subsec-b_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the State Curator.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-651_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee shall biennially elect a chair from among its legislative members. A quorum shall consist of seven members.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-651_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee shall meet at least one time when the General Assembly is in session. When the General Assembly is not in session, the Committee shall meet at least one time, but the Committee and any subcommittees shall not cumulatively meet more than six times per year; provided, however, that the Committee and any subcommittees of the Committee may meet more often with the approval of the Speaker of the House and the President Pro Tempore of the Senate. The Commissioner of Buildings and General Services shall keep minutes of the meetings and maintain a file thereof.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-651_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee shall have the assistance of the Office of Legislative Counsel and the Office of Legislative Operations.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-651_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A member of the Committee shall not vote on a matter under consideration by the Committee regarding any activities or duties the member is responsible for discharging.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-652"><akn:num>Section 652</akn:num><akn:heading>Per diem and expenses; legislative members</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>For meetings held during adjournment of the General Assembly, the legislative members of the Committee shall be entitled to per diem compensation and expense reimbursement as provided in section 23 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-653"><akn:num>Section 653</akn:num><akn:heading>Functions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-653_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-653_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>review, coordinate, and make recommendations on all activities relating to the collections and care of art, historic artifacts, and furnishings and the refurbishing, renovation, preservation, and expansion of the building and its interior; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-653_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>approve a collections policy for the State House collection, as developed by the State Curator pursuant to 29 V.S.A. § 154a</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-653_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Sergeant at Arms and the Commissioner of Buildings and General Services, in discharging responsibilities under subdivision 62</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-653_subsec-b_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title and 29 V.S.A. §§ 154</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-19_section-653_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>and 154a, respectively, shall consider the recommendations of the Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-20"><akn:num>Chapter 20</akn:num><akn:heading>Health Reform Oversight Committee</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-691"><akn:num>Section 691</akn:num><akn:heading>Committee creation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-691_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Chair of the House Committee on Appropriations;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-691_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Chair of the Senate Committee on Appropriations;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-691_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Chair of the House Committee on Ways and Means;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-691_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Chair of the Senate Committee on Finance;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-691_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Chair of the House Committee on Health Care;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-691_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Chair of the Senate Committee on Health and Welfare;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-691_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Chair of the House Committee on Human Services; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-691_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>one member of the Senate appointed by the Committee on Committees.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-692"><akn:num>Section 692</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers and duties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-692_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When the General Assembly is adjourned, the Committee shall provide legislative oversight and review of revenue collection, expenditures, and planning related to health care reform efforts in Vermont.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-692_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When the General Assembly is adjourned during fiscal year 2015, the Commissioner of Vermont Health Access shall provide monthly updates regarding Vermont Health Benefit Exchange operations, enrollment data, coverage status, customer support, and Exchange website functionality.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-692_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Effective on January 1, 2015, all reports previously submitted to the Health Care Oversight Committee shall be submitted to the Health Reform Oversight Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-693"><akn:num>Section 693</akn:num><akn:heading>Assistance</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-693_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee shall have the administrative, technical, and legal assistance of the Office of Legislative Counsel, the Office of Legislative Operations, and the Joint Fiscal Office.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-693_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-693_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of Administration and other members of the Executive Branch shall report to the Committee upon request.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-693_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If applicable, the Secretary shall submit an electronic report to the Joint Fiscal Office for distribution to members of the Committee that summarizes any plans or actions taken by the Executive Branch to delay health care reform project schedules as a result of:
(A) increased costs exceeding official estimates;
(B) [Repealed.]
(C) changes in the availability of federal funding; or
(D) any other changes related to the planning for and implementation of health care reform as directed by 2011 Acts and Resolves No. 48.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-694"><akn:num>Section 694</akn:num><akn:heading>Meetings</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-694_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee shall select a Chair from among its members at the first meeting of each biennium.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-694_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Meetings shall be convened by the Chair and when practicable shall be held in conjunction with meetings of the Joint Fiscal Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-694_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-694_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A majority of the members of the Committee shall be physically present at the same location to constitute a quorum.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-694_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A member may vote only if physically present at the meeting location.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-694_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Action shall be taken only if there is both a quorum and a majority vote of the members physically present and voting.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-20_section-695"><akn:num>Section 695</akn:num><akn:heading>Reimbursement</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>For attendance at meetings during adjournment of the General Assembly, members of the Committee shall be entitled to per diem compensation and reimbursement of expenses pursuant to section 406 of this title for no more than six meetings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-21"><akn:num>Chapter 21</akn:num><akn:heading>Office of Legislative Information Technology</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-701"><akn:num>Section 701</akn:num><akn:heading>Creation and purpose</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Office of Legislative Information Technology is created as a permanent agency to serve the members and employees of the General Assembly with information technology resources and nonpartisan technology-related services.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-702"><akn:num>Section 702</akn:num><akn:heading>Director; employees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-702_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Joint Legislative Management Committee shall employ an individual with experience and expertise in information technology to be the Director of Legislative Information Technology. The Committee may conduct the hiring process itself or it may delegate this duty to a special hiring committee comprising an equal number of members from the House and Senate, not all of whom shall be from the same political party; however, the Joint Legislative Management Committee shall make the final hiring decision.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-702_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-702_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Director shall employ additional information technology staff as needed to carry out the duties of the Office of Legislative Information Technology, except that requests for new, permanent positions shall be subject to the approval of the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-702_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All individuals employed by the Office of Legislative Information Technology shall be subject to the personnel policies adopted by the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-702_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The provisions of 3 V.S.A. chapter 13 (classification of State personnel) shall not apply to employees of the Office of Legislative Information Technology unless this exception is partially or wholly waived by the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-703"><akn:num>Section 703</akn:num><akn:heading>Functions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-703_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>design, support, and maintain the General Assembly’s information systems;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-703_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>provide hardware, software, and customer support to members and employees of the General Assembly to enable them to fulfill their professional responsibilities; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-703_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>ensure that legislative records created, received, stored, or transmitted using information technology are maintained in accordance with the General Assembly’s recordkeeping requirements.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-704"><akn:num>Section 704</akn:num><akn:heading>Strategic plan for legislative information technology</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-704_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Director of Legislative Information Technology shall prepare, maintain, and update, at least biennially, a long-range strategic plan for information technology operations and services in the Legislative Branch.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-704_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In preparing the plan, the Director or designee shall consult with members of the Joint Information Technology Oversight Committee, other members of the General Assembly, and employees of other legislative staff offices. In addition, the Director or designee may also consult with the State Archivist, representatives of the Executive and Judicial Branches, and members of the public.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-704_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The strategic plan shall be subject to review and approval by the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-705"><akn:num>Section 705</akn:num><akn:heading>Contracts for Internet service</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Every contract for broadband Internet access service, as defined in 3 V.S.A. § 348(d)(1), for the Legislative Branch shall include terms and conditions requiring that the Internet service provider certify that it is in compliance with the consumer protection and net neutrality standards established in 3 V.S.A. § 348.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-21_section-706"><akn:num>Section 706</akn:num><akn:heading>Budget</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Director of Legislative Information Technology shall propose a budget for the Office of Legislative Information Technology to the Joint Legislative Management Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-22"><akn:num>Chapter 22</akn:num><akn:heading>Legislative Information Technology Committee</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-23"><akn:num>Chapter 23</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint Legislative Justice Oversight Committee</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-801"><akn:num>Section 801</akn:num><akn:heading>Creation of Committee</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-801_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There is created a Joint Legislative Justice Oversight Committee whose membership shall be appointed each biennial session of the General Assembly. The Committee shall exercise oversight over the Department of Corrections and work with and provide assistance to other legislative committees on matters related to juvenile justice and criminal justice policies.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-801_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee shall be composed of 10 members: five members of the House of Representatives, who shall not all be from the same party, appointed by the Speaker of the House; and five members of the Senate, who shall not all be from the same party, appointed by the Committee on Committees. In addition to one member-at-large appointed from each chamber, one appointment shall be made from each of the House and Senate Committees on Appropriations and on Judiciary, the Senate Committees on Health and Welfare and on Institutions, and the House Committees on Corrections and Institutions and on Human Services.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-801_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee shall elect a chair, vice chair, and clerk from among its members and shall adopt rules of procedure. The Chair shall rotate biennially between the House and the Senate members. The Committee shall keep minutes of its meetings and maintain a file thereof. A quorum shall consist of six members.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-801_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When the General Assembly is in session, the Committee shall meet at the call of the Chair. The Committee may meet six times during adjournment, and may meet more often subject to approval of the Speaker of the House and the President Pro Tempore of the Senate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-801_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For attendance at a meeting when the General Assembly is not in session, members of the Committee shall be entitled to compensation for services and reimbursement of expenses as provided under subsection 23</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-801_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-801_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The professional and clerical services of the Joint Fiscal Office, the Office of Legislative Operations, and the Office of Legislative Counsel shall be available to the Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-802"><akn:num>Section 802</akn:num><akn:heading>Duties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-802_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In addition to the general responsibilities set forth in subsection 801</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-802_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title, the Committee shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-802_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>review and make recommendations regarding the Department of Corrections’ strategic, operating, and capital plans;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-802_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>review and make recommendations to the House and Senate Committees on Appropriations regarding departmental budget proposals;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-802_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>provide general oversight on departmental policy development;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-802_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>encourage improved communication between the Department and other relevant components of the administrative branch and the criminal justice system;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-802_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>evaluate the statewide system of pretrial services, court diversion programs, community justice center services, and other relevant programs and services, and determine whether there is variation in policies, procedures, practices, and results among different areas of the State and the causes of any such variation;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-802_subsec-a_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>make recommendations to the General Assembly regarding the creation of a consistent and cost-efficient statewide juvenile justice system and criminal justice system;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-802_subsec-a_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>review and make recommendations to the General Assembly to ensure the juvenile justice and criminal justice statutes reflect principles of restorative justice; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-802_subsec-a_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>review and make recommendations to the General Assembly regarding the timeliness of judicial proceedings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-23_section-802_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-24"><akn:num>Chapter 24</akn:num><akn:heading>Health Care Oversight Committee</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-25"><akn:num>Chapter 25</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint Legislative Commission on Health Care Reform</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-26"><akn:num>Chapter 26</akn:num><akn:heading>National Legislative Association on Prescription Drug Prices</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-28"><akn:num>Chapter 28</akn:num><akn:heading>Government Accountability Committee</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970"><akn:num>Section 970</akn:num><akn:heading>Government Accountability Committee</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There is created the joint legislative Government Accountability Committee. The Committee shall recommend mechanisms for State government to be more forward-thinking, strategic, and responsive to the long-term needs of Vermonters. In pursuit of this goal, the Committee shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Propose areas for the review of statutory mandates for public services that may result in service duplication and to review the alignment of financial and staff resources required to carry out those mandates.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Review the legislative process for the creation and elimination of programs and make recommendations for enhancements to the process that support greater long-range planning and responsiveness to the needs of Vermonters.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Recommend strategies and tools that permit all branches of State government to prioritize the investment of federal, State, and local resources in programs that respond to the needs of the citizens of Vermont in a collaborative, cost-effective, and efficient manner. Pursuant to those strategies and tools, functions that are not critical to an agency or department mission may be recommended for combination or elimination, while other functions may be optimized.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Determine that data-based program-level performance measures that demonstrate program results have been adopted for the programs in each agency and department.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-a_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Determine whether each agency and department is taking actions to achieve the population-level outcomes set forth in 3 V.S.A. § 2311 that are relevant to that agency or department, as shown by the manner in which the agency’s or department’s program-level performance measures inform population-level indicators.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-a_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Ensure that the report set forth in 3 V.S.A. § 2311 regarding population-level outcomes and indicators and each agency’s or department’s program-level performance measures are transparent and readily accessible to the public via electronic publication.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-a_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Assess the effectiveness of population-level indicators in measuring progress in achieving population-level outcomes, and annually review population-level indicators in the context of new data development.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-a_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Approve the addition, amendment, or elimination of population-level indicators in accordance with 3 V.S.A. § 2311</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-a_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-a_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Assess whether and how the State of Vermont should provide funds to nonprofit organizations, including whether grants to or contracts with nonprofit organizations should require results-based accountability.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The membership of the Committee shall be appointed each biennial session of the General Assembly. The Committee shall comprise eight members:
(A) four members of the House of Representatives appointed by the Speaker of the House who shall not all be from the same party and at least one of whom shall be from the Committee on Government Operations; and
(B) four members of the Senate appointed by the Committee on Committees who shall not all be from the same party and at least one of whom shall be from the Committee on Government Operations.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Chief Performance Officer shall serve as a nonvoting liaison to the Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee shall elect two co-chairs from among its members and shall adopt rules of procedure. The Co-Chairs shall be a House and a Senate member. The Committee shall keep minutes of its meetings and maintain a file thereof. A quorum shall consist of five members.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>During the legislative session, the Committee shall meet at the call of the Co-Chairs. When the General Assembly is not in session, the Committee may meet monthly at the call of the Co-Chairs and may meet more often, subject to the approval of the Speaker of the House and the President Pro Tempore of the Senate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For attendance at a meeting when the General Assembly is not in session, legislative members of the Committee shall be entitled to compensation for services and reimbursement of expenses as provided under section 23 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The staff services of the Joint Fiscal Office, the Office of Legislative Operations, and the Office of the Legislative Counsel shall be available to the Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>At least annually, by January 15, the Committee shall report its activities, together with recommendations, if any, to the General Assembly. The report shall be in brief summary form.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-28_section-970_subsec-h"><akn:num>(h)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-30"><akn:num>Chapter 30</akn:num><akn:heading>Capitol Complex Security Advisory Committee</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-30_section-991"><akn:num>Section 991</akn:num><akn:heading>Section 991 repealed effective June 30, 2023. Capitol Complex Security Advisory Committee</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-30_section-991_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Creation.   There is created an advisory committee for the purpose of:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-30_section-991_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>reviewing and coordinating security in the Capitol Complex; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-30_section-991_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>enhancing communication, operability, and efficiency on security issues in the Capitol Complex among the Executive, Legislative, and Judicial branches.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-30_section-991_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Membership.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-30_section-991_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee shall be composed of the following members:
(A) the Commissioner of Buildings and General Services or designee;
(B) the Commissioner of Public Safety or designee;
(C) the Commissioner of Motor Vehicles or designee;
(D) the Chief of the Capitol Police or designee;
(E) the Chairs of the House Committee on Corrections and Institutions and of the Senate Committee on Institutions;
(F) the Sergeant at Arms;
(G) the Court Administrator or designee; and
(H) the Chief of the Montpelier Police Department or designee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-30_section-991_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In the first year, the Chair of the House Committee on Corrections and Institutions shall serve as Chair of the Committee and the Chair of the Senate Committee on Institutions shall serve as Vice Chair. Annually thereafter, the offices of Chair and Vice Chair shall rotate between the Chairs of the House Committee on Corrections and Institutions and of the Senate Committee on Institutions.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-30_section-991_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee shall have the assistance of the staff of the Office of Legislative Counsel and the Joint Fiscal Office.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-30_section-991_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Powers and duties.   The Committee shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-30_section-991_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>review proposed security enhancements and security plans for the Capitol Complex, and make recommendations to the House Committee on Corrections and Institutions and the Senate Committee on Institutions;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-30_section-991_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>review the coordination of security plans and law enforcement services in the Capitol Complex among the Commissioner of Buildings and General Services, the Court Administrator, and the Sergeant at Arms; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-30_section-991_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>annually review the memorandum of understanding coordinating the provision of security plans and law enforcement activities in the Capitol Complex, as required by 29 V.S.A. § 171</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-30_section-991_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Meetings.   The Committee may meet at any time at the call of the Co-Chairs, but no more than two times when the General Assembly is not in session.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-30_section-991_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Reimbursement.   For attendance at meetings during adjournment of the General Assembly, legislative members of the Committee shall be entitled to per diem compensation and reimbursement of expenses pursuant to 2 V.S.A. § 23.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-30_section-991_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Definition.   As used in this section, “Capitol Complex” shall have the same meaning as in 29 V.S.A. § 182.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-02_chapter-31"><akn:num>Chapter 31</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint Public Pension Oversight Committee</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001"><akn:num>Section 1001</akn:num><akn:heading>Creation of Committee</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Creation.   There is created the Joint Public Pension Oversight Committee for the purpose of working with and providing assistance to other legislative committees on matters related to the State’s retirement system and other postemployment benefits.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Members.   The Committee shall be composed of the following members, who shall be appointed each biennial session of the General Assembly:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>three members of the House, who shall not be from the same party, appointed by the Speaker of the House; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>three members of the Senate, who shall not be from the same party, appointed by the Committee on Committees.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Powers and duties.   The Committee shall evaluate and make recommendations on the following:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>issues of public policy related to the provision of retirement benefits to the State’s public sector workforce;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>changes to statutory provisions regarding the provision, design, and administration of retirement benefits and the retirement systems;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>issues of public policy relating to health benefit design innovations, State regulatory measures, and alternative methods of providing pooled health care benefits to both active and retired school employees to lower health care costs for employees, retirees, school boards, and the State; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-c_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the appropriate annual appropriation to fund the State’s retirement obligations in accordance with actuarial recommendations, statutory amortization schedules, and funding policies.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Policies.   The Committee shall elect a chair, vice chair, and clerk from among its members and shall adopt rules of procedure. The Chair shall rotate biennially between the House and Senate members. The Committee shall keep minutes of its meetings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Meetings.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-e_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When the General Assembly is in session, the Committee shall meet at the call of the Chair.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-e_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee may meet six times during adjournment and may meet more often subject to approval of the Speaker of the House and the President Pro Tempore of the Senate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-e_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A quorum shall consist of four members.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Assistance.   The Committee shall have assistance from the Office of Legislative Counsel, the Office of Legislative Operations, and the Joint Fiscal Office.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Compensation and reimbursement.   For attendance at a meeting when the General Assembly is not in session, members of the Committee shall be entitled to compensations for services and reimbursement of expenses as provided under subsection 23</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-02_chapter-31_section-1001_subsec-h"><akn:num>(h)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Reports.   Annually, on or before December 1 each year, the Vermont Investment Pension Commission and the Boards of Trustees for the State Employees’ Retirement System, Teachers’ Retirement System, and Municipal Employees’ Retirement, shall report to the Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter></akn:title></akn:body></akn:act></akn:akomaNtoso>