<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akn:akomaNtoso xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><akn:act><akn:meta><akn:identification source="#cosilico"><akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-31" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-31" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-05-01" name="release" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#vermont-legislature" /><akn:FRBRcountry value="us-vt" /><akn:FRBRnumber value="31" /><akn:FRBRname value="Vermont Statutes Annotated" /></akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-31/eng@2023-05-01" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-31/eng@2023-05-01" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-05-01" name="publication" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /><akn:FRBRlanguage language="eng" /></akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRManifestation><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-31/eng@2023-05-01/akn.xml" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-31/eng@2023-05-01/akn.xml" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /></akn:FRBRManifestation></akn:identification><akn:references><akn:TLCOrganization eId="vermont-legislature" href="https://legislature.vermont.gov" showAs="Vermont General Assembly" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico" /></akn:references></akn:meta><akn:body><akn:title eId="title-31"><akn:num>Title 31</akn:num><akn:heading>Recreation and Sports</akn:heading><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-1"><akn:num>Chapter 1</akn:num><akn:heading>State Recreation Board</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-3"><akn:num>Chapter 3</akn:num><akn:heading>Boxing Control Board</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-5"><akn:num>Chapter 5</akn:num><akn:heading>Municipal Recreation</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-7"><akn:num>Chapter 7</akn:num><akn:heading>Motor Vehicle Races</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-8"><akn:num>Chapter 8</akn:num><akn:heading>Motorcycle Racing</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-9"><akn:num>Chapter 9</akn:num><akn:heading>Municipal Regulation of Entertainment</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-11"><akn:num>Chapter 11</akn:num><akn:heading>Municipal Regulation of Dance Halls, Bowling Alleys, Pool Halls, and Coasting</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-13"><akn:num>Chapter 13</akn:num><akn:heading>Horse Racing</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-14"><akn:num>Chapter 14</akn:num><akn:heading>State Lottery</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-15"><akn:num>Chapter 15</akn:num><akn:heading>Ski Tramways</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-16"><akn:num>Chapter 16</akn:num><akn:heading>Amusement Rides</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-17"><akn:num>Chapter 17</akn:num><akn:heading>Snowmobiles</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-19"><akn:num>Chapter 19</akn:num><akn:heading>Leisure Time and Benefits for Elders</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-21"><akn:num>Chapter 21</akn:num><akn:heading>Boxing</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-23"><akn:num>Chapter 23</akn:num><akn:heading>Games of Chance</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-1"><akn:num>Chapter 1</akn:num><akn:heading>State Recreation Board</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-3"><akn:num>Chapter 3</akn:num><akn:heading>Boxing Control Board</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-5"><akn:num>Chapter 5</akn:num><akn:heading>Municipal Recreation</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-5_section-201"><akn:num>Section 201</akn:num><akn:heading>Authority to appropriate for recreation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A city by its council or an incorporated village, at an annual meeting, may appropriate such sums of money as it deems best, not exceeding four percent of its grand list, for the purchase of public playgrounds and lands, and for the construction and maintenance of buildings and equipment thereon, for public recreational purposes.  This section shall not apply to a city or incorporated village whose charter or bylaws authorize such appropriation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-5_section-202"><akn:num>Section 202</akn:num><akn:heading>Authority to establish and finance recreation system</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Municipalities, singly or jointly, may establish, maintain, and conduct a system of public recreation, including playgrounds; may set apart for such use any land or buildings owned or leased by it; may acquire land, buildings, and other recreational facilities by gift or purchase, and may issue bonds therefor as provided in 24 V.S.A. §§ 1751-1788 and equip and conduct the same; may employ a director of recreation and assistant; and may expend funds for the aforesaid purposes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-5_section-203"><akn:num>Section 203</akn:num><akn:heading>Control and supervision of system</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The legislative body may conduct the same through a department or bureau of recreation or may delegate the conduct thereof to a recreational board created by them, or to a school board or to any other appropriate existing board or commission.  The members of such body first appointed shall be appointed for such terms that the term of one member shall expire annually thereafter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-5_section-204"><akn:num>Section 204</akn:num><akn:heading>Free musical entertainments</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A municipality may appropriate such sums of money not exceeding five percent of its grand list, when the grand list of such municipality does not exceed $20,000.00, and a sum not to exceed three percent of the grand list of such municipality, when the grand list exceeds $20,000.00, to pay the expenses of free musical entertainments, to be held within its limits, at such times and places as is directed by such vote.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-7"><akn:num>Chapter 7</akn:num><akn:heading>Motor Vehicle Races</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-8"><akn:num>Chapter 8</akn:num><akn:heading>Motorcycle Racing</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-9"><akn:num>Chapter 9</akn:num><akn:heading>Municipal Regulation of Entertainment</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-9_section-401"><akn:num>Section 401</akn:num><akn:heading>Permits and fees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A selectboard may permit the exhibition in its town of any show mentioned in 32 V.S.A. §§ 9905 and 9906, on payment by the owners or operators thereof, for the use of the town, of not more than $100.00 nor less than $10.00 for every day on which exhibitions are given in such town.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-9_section-402"><akn:num>Section 402</akn:num><akn:heading>Revocation of permit</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>If, during the exhibition of a show under such license, the selectboard is satisfied that such exhibition disturbs the public peace, it may give notice in writing to the owner or operator thereof that the license is revoked.  If, after such notice, such exhibition is not immediately suspended, the owner or operator shall be subject to the same penalty as if he or she had exhibited without a license.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-9_section-403"><akn:num>Section 403</akn:num><akn:heading>Penalties imposed on town officers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Town clerks, selectboards, village trustees, or any other town or city officials shall be fined not more than $10.00 for issuing a permit or license to the owner or operator of a show mentioned in this chapter for less than the minimum fee prescribed for the use of the town in section 401 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-9_section-404"><akn:num>Section 404</akn:num><akn:heading>Exhibiting without State and town licenses</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A person who gives or attempts to give an exhibition in a town of a show mentioned in 32 V.S.A. §§ 9901-9910 without first having obtained permission of the selectboard of such town therefor and without having received from the Secretary of State the license as provided in 32 V.S.A. §§ 9901-9910, shall be fined not more than $3,000.00 nor less than $1,000.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-9_section-405"><akn:num>Section 405</akn:num><akn:heading>Permits to exhibit natural curiosities</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A selectboard may permit a person to exhibit living animals and other natural curiosities for not more than two days at one time on payment of not more than $50.00 nor less than $10.00 by such person to the selectboard for the use of the town.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-9_section-406"><akn:num>Section 406</akn:num><akn:heading>Exhibition without license</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A person who for reward or gain or under color of a gratuity suffers premises under his or her control to be used for the exhibition of a circus, living animals, and natural curiosities or exhibits a living animal or natural curiosity without having previously obtained such permission shall be fined not more than $200.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-9_section-441"><akn:num>Section 441</akn:num><akn:heading>Regulation of shows and games of chance</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The officers of a town fair association may regulate and prevent theatrical, circus, or mountebank exhibitions and shows, or traffic in fruits, goods, wares, and merchandise of whatever description, the trading of horses, and games of chance, on fair days, within a distance of 200 yards in any highway leading to or passing a fairground, if in the opinion of such officers the same would obstruct or interfere with the free and uninterrupted use of such highways.  The police employed by such association shall have the same power in respect to such matters on such highways as they have within such grounds.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-9_section-442"><akn:num>Section 442</akn:num><akn:heading>Licenses for theatres and similar entertainment</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The selectboard of a town, trustees of an incorporated village, and the aldermen of a city may grant licenses and fix a fee therefor, for theatres, shows, moving picture shows, or concert halls operated and maintained for profit, may revoke the same, and may also, after hearing, refuse to grant such a license when, in their judgment, the public good requires.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-9_section-443"><akn:num>Section 443</akn:num><akn:heading>Operating without license</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A person who installs, operates, or maintains a theatre, show, moving picture show, or concert hall without first obtaining a license therefor, if required by the selectboard of a town, the trustees of an incorporated village, or the aldermen of a city, as provided in section 442 of this title, shall be fined not more than $100.00 for each day on which he or she so operates or maintains the same.  Such fine shall be paid to the town treasurer for the benefit of the town.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-11"><akn:num>Chapter 11</akn:num><akn:heading>Municipal Regulation of Dance Halls, Bowling Alleys, Pool Halls, and Coasting</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-11_section-501"><akn:num>Section 501</akn:num><akn:heading>Dance hall defined</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A room, hall, eating place, building, structure, or place shall be deemed to be a dance hall for the purposes of this chapter at all times and occasions when dancing, for which admission is charged and which is open to the general public, is conducted or permitted therein.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-11_section-502"><akn:num>Section 502</akn:num><akn:heading>Supervision</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A person, partnership, association, or corporation shall not operate a dance hall unless, at the hours when dancing is conducted or permitted therein, there is in attendance one or more police or other officers empowered to make arrests.  With the approval of the selectboard, city council, or trustees of the town, city, or incorporated village where the dance hall is operated, licensed security guards may be employed in place of officers.  The officers or security guards shall be paid for their services by the operator of the dance hall.  The number of officers or security guards and the individuals so acting shall be approved by the selectboard, mayor, or trustees of the town, city, or incorporated village.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-11_section-503"><akn:num>Section 503</akn:num><akn:heading>License required</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A person, partnership, association, or corporation shall not operate a dance hall, bowling alley, or pool hall unless a license so to do has been obtained from the selectboard, city council, or trustees of the town, city, or incorporated village in which it is proposed to operate such dance hall, bowling alley, or pool hall.  Any such license may, after hearing and for cause, be revoked by the municipal officers granting the same when in their judgment the public good requires.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-11_section-504"><akn:num>Section 504</akn:num><akn:heading>Fees and regulations</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The selectboard, city council, or trustees of a town, city, or incorporated village shall grant a license as provided in section 503 of this title upon application therefor and upon compliance by the applicant with such reasonable requirements as they may prescribe for the protection and safety of the public and the preservation of the public morals and upon payment of such fee as they may require, not to exceed $25.00 in case of an annual fee or $5.00 in case of a single dance.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-11_section-505"><akn:num>Section 505</akn:num><akn:heading>Regulations on operation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The selectboard, city council, or trustees of a town, city, or incorporated village are hereby empowered to make regulations concerning the operation of dance halls, bowling alleys, and pool halls including lighting, both inside and outside, on the premises where such dance halls, bowling alleys, or pool halls are operated.  Such rules and regulations shall not be effective until they are recorded in the office of the clerk of the municipality for which the same are made, and no license shall be issued until such rules and regulations are complied with.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-11_section-506"><akn:num>Section 506</akn:num><akn:heading>Charitable exemptions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The provisions of sections 503-505 of this title shall not apply to dance halls, bowling alleys, or pool halls operated by charitable, educational, and fraternal organizations or institutions on premises owned or regularly occupied by charitable, educational, and fraternal organizations or institutions except that in any event no license fee shall be required from any of the organizations or institutions mentioned in this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-11_section-507"><akn:num>Section 507</akn:num><akn:heading>Construction</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The provisions of sections 503-506 of this title shall not apply to cities or incorporated villages whose charters, ordinances, or bylaws make different provisions as to the licenses or any of them provided for in this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-11_section-508"><akn:num>Section 508</akn:num><akn:heading>Penalties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A person, partnership, association, or corporation who violates a provision of sections 501-507 of this title or who violates any lawful rule or regulation made as provided in section 505 of this title shall be fined not more than $100.00 nor less than $25.00 for each such violation.  Each such violation occurring at any single dance shall be deemed to be a separate offense.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-11_section-509"><akn:num>Section 509</akn:num><akn:heading>Setting up alley near schoolhouse or church</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A person as owner or keeper, who sets up or uses a bowling alley upon land adjoining the land on which a school building, college, academy, or church is located, shall be fined $20.00 for each day or time he or she permits such alley to be used.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-11_section-511"><akn:num>Section 511</akn:num><akn:heading>Coasting on sleds</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The selectboard shall forbid coasting upon the highways when it endangers the lives or property of travelers and shall post notices to that effect in two or more conspicuous places in the vicinity.  However, such prohibition shall not apply to highways in villages or cities having regulations respecting coasting.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-11_section-512"><akn:num>Section 512</akn:num><akn:heading>Penalties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A person who thereafter coasts on a highway specified in such notice shall be fined $2.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-13"><akn:num>Chapter 13</akn:num><akn:heading>Horse Racing</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-14"><akn:num>Chapter 14</akn:num><akn:heading>State Lottery</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-651"><akn:num>Section 651</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers and duties of Board of Liquor and Lottery</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-651_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Types of lotteries to be conducted, provided that no lottery shall be conducted that depends upon the outcome of an athletic contest except that the lottery may be affiliated with a sporting event, or sweepstakes, where the outcome is determined solely by lot or random drawing and not by choice of the lottery participant.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-651_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Price of lottery tickets.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-651_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Number and size of prizes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-651_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Manner of payment of prizes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-651_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Manner and frequency of drawings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-651_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The licensing of agents, provided that:
(A) no person who has not attained the age of majority shall be licensed as an agent; and
(B) no agent shall be in the business of solely selling lottery tickets.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-651_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Lottery product sales locations, which may include State agency liquor stores; private business establishments, except establishments holding first- or first- and third-class licenses pursuant to Title 7; fraternal, religious, and volunteer organizations; town clerks’ offices; and State fairs, race tracks, and other sporting arenas.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-651_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Method for sale of tickets, provided that they may be sold only for cash.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-651_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Manner of compensation of sales agents, claims agents, and financial institutions involved in the operation of the Lottery.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-651_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Manner of selecting winning tickets.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-651_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Apportionment of total revenues, within limits hereinafter specified, accruing to the State Lottery Fund among:
(A) the payment of prizes to winning ticket holders;
(B) the payment of all costs incurred in the creation, operation, and administration of the State Lottery, including compensation of the Board, Commissioner of Liquor and Lottery, employees of the Department of Liquor and Lottery, consultants, and contractors and other necessary expenses;
(C) the repayment of monies advanced to the State Lottery Fund for initial funding of the State Lottery;
(D) the transfer of monies to the Education Fund established by 16 V.S.A. § 4025, to be used solely for the purposes of State and local funding of public education.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-652"><akn:num>Section 652</akn:num><akn:heading>Multijurisdictional lottery games</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-652_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-652_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In addition to the Tri-State Lotto Compact provided for in subchapter 2 of this chapter, and the other authority to operate lotteries contained in this chapter, the Board of Liquor and Lottery is authorized to negotiate and contract with not more than four multijurisdictional lotteries to offer and provide multijurisdictional lottery games. The Board may join any multijurisdictional lottery that provides indemnification for its standing committee members, officers, directors, employees, and agents.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-652_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) The Board shall adopt procedures pursuant to 3 V.S.A. § 835 to govern the establishment and operation of any multijurisdictional lottery game authorized by this section. For each procedure proposed to be adopted or amended pursuant to this section, the Board shall publish the proposal on the Department of Liquor and Lottery’s website, provide notice of the proposal to all persons licensed to sell lottery tickets, provide not less than 30 days for public comment on the proposal, and hold not less than two public hearings at which members of the public may seek additional information or submit oral or written comments on the proposal.
(B) The Board of Liquor and Lottery shall not be required to initiate rulemaking pursuant to 3 V.S.A. § 831</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-652_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>in relation to a procedure adopted pursuant to this section.
(C) A procedure adopted pursuant to this section shall have the force of law and be binding on all persons who play or sell the multijurisdictional lottery game.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-652_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In each fiscal year, the revenues received from the operation of any multijurisdictional lottery game authorized by this section, after payment of prizes and costs of administration, shall be deposited in the Education Fund established in 16 V.S.A. § 4025.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-652_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The provisions of subdivisions 674L.1.1A through 674L.1.1I of this title shall apply to the payment of prizes to a person other than a winner for prizes awarded under any multijurisdictional lottery authorized by this section, except that the Board of Liquor and Lottery shall be responsible for implementing the provisions under this section, rather than the Tri-State Lotto Commission.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-653"><akn:num>Section 653</akn:num><akn:heading>License fees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A license fee shall be charged for each sales license granted to a person for the purpose of selling lottery tickets at the time the person is first granted a license. The fee shall be fixed by the Board of Liquor and Lottery, but no license fee in excess of $50.00 may be charged.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-654"><akn:num>Section 654</akn:num><akn:heading>Interstate lottery; consultant; management</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-654_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Board of Liquor and Lottery may develop and operate a lottery or the State may enter into a contractual agreement with another state or states to provide for the operation of the Lottery. Approval of the Joint Fiscal Committee and the Governor shall be required for such contractual agreements with other states.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-654_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If no interstate contract is entered into, the Board shall obtain the service of an experienced lottery design and implementation consultant. The fee for the consultant may be fixed or may be based upon a percentage of gross receipts realized from the Lottery.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-654_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Board may enter into a facilities management type of agreement for operation of the Lottery by a third party.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-655"><akn:num>Section 655</akn:num><akn:heading>Duties of the Commissioner</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-655_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The State Lottery shall be under the immediate supervision and direction of the Commissioner of Liquor and Lottery.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-655_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commissioner shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-655_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Supervise and administer the operation of the Lottery within the rules adopted by the Board of Liquor and Lottery.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-655_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Subject to the approval of the Board, enter into contracts necessary for the proper creation, administration, operation, modification, and promotion of the State Lottery or any part of the Lottery. These contracts shall not be assignable.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-655_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>License sales agents and suspend or revoke any license in accordance with the provisions of this chapter and the rules of the Board.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-655_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Act as Secretary to the Board, but as a nonvoting member of the Board.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-655_subsec-b_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Employ professional and secretarial staff as necessary to carry out the functions of the Division of the Lottery. 3 V.S.A. chapter 13 shall apply to employees of the Division.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-655_subsec-b_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Annually prepare a budget and submit it to the Board.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-655_subsec-b_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Subject to the approval of the Board, establish a user agreement with the Vermont Crime Information Center in accordance with 20 V.S.A. chapter 117 for the purpose of obtaining Vermont criminal history records, out-of-state criminal history records, and criminal history records from the Federal Bureau of Investigation to review applications for any Lottery sales agent license issued under this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-656"><akn:num>Section 656</akn:num><akn:heading>State Lottery Fund</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-656_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There is hereby created in the State Treasury a separate fund to be known as the State Lottery Fund. The Fund shall consist of all revenues received from the Treasurer for initial funding, from sale of lottery tickets, from license fees, and from all other money credited or transferred from any other fund or source pursuant to law. The monies in the State Lottery Fund shall be disbursed pursuant to subdivision 651</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-656_subsec-a_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title, and shall be disbursed by the Treasurer on warrants issued by the Commissioner of Finance and Management, when authorized by the Commissioner of Liquor and Lottery and approved by the Commissioner of Finance and Management.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-656_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Expenditures for administrative and overhead expenses of the operation of the State Lottery, except agent and bank commissions, shall be paid from Lottery receipts from an appropriation authorized for that purpose. Agent commissions shall be set by the Board of Liquor and Lottery and shall not exceed 6.25 percent of gross receipts and bank commissions shall not exceed one percent of gross receipts. Once the draw game results become official, the payment of any commission on any draw game ticket that wins at least $10,000.00 shall be made through the normal course of processing payments to lottery agents, regardless of whether the winning ticket is claimed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-656_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Not less than 50 percent of gross receipts shall be paid out as prizes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-656_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Annuities for lottery winners shall be purchased by the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall make all investments of State Lottery Fund monies.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-657"><akn:num>Section 657</akn:num><akn:heading>Report of the Board</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Board of Liquor and Lottery shall make an annual report to the Governor and to the General Assembly on or before the 10th day of January in each year. The report shall include an account of the Board’s actions and the receipts derived under the provisions of this chapter, the practical effects of the application of the proceeds of the Lottery, and any recommendation for legislation that the Board deems advisable.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-658"><akn:num>Section 658</akn:num><akn:heading>Postaudits</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>All State Lottery accounts and transactions of the Board of Liquor and Lottery shall be subject to annual postaudits conducted by independent auditors retained by the Board for this purpose. The Board may order other audits as it deems necessary and desirable.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-659"><akn:num>Section 659</akn:num><akn:heading>Sales and purchase of lottery tickets</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-659_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Persons convicted of a felony within five years of the date of making application shall not be licensed to sell lottery tickets.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-659_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>No tickets shall be sold at a price higher than the price printed on the lottery tickets.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-659_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>No tickets shall be sold to individuals who have not attained the age of majority. However, tickets may be given as gifts to minors or any other individuals except as prohibited by this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-659_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>No member of the Board of Liquor and Lottery or employee of the Department of Liquor and Lottery, or member of his or her immediate household, shall claim or receive prize money under this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-660"><akn:num>Section 660</akn:num><akn:heading>Unclaimed prize money</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Lottery prize winners will be allowed one year from their prize eligibility date to claim a prize.  All prize money that is unclaimed after one year shall revert to the State Lottery Fund.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-661"><akn:num>Section 661</akn:num><akn:heading>State gaming laws inapplicable as to lottery</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>13 V.S.A. chapter 51, subchapters 1, 2, and 3 shall not apply to the sale of lottery tickets as provided in this chapter. No law providing for any penalty or disability for the sale of lottery tickets or any acts done in connection with a lottery shall apply to the sale of tickets or acts performed pursuant to this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-662"><akn:num>Section 662</akn:num><akn:heading>Penalties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Any person who is convicted of violating a provision of this chapter shall be fined not more than $500.00 or imprisoned for not more than two years, or both.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-663"><akn:num>Section 663</akn:num><akn:heading>Publication of odds</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Any promotional advertising shall, to the extent practicable, estimate the general odds of winning.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-664"><akn:num>Section 664</akn:num><akn:heading>Fiscal Committee review</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-664_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Whenever the gross receipts of the State Lottery fall below $450,000.00 during any three-month period after the commencement of the first game, the Joint Fiscal Committee shall immediately investigate the condition of the State Lottery, and its likelihood for continuing success.  If, after investigation, the Joint Fiscal Committee determines that continuation of the Lottery is not in the best interests of the State, it may order the termination of the State Lottery.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-664_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>This section shall not apply in the event the Board of Liquor and Lottery enters into a facilities management agreement pursuant to the provisions of subsection 654</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-664_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-671"><akn:num>Section 671</akn:num><akn:heading>Short title</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>This Compact shall be known and may be cited as the “Tri-State Lotto Compact.”</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-672"><akn:num>Section 672</akn:num><akn:heading>Compact</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The State of Vermont enters into the following Compact with the states of Maine and New Hampshire subject to the terms and conditions stated in the Compact.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-673"><akn:num>Section 673</akn:num><akn:heading>General provisions—Article I</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A. Statement of policy and purpose.   This Compact is enacted to implement the operation of Tri-State Lotto, for the purpose of raising additional revenue for each of the party states. Tri-State Lotto is not intended to replace any existing lottery game in the party states, but, rather, to be run in addition to these games. Tri-State Lotto tickets will be sold in each of the party states and processed in a central area to be determined by the Commission. No less than 50 percent of the gross sales from each state will be aggregated in a common prize pool, and operating costs will be charged proportionally to the party states. The remaining revenues generated within each state will remain in that particular state.
B. Definitions.
1. “Tri-State Lotto” means a combined lotto game for all member states, with common tickets, common advertising and a common prize pool.
2. “Party states” means the states of New Hampshire, Vermont, and Maine.
3. “Commission” means the Tri-State Lotto Commission created and established by this Compact.
4. “Concurrent legislation” means legislation enacted by one of the party states which is concurred in by the other party states in the form of enactments having like effect.
5. “Lotto” means a game of lotto as prescribed by the Commission.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-674"><akn:num>Section 674</akn:num><akn:heading>Procedures and conditions governing the tri-state lottery—Article II</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-674_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The payable due dates and amounts of each payment to be assigned.
(ii) The gross amount of the annual payment or payments to be assigned before taxes.
(D) A notice of right to cancel in immediate proximity to the space reserved for the signature of the assignor in boldface type of a minimum size of 10 points which shall provide that:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-674_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The assignor may cancel the assignment without cost until midnight 15 business days after the day on which the assignor has signed an agreement to assign a prize or portion of a prize.
(ii) Cancellation occurs when notice of cancellation is given to the assignee.
(iii) Notice is sufficient if it indicates the intention of the assignor not to be bound.
(iv) Notice of cancellation, if given by mail, shall be deemed given when deposited in a mailbox properly addressed and first class mail postage prepaid. Failure to provide the notice of right to cancel as provided in this subdivision shall render the assignment agreement unenforceable and the assignor may collect reasonable attorney’s fees in any action to enforce such agreement.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-674_subsec-i_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>That prior to execution of the assignment agreement, the assignee has provided to the assignor in writing, on a disclosure form separate and apart from the agreement, the following:
(A) the aggregate dollar value of payments assigned;
(B) the total consideration paid to the assignor by the assignee;
(C) an itemization of all other fees or costs to be paid by the assignor, or deducted from the payment to the assignor.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-674_subsec-i_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>That the assignor has represented to the court in sworn testimony, if a personal appearance is required by the court, or in the assignor’s written affidavit, sworn to under penalty of perjury, that:
(A) Prior to signing the assignment agreement, the assignor reviewed the agreement and understood its terms and effects.
(B) The assignor has consulted with independent financial and tax advisors not referred by or associated with the assignee.
(C) The assignor has signed the assignment agreement acting under free will without undue influence or duress.
(D) The assignor is not under any obligation to pay child support, or is under such obligation and is in good standing with respect to that obligation or has agreed to a payment plan with the party state agency responsible for child support and is in full compliance with that plan.
(E) The assigned payment or payments are not subject to any claims, liens, levies, security interests, assignments, or offsets asserted by other persons or the party states or has provided the court with written consent of each person having such an interest.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-674_subsec-i_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If the assignor is married, the assignor has submitted to the court a signed and notarized statement of the spouse consenting to the assignment. If a notarized statement is not presented to the court, the court shall determine the ability of the assignor to make the proposed assignment without the spouse’s consent.

1B. a. A winner may pledge all or any part of a prize as collateral for a loan. Notwithstanding any provision of Article 9 of the Uniform Commercial Code to the contrary, perfection of a security interest in a prize shall be completed by filing, in addition to any other filings which may be required, a financing statement with the Commission.
b. In order to be entitled to receive a prize payment or payments from the Commission, a secured party shall be required to obtain a certified final order of a court of competent jurisdiction which:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-674_subsec-i_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Adjudges the prize winner in default of a loan agreement with the secured party.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-674_subsec-i_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Makes findings with respect to the loan agreements and financing statements constituting the loan transaction which are equivalent to those required pursuant to subdivisions 1A.c.(1)-</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-674_subsec-i_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this paragraph and, in addition, a finding that truth-in-lending disclosures set forth in 12 C.F.R. §§ 226.17, 226.18, 226.19, and 226.20 were made.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-674_subsec-i_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Identifies specific payments and awards ownership of said payments to the secured party.
c. Nothing in this paragraph shall be construed to:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-674_subsec-i_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Create or enlarge a cause of action in favor of a secured party.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-674_subsec-i_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Alter or impair any rule of law applicable to or governing the rights of a debtor under federal or state lending statutes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-674_subsec-i_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Alter or impair the provisions of Article 9 of the Uniform Commercial Code except to the extent inconsistent with the provisions of this paragraph.
1C. The Commission may intervene as of right in any action pursuant to subsection 1A.c or paragraph 1B of this section, but shall not be deemed an indispensable or necessary party.
1D. A certified copy of the final order required by subsection 1A.b of this section, a certified copy of the final order and the assignor’s affidavit required by subsection  1A.c of this section, and a certified copy of the final order required by paragraph 1B of this section shall be served on the Commission together with a nonrefundable processing fee of $500.00 within 15 days after entry of the order.
1E. The Commission may file a request to modify or vacate a final order pursuant to subsection 1A.c or paragraph 1B of this section within l5 days after service of the order on the Commission.
1F. Commencing on the 30th day after full compliance with paragraph 1D of this section, or after final determination of any motion filed to vacate or modify a final order entered pursuant to paragraph 1E of this section, the Commission shall be obligated to make payments, subject to tax withholding, in accordance with said order.
1G. No modification or amendment to an order pursuant to subsections 1A.b or c or paragraph 1B of this section and no additional or subsequent assignment of a prize, shall be valid or binding on the Commission unless the modification, amendment, or assignment is approved by a separate court order which meets the requirements of this section.
1H. The Commission, its officers, agents, and employees shall be discharged of all further liability upon payment of a prize pursuant to this section.
1I. The financial, tax, trust, or personal records filed, received, maintained, or produced by the Commission in connection with payment of a prize as provided in this section are confidential. Such records shall not be deemed public records u</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-675"><akn:num>Section 675</akn:num><akn:heading>Criminal provisions—Article III</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A. No person shall sell a ticket or share in a ticket at a price greater than that fixed by the Commission. No person other than a lottery agent shall sell lottery tickets. Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent any individual purchaser from giving lottery tickets or shares to another as a gift. Any person convicted of violating this article shall be punished by imprisonment for six months and a fine of $1,000.00.
B. Any person who falsely or fraudulently makes, forges, alters, or counterfeits or causes or procures to be made, forged, altered, or counterfeited, any Vermont State Lottery ticket or Commission ticket as any party thereof, or any person who knowingly and willfully utters, publishes, passes, or tenders as true, any forged, altered, or counterfeited Vermont Lottery tickets or Commission lottery tickets shall be punished by imprisonment for six months and a fine of $5,000.00.
C. Any subsequent offense shall be punished by imprisonment for two years and $20,000.00 fine for each offense.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-676"><akn:num>Section 676</akn:num><akn:heading>Reducing or expanding Compact</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>This Compact may be reduced or expanded among the New England states as to the number of member states, with the consent of the individual states’ commissions.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-677"><akn:num>Section 677</akn:num><akn:heading>Allocation of profits</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The profits received by the State of Vermont through the sale of the Tri-State Lotto tickets shall be deposited in the Education Fund established by 16 V.S.A. § 4025 and used solely for the purposes of State and local funding of public education.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-14_section-678"><akn:num>Section 678</akn:num><akn:heading>Effective date—Article IV</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>This Compact shall become effective when bills of the Maine and the New Hampshire general assemblies which incorporate the Compact become law in Maine and New Hampshire.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-15"><akn:num>Chapter 15</akn:num><akn:heading>Ski Tramways</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-701"><akn:num>Section 701</akn:num><akn:heading>Declaration of policy</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>It shall be the policy of the State of Vermont to prevent unnecessary hazards in the operation of ski tows, lifts, and tramways, to ensure that reasonable design and construction are used, that accepted safety devices are provided for and that periodic inspections and adjustments are made, all for the purpose of making safe the operation of ski tows, ski lifts, and passenger tramways.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-702"><akn:num>Section 702</akn:num><akn:heading>Definition of terms</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-702_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“A passenger tramway” is a device used to transport passengers uphill on skis, or in cars on tracks or suspended in the air, by the use of steel cables, chains, or belts or by ropes and usually supported by trestles or towers with one or more spans. The term passenger tramway shall include the following:
(A) “Two-car passenger tramway,” a device used to transport passengers in two open or enclosed cars attached to, and suspended from, a moving wire rope, or attached to a moving wire rope and supported on a standing wire rope, or similar devices.
(B) “Multi-car passenger tramway,” a device used to transport passengers in several open or enclosed cars attached to, and suspended from, a moving wire rope, or attached to a moving wire rope and supported on a standing wire rope, or similar devices.
(C) “Skimobile,” a device in which a passenger car running on steel or wooden tracks is attached to and pulled by a steel cable, or similar devices.
(D) “Chair lift,” a type of transportation on which passengers are carried on chairs suspended in the air and attached to a moving cable, chain, or link belt supported by trestles or towers with one or more spans, or similar devices. A chair lift may be a “fixed grip lift” or a “detachable grip lift.”
(E) “Surface lift,” a type of transportation which pulls skiers riding on skis by means of an attachment to a main overhead cable supported by trestles or towers with one or more spans. Surface lifts include so-called T bars, J bars, poma lifts, platter pulls, and similar type devices.
(F) “Rope tow,” a type of transportation which pulls the skiers riding on skis as the skier grasps the rope manually, or similar devices.
(G) “Detachable grip lift,” an aerial lift on which carriers alternately attach to and detach from a moving haul rope. The tramway system may be mono-cable or bi-cable.
(H) “Fixed grip lift,” an aerial lift on which carriers remain attached to a haul rope. The tramway system may be either continuous or intermittent ci</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-702_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Industry” shall mean the activities of all those persons in the State who own or control the operation of passenger tramways.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-702_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Operator” is a person who owns or controls the operation of a passenger tramway.  The word “operator” shall include the State or any political subdivision.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-702_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Board” shall mean the Passenger Tramway Board.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-702_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Department” shall mean the Department of Labor.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-702_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Lineal footage” is one-half of the total length of the cable or rope as determined when the tramway is installed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-703"><akn:num>Section 703</akn:num><akn:heading>Passenger Tramway Board</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>There is hereby created the Passenger Tramway Board within the Department of Labor which shall consist of the Commissioner of Labor, ex officio, who shall serve as chair, and four appointive members.  The appointive members of said Board shall be appointed by the Governor.  Two of the appointive members who are first appointed shall be designated to serve terms of two years and two of the appointive members shall be designated to serve terms of four years, but thereafter appointive members shall be appointed for terms of four years except that all vacancies shall be filled for the unexpired term.  An appointive member shall hold office until his successor has been appointed and has qualified.  Two appointive members shall be engaged in the industry and two shall be representatives of the public at large.  Appointive members of the Board shall receive as compensation the sum of $15.00 per diem for their services and their necessary expenses when in the performance of their duties.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-704"><akn:num>Section 704</akn:num><akn:heading>Rules</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Board may, in accordance with 3 V.S.A. chapter 25, adopt reasonable rules relating to public safety in the construction, operation, maintenance, and inspection of passenger tramways.  The rules authorized hereunder shall conform as nearly as practicable to established standards, if any, and shall not be discriminatory in their application to operators of passenger tramways.  Rules adopted by the Board shall in no way reduce or diminish the standard of care imposed upon passenger tramway operators under existing law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-705"><akn:num>Section 705</akn:num><akn:heading>Enforcement, certificate</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Department shall enforce the rules adopted by the Board and inspect the construction, operation, and maintenance of passenger tramways to determine whether the rules adopted by the Board have been complied with by the operators. Certification of compliance by a qualified inspector who has been approved by the Department may be accepted by the Department instead of other inspection. In any legal proceedings, a certificate of compliance issued pursuant to this section shall be competent evidence only for the purpose of establishing the fact of issuance of said certificate and for no other purpose.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-706"><akn:num>Section 706</akn:num><akn:heading>Operators to pay cost of inspection</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The expenses of the Department in connection with making the inspections under section 705 of this title shall be paid in the first instance by the Department. In the event that contractors are used by the Department for specialized engineering consultation, such as structural, electrical, mechanical, or failure analysis, the cost shall be reimbursed to the Department by the affected area tramway operators. The reimbursement shall be credited to the special fund created under this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707"><akn:num>Section 707</akn:num><akn:heading>Registration and fees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A passenger tramway shall not be operated in this State unless the operator thereof has been registered by the Department. On or before the first day of November in each year, every operator of a passenger tramway shall apply to the Department on forms prepared by it for registration hereunder. The application shall contain such information as the Department may require and shall be accompanied by a registration fee, according to the formula stated in this section, unless an alternate payment plan is approved by the Commissioner pursuant to subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section. The Department shall assess total registration fees in the sum of the amount approved in the appropriations process for the program for that fiscal year, adjusted by any balance in the Passenger Tramway Special Fund from the prior fiscal year.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Each operator shall pay a proportionate share of the total registration fees as determined by the total lineal feet of each type of tramway operated as follows:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the operator’s total lineal footage of multi-car passenger tramways times the product of the base rate times 150 percent;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the operator’s total lineal footage of detachable grip chair lifts times the product of the base rate times 125 percent;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the operator’s total lineal footage of fixed grip chair lifts times the base rate;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the operator’s total lineal footage of surface lifts and rope tows times the product of the base rate times 50 percent;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-b_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>all tramways being registered for the first time shall pay a sum equal to five times the registration fee required to be paid for similar type tramways that have previously been registered;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-b_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>all major modifications of existing passenger tramways where the Department has determined that a 50 percent alteration or upgrade of structural, mechanical, or electrical systems has occurred or where the Department has determined that a full load test of the lift is required, shall pay a fee according to the following schedule:
(A) drive terminal, tension terminal, or mid-station terminal M-modification (50 percent or more) shall pay an equivalent annual registration fee times two;
(B) any two of the above M-modifications (50 percent or more) shall pay an equivalent annual registration fee times three;
(C) any three of the above M-modifications (50 percent or more) shall pay an equivalent annual registration fee times four;
(D) towers, structures, and foundation M-modification (50 percent or more) not including any of the M-modifications listed in subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-b_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>any passenger tramway that operates for more than five days singly or in aggregate, between the periods of June 1 through October 30, shall pay an annual registration fee equal to that of a similar type tramway plus 25 percent.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For purposes of computing the base rate, “lineal footage” means the total lineal footage of each type of tramway registered during the previous operating year.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-e_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All fees collected under this section shall be credited to a special fund for the Department to be expended for carrying out its duties under this chapter and may also be expended as provided pursuant to subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-e_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-e_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Passenger Tramway Board may expend amounts that it determines to be appropriate from the special fund established pursuant to subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-e_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection for the purpose of contributing to ski lift mechanic education, job training, and apprenticeship programs.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-707_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commissioner has discretion to authorize a tramway operator to enter a payment plan to pay some or all of the fee-due-State after November 1 upon a showing of financial need. The authorization and terms of any payment plan shall be in writing and set a date or dates for payment, provided that the total amount of the fee-due-State shall be paid no later than January 15. Failure to pay on November 1 or pursuant to an authorized plan may subject the operator to the penalties established in section 712 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-708"><akn:num>Section 708</akn:num><akn:heading>Orders</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>If, after investigation, the Department finds that a violation of any of the rules exists, or that there is a condition in passenger tramway construction, operation, or maintenance endangering the safety of the public, it shall forthwith issue its written order setting forth its findings, the corrective action to be taken, and fixing a reasonable time for compliance therewith.  The order shall be served upon the operator involved by registered mail and shall become final unless the operator applies to the Board for a hearing in the manner provided in section 709 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-708a"><akn:num>Section 708a</akn:num><akn:heading>Emergency orders</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Whenever the condition is deemed to be imminently hazardous, involving the safety of passengers, the Department’s representative shall be authorized to order the operator in writing to immediately suspend operation of the tramway, until such time as the hazardous condition has been remedied.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-709"><akn:num>Section 709</akn:num><akn:heading>Hearing</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Any operator who is aggrieved by Department order may, within ten days after service thereof upon him or her, apply to the Board for a review of the order.  The Board shall hold a hearing thereon at the earliest convenient day.  At the hearing, the operator shall have a right to a full hearing, including the right to be heard personally and by counsel, to cross-examine witnesses, and to produce evidence in his or her own behalf.  After the hearing, the Board shall report its findings, in writing, and make such order as the facts may require.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-710"><akn:num>Section 710</akn:num><akn:heading>Appeal</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Any operator who is aggrieved by any order of the Department following the hearing provided in section 709 of this title may, within 30 days after entry thereof, appeal to the Superior Court for the county in which the passenger tramway is located.  An appeal shall not suspend the operation of the order made by the Board, but the Superior Court may suspend the order of the Board pending determination of the appeal whenever, in the opinion of the court, justice may require its suspension.  The Superior Court shall hear the appeal and make such decree as justice may require.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-711"><akn:num>Section 711</akn:num><akn:heading>Suspension</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>If any operator fails to comply with a lawful order issued under sections 708 and 709 of this title, the Department may order the operator to cease operations for such time as it considers necessary for the protection of the safety of the public.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-712"><akn:num>Section 712</akn:num><akn:heading>Penalties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-712_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Operating without passing inspection.   Any operator who operates a passenger tramway without first passing the annual inspection by the Department shall be fined not more than $1,000.00 for each day of operation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-712_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Operating without paying fee-due-State.   Any operator who operates a passenger tramway without paying the fee-due-State as provided in section 707 of this title shall be fined not more than $50.00 for each day of operation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-15_section-712_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Operating after an order to cease.   Any person who operates a passenger tramway after being ordered to cease operations shall be fined not more than $5,000.00 for each day of illegal operation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-16"><akn:num>Chapter 16</akn:num><akn:heading>Amusement Rides</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-721"><akn:num>Section 721</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-721_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Amusement ride” means a mechanical device that carries or conveys passengers along, around, or over a fixed or restricted route or course for the purpose of giving the passengers amusement, pleasure, thrills, or excitement. For the purposes of this chapter, amusement ride shall not include bungee jumping, zip lines, or waterslides or obstacle, challenge, or adventure courses.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-721_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Operator” or “owner” means a person who owns or controls or has the duty to control the operation of amusement rides.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-721_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722"><akn:num>Section 722</akn:num><akn:heading>Certificate of operation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An amusement ride may not be operated in this State unless the Secretary of State has issued a certificate of operation to the owner or operator within the preceding 12 months.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An application for a certificate of operation shall be submitted to the Secretary of State not fewer than 30 business days before an amusement ride is operated in this State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of State shall issue a certificate of operation not fewer than 15 business days before the amusement ride is operated in the State, if the owner or operator submits the following:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>certificate of insurance in the amount of not less than $1,000,000.00 that insures both the owner and the operator against liability for injury to persons and property arising out of the use or operation of the amusement ride;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>payment of a fee in the amount of $100.00;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>proof or a statement of compliance with the requirements of 21 V.S.A. chapter 9.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The certificate of operation shall be valid for one year from the date of issue and shall be in a manner and format to be prescribed by the Secretary of State. A certificate of operation shall identify the ride’s:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>name and model;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>serial number;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-d_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>passenger capacity; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-d_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>recommended maximum speed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A copy of the certificate of operation shall be kept at the office of the amusement ride operator.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of State shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-f_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>determine the manner and format of the certificate of operation, any forms to be used to apply for the certificate of operation, the adhesive sticker that shall be affixed to the ride pursuant to subdivision 723a</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-f_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title, and the certification to be filed pursuant to subdivision 723a</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-f_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-f_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>make any forms and certifications available on the Secretary of State’s website and shall provide adhesive stickers to inspectors;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-f_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>allow an owner or operator to apply for certificates of operation for multiple rides at one time, using one form;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-722_subsec-f_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>charge one fee for the filing of each application form, regardless of the number of rides listed on the application.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723"><akn:num>Section 723</akn:num><akn:heading>Operator and patron responsibilities</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An operator of an amusement ride shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>be at least 18 years of age;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>operate only one amusement ride at a time;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>be in attendance at all times that the ride is operating; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>operate the ride in accordance with the ride manufacturer’s specifications.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An operator of an amusement ride may deny any person entrance to an amusement ride if the operator believes that entrance by that person may jeopardize the safety of the person or other persons.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A patron shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>understand that there are risks in riding an amusement ride;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>exercise good judgment and act in a responsible and safe manner while riding an amusement ride; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>obey all signage that is reasonably written and posted and all directions from ride operators and owners that are given in a clear and understandable manner.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a"><akn:num>Section 723a</akn:num><akn:heading>Safety inspections</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A amusement ride shall not be operated in this State unless:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The ride has been inspected in the State within the preceding 12 months by a person who is:
(A) certified:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>by the National Association of Amusement Ride Safety Officials as a Level II Inspector; or
(ii) by the Amusement Industry Manufacturers and Suppliers International at a level that is equivalent to the certification pursuant to subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subdivision (1)(A); and
(B) insured, including for liability; and
(C) not the owner or operator of the ride or an employee or agent of the owner or operator.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-i_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The inspection complied with the American Society for Testing and Materials (ASTM) current standard F770 concerning the practices for ownership, operation, maintenance, and inspection of amusement rides and devices.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-i_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A valid certificate of operation has been issued for the ride pursuant to section 722 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>After a ride has been inspected pursuant to subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The owner or operator shall submit the certificate or other record of inspection to the Secretary of State within 15 business days following the date of inspection.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An adhesive sticker, in a format to be determined by the Secretary of State, shall be affixed to the ride that indicates:
(A) the date and location the inspection was completed; and
(B) the name of the inspector.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The owner or operator shall submit a certification, in a format to be determined by the Secretary of State, to the organization hosting a fair, field day, or other event or location, at which the owner or operator intends to operate a ride, stating that the ride has been inspected pursuant to subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section and stickers have been affixed pursuant to this subsection prior to the ride being used to carry or convey passengers.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A ride shall be inspected for safety by the owner or operator:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>after the ride has been set up but before being used to carry or convey passengers; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>every day thereafter that the ride is used to carry or convey passengers.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The owner or operator of an amusement ride shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>keep records of all safety inspections;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>make those records available to the Secretary of State or the Office of the Attorney General promptly upon request;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-d_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>keep a paper or electronic copy of all required forms or certifications, and of all safety inspections conducted by the owner or operator during the preceding 12 months for each ride:
(A) on or near that ride; or
(B) at the office of the amusement ride operator; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-723a_subsec-d_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>operate, maintain, and inspect all rides in compliance with ASTM current standards for ownership, operation, maintenance, and inspection of amusement rides and devices.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-16_section-724"><akn:num>Section 724</akn:num><akn:heading>Penalty</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>An operator or owner who violates any provision of this chapter shall be fined no more than $500.00 per day for each day the violation continues.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-17"><akn:num>Chapter 17</akn:num><akn:heading>Snowmobiles</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-19"><akn:num>Chapter 19</akn:num><akn:heading>Leisure Time and Benefits for Elders</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1001"><akn:num>Section 1001</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1001_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Commissioner” means the Commissioner of Disabilities, Aging, and Independent Living established by 3 V.S.A. § 3085a.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1001_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Passport” means a “Green Mountain Passport” as provided by section 1002 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1001_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“State-sponsored public event” means all events, exhibits, concerts, or museums fully supported by State funds to which the public is invited and all State parks, historical sites, and State lands normally open to the public.  Overnight camping is excluded subject to regulations granted by the Department of Forests, Parks and Recreation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1001_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Medical statistics” means information as to whether the passport holder has any chronic ailment or requires special medication.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1002"><akn:num>Section 1002</akn:num><akn:heading>Green Mountain Passport; eligibility</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1002_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any person is eligible to obtain a Green Mountain Passport who:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1002_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>is:
(A) at least 62 years of age; or
(B) a veteran of the uniformed services; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1002_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>is a resident of the State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1002_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A Green Mountain Passport application shall be issued by the clerk of any town to a resident of that town who swears under oath that he or she meets the eligibility criteria established pursuant to subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1002_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section. A fee of $2.00 will be charged at the time of application and shall be retained by the town issuing the passport. The town clerk shall issue the actual passport. Records shall be maintained as prescribed by law. Statistical information shall be furnished to the Commissioner upon request.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1002_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Forms for the issuance of passports shall be prepared by the Commissioner and provided in sufficient number by him or her to the clerk of each town.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1003"><akn:num>Section 1003</akn:num><akn:heading>Passport privileges</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1003_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Upon the exhibit of a Green Mountain Passport, the bearer shall be entitled to free admission to any fully State-sponsored public event and to any benefits offered by private entities pursuant to section 1004 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1003_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Upon the exhibit of the Green Mountain Passport, the bearer shall be entitled to one day’s admission to any fair, field days, or exposition that is either fully or partially supported by State grants or stipends, and that operates for more than one day.  The management of such fair, field days, or exposition shall publicize the day on which the passports will be honored at least one week prior to the beginning of such an event.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1004"><akn:num>Section 1004</akn:num><akn:heading>Private cooperation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of Human Services may instruct the Commissioner to prepare a decal containing a suitable symbol and make them available to private businesses cooperating in the passport program for display at each such business establishment.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-19_section-1005"><akn:num>Section 1005</akn:num><akn:heading>Misuse of passport; forgery; penalty</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A person who makes any false statement on an application for a passport or who possesses or uses a passport issued to another or falsely makes, alters, forges, or counterfeits a passport shall be fined not more than $500.00 or imprisoned for not more than six months or both.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-21"><akn:num>Chapter 21</akn:num><akn:heading>Boxing</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-31_chapter-23"><akn:num>Chapter 23</akn:num><akn:heading>Games of Chance</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1201"><akn:num>Section 1201</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1201_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Break-open ticket” means a lottery utilizing a card or ticket of the so-called pickle card, jar ticket, or break-open variety commonly bearing the name “Lucky 7,” “Nevada Club,” “Victory Bar,” “Texas Poker,” “Triple Bingo,” or any other name.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1201_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Commissioner” means the Commissioner of Liquor and Lottery.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1201_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) “Distributor” means a person that purchases break-open tickets from a manufacturer and sells or distributes break-open tickets at wholesale in Vermont. “Distributor” shall include any officer, employee, or agent of a corporation or dissolved corporation that has a duty to act for the corporation in complying with the requirements of this chapter.
(B) “Distributor” shall not include a person who distributes only jar tickets that are used only for merchandise prizes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1201_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Manufacturer” means a person that designs, assembles, fabricates, produces, constructs, or otherwise prepares a break-open ticket for sale to a distributor.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1201_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Nonprofit organization” means a nonprofit corporation that is qualified for tax exempt status under I.R.C. § 501(c), as amended, and that has engaged, in good faith, in charitable, religious, educational, or civic activities in Vermont on a regular basis during the preceding year. “Nonprofit organization” also includes churches, schools, fire departments, municipalities, fraternal organizations, and organizations that operate agricultural fairs or field days, and that have engaged, in good faith, in charitable, religious, educational, or civic activities in Vermont on a regular basis during the preceding year. An organization shall be considered a nonprofit organization under this subdivision only if it certifies annually, on a form with whatever information is required by the Commissioner, how it meets the definition under this subdivision.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1202"><akn:num>Section 1202</akn:num><akn:heading>License required</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1202_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Manufacture.   Break-open tickets sold in Vermont shall be manufactured only by a person licensed by the Commissioner. A licensed manufacturer shall sell break-open tickets only to distributors licensed under this chapter. A distributor licensed under this chapter shall purchase break-open tickets only from a manufacturer licensed under this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1202_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Distribution.   A distributor who sells or distributes break-open tickets for resale in Vermont shall be licensed by the Commissioner and shall also be:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1202_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a natural person who is a resident of Vermont;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1202_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a partnership in which the majority of partners are residents of Vermont;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1202_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a corporation incorporated under the laws of Vermont, provided that a majority of the ownership interest is held by residents of Vermont; or</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1202_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a person who is not a resident of Vermont and whose state of residence allows residents or corporations of Vermont to distribute break-open tickets in that state under similar terms and conditions as provided under this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1203"><akn:num>Section 1203</akn:num><akn:heading>Distribution; retail purchase and sale</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1203_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Only nonprofit organizations may purchase break-open tickets from a distributor licensed under this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1203_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>No person, other than a licensed distributor or a nonprofit organization acting under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1203_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, shall distribute a box of break-open tickets. No person shall distribute a box of break-open tickets unless the box bears indicia as required by the Commissioner. No person shall distribute or sell a break-open ticket at retail unless the ticket bears a unique serial number.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1203_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A distributor licensed under this chapter may sell break-open tickets only to nonprofit organizations as defined in subdivision 1201</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1203_subsec-c_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter, except that a person other than a licensed distributor may sell such tickets to a licensed distributor upon written approval of the Commissioner.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1203_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Only nonprofit organizations may sell break-open tickets at retail.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1203_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Break-open tickets shall not be sold at premises licensed to sell alcoholic beverages except:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1203_subsec-e_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>at clubs as defined in 7 V.S.A. § 2; or</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1203_subsec-e_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a nonprofit organization may sell break-open tickets at premises licensed to sell alcoholic beverages if, notwithstanding 13 V.S.A. § 2143</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1203_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A nonprofit organization that sells break-open tickets, other than a club as defined in 7 V.S.A. § 2, shall report to the Department of Liquor and Lottery on a quarterly basis the number of tickets purchased and distributed, and the corresponding serial numbers of those tickets, the amount of revenue realized by the nonprofit organization, and the amounts accounted for under subdivisions </akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1203_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The provisions of this chapter regarding sales and purchases of break-open tickets also apply to transfers of break-open tickets for no charge.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1204"><akn:num>Section 1204</akn:num><akn:heading>License requirements; fees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1204_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Upon application and payment of the fee, the Commissioner may issue the following licenses to qualified applicants:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1204_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Manufacturer annual license: $3,000.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1204_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Distributor annual license: $2,000.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1204_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A license shall not be granted to an individual who has been convicted of a felony within five years of the license application nor to an entity in which any partner, officer, or director has been convicted of a felony within five years of the application.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1204_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Licenses issued under this section may be renewed annually on October 1, upon reapplication and payment of the licensing fee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1204_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All fees collected pursuant to this section shall be deposited into the Liquor Control Enterprise Fund.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1205"><akn:num>Section 1205</akn:num><akn:heading>Records; report</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1205_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Each distributor and manufacturer licensed under this chapter shall maintain records and books relating to the distribution and sale of break-open tickets and to any other expenditure required by the Commissioner. A licensee shall make its records and books available to the Commissioner for auditing.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1205_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Each licensed distributor shall file with the Commissioner, on the same schedule as the distributor files sales tax returns, the following information for the preceding reporting period:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1205_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the names of organizations to which boxes of break-open tickets were sold;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1205_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the number of boxes of break-open tickets sold to each organization; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1205_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the ticket denomination and serial numbers of tickets for each box.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1205_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Records and reports filed under this section shall be designated confidential unless, under State or federal law or regulation, the record or information may be disclosed to specifically designated persons.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1205_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notwithstanding subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1205_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, the Commissioner of Liquor and Lottery shall provide the records and reports filed under this section to the Attorney General, upon request.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1206"><akn:num>Section 1206</akn:num><akn:heading>Enforcement</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1206_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any person who intentionally violates section 1203 of this chapter shall be fined not more than $500.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1206_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any person who intentionally violates section 1202, 1204, or 1205 of this chapter shall be fined not more than $10,000.00 for the first offense and fined not more than $20,000.00 or imprisoned not more than one year, or both, for each subsequent offense.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1206_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In addition to the criminal penalties provided under subsections</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1206_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1206_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, any person who violates a provision of this chapter shall be subject to one or more of the following penalties:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1206_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Revocation or suspension by the Commissioner of a license granted pursuant to this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1206_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Confiscation of break-open tickets or confiscation of the revenues derived from the sale of those tickets, or both.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1207"><akn:num>Section 1207</akn:num><akn:heading>Appeals</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1207_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this chapter and any person aggrieved by the Commissioner’s refusal to issue or renew a license under this chapter may appeal in writing to the Commissioner for review of such action. The Commissioner shall thereafter grant a hearing subject to the provisions of 3 V.S.A. chapter 25 upon the matter and notify the aggrieved person in writing of his or her determination. The Commissioner’s determination may be appealed within 30 days to the Washington Superior Court or the Superior Court of the county in which the taxpayer resides or has a place of business.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1208"><akn:num>Section 1208</akn:num><akn:heading>Rulemaking</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1208_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the actual cost of the break-open tickets;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1208_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the prizes awarded; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-31_chapter-23_section-1208_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>any sales tax due on the sale of break-open tickets under 32 V.S.A. chapter 233.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter></akn:title></akn:body></akn:act></akn:akomaNtoso>