<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akn:akomaNtoso xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><akn:act><akn:meta><akn:identification source="#cosilico"><akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-04" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-04" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-05-01" name="release" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#vermont-legislature" /><akn:FRBRcountry value="us-vt" /><akn:FRBRnumber value="04" /><akn:FRBRname value="Vermont Statutes Annotated" /></akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-04/eng@2023-05-01" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-04/eng@2023-05-01" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-05-01" name="publication" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /><akn:FRBRlanguage language="eng" /></akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRManifestation><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-04/eng@2023-05-01/akn.xml" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-04/eng@2023-05-01/akn.xml" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /></akn:FRBRManifestation></akn:identification><akn:references><akn:TLCOrganization eId="vermont-legislature" href="https://legislature.vermont.gov" showAs="Vermont General Assembly" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico" /></akn:references></akn:meta><akn:body><akn:title eId="title-04"><akn:num>Title 04</akn:num><akn:heading>Judiciary</akn:heading><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-1"><akn:num>Chapter 1</akn:num><akn:heading>Supreme Court</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-3"><akn:num>Chapter 3</akn:num><akn:heading>Superior Judges and Superior Courts</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-5"><akn:num>Chapter 5</akn:num><akn:heading>Court of Chancery</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-7"><akn:num>Chapter 7</akn:num><akn:heading>Probate Courts</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-9"><akn:num>Chapter 9</akn:num><akn:heading>District Court</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-10"><akn:num>Chapter 10</akn:num><akn:heading>Family Court</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-11"><akn:num>Chapter 11</akn:num><akn:heading>Justices of the Peace</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-13"><akn:num>Chapter 13</akn:num><akn:heading>Judicial Council</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-15"><akn:num>Chapter 15</akn:num><akn:heading>Judicial Nominations and Appointments</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-17"><akn:num>Chapter 17</akn:num><akn:heading>Clerks of Court; Court and Other Records and Accounts</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-19"><akn:num>Chapter 19</akn:num><akn:heading>Stenographic Reporters</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-21"><akn:num>Chapter 21</akn:num><akn:heading>Commissioners in Other States and Foreign Countries</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-23"><akn:num>Chapter 23</akn:num><akn:heading>Attorneys</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-25"><akn:num>Chapter 25</akn:num><akn:heading>Jury Commission</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-27"><akn:num>Chapter 27</akn:num><akn:heading>Environmental Court</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-29"><akn:num>Chapter 29</akn:num><akn:heading>Judicial Bureau</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-1"><akn:num>Chapter 1</akn:num><akn:heading>Supreme Court</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-1"><akn:num>Section 1</akn:num><akn:heading>Unified court system established</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Judiciary shall be a unified court system under the administrative control of the Supreme Court. It shall consist of an appellate division, which shall be the Supreme Court, and a trial division, which shall consist of a trial court of general jurisdiction to be known as the Superior Court, and a Judicial Bureau.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-2"><akn:num>Section 2</akn:num><akn:heading>Supreme Court established; jurisdiction</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-2_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Supreme Court shall have exclusive jurisdiction of appeals from judgments, rulings, and orders of the Superior Court, administrative agencies, boards, commissions, and officers unless otherwise provided by law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-2_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Supreme Court shall have original jurisdiction, concurrent with the Superior Court, of proceedings in certiorari, mandamus, prohibition, and quo warranto and shall have jurisdiction to issue all writs, processes, and orders that may be necessary to the furtherance of justice and the regular execution of the law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-3"><akn:num>Section 3</akn:num><akn:heading>Judicial officers; administrative and disciplinary control</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Supreme Court shall have administrative and disciplinary control of all judicial officers of the State, in addition to and not inconsistent with the constitutional powers of the General Assembly in those matters. It shall promulgate a Code of Judicial Ethics that shall be binding on those officers for disciplinary purposes. It may promulgate rules providing for the exercise of disciplinary control, including providing for the manner of making and disposing of complaints of violations of judicial ethics, a committee of the Judiciary for determining issues raised by complaints, and imposing sanctions, including when appropriate suspension from judicial duties for the balance of the term of the judicial officer charged.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-4"><akn:num>Section 4</akn:num><akn:heading>Justices</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-4_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Supreme Court shall consist of one Chief Justice and four Associate Justices, appointed in accordance with the Constitution and chapter 15 of this title or retained in office under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-4_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-4_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When the Office of Chief Justice becomes vacant for any reason, the duties of that Office shall forthwith devolve upon the Justice with the longest period of service on the Supreme Court until the appointment of a Chief Justice in accordance with the Constitution.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-4_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A Supreme Court Justice may file in the Office of the Secretary of State, on or before September 1 of the year preceding the expiration of the term for which the Justice was appointed or retained, a declaration that the Justice will be a candidate for retention. However, a Justice appointed and having taken the oath of office after September 1 of the year preceding the expiration of the term of office shall automatically be a candidate for retention without filing notice. When a Justice files such a declaration, the Justice’s name shall be submitted to the General Assembly for a vote on retention. The General Assembly shall vote upon one ballot on the question “Shall the following Supreme Court Justices be retained in office?” The names of the Justices shall be followed by “Yes __ No __ .” If a majority of those voting on the question vote against retention, upon expiration of the term of office, a vacancy shall exist that shall be filled by appointment in accordance with the Constitution and chapter 15 of this title; if the majority vote is in favor of retention, the Justice shall, unless removed for cause, remain in office for another term and, at its end, shall be eligible for retention in office in the manner prescribed pursuant to this subsection.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-4_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Court Administrator shall notify the Secretary of State whenever a Justice is appointed and takes the oath of office after September 1 of the year preceding the expiration of the term of office to which the Justice has succeeded, thereby resulting in automatic notification of an intention to continue in office. Whenever a Justice files a declaration under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-4_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, or notification occurs automatically, the Secretary of State shall notify the President of the Senate, the Speaker of the House, the Office of Legislative Counsel, and the Office of Legislative Operations forthwith.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-5"><akn:num>Section 5</akn:num><akn:heading>Term of Justices</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-5_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The term of the Justices, except in case of an appointment to fill a vacancy, shall be for a term of six years from and including April 1 in the year of such appointment or retention under subsection 4</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-5_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title.  When a Justice of the Supreme Court who has sat at the hearing of a cause retires from office before such cause is decided, the Justice shall remain a member of such Court for the purpose of assisting in the decision thereof and of signing the entry order, provided that such service may extend only to the following term of Court.  For such service, the Justice shall receive a reasonable compensation to be fixed by the Justices of such Court and reasonable expenses while on office business.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-5_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A Justice shall remain in office until a successor is appointed and qualified, unless sooner removed for cause or unless he or she resigns.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-6"><akn:num>Section 6</akn:num><akn:heading>Disqualification of Justices</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A Justice of the Supreme Court shall not be an officer in a railroad, banking, or insurance corporation in this State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-8"><akn:num>Section 8</akn:num><akn:heading>General and special terms</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The terms of the Supreme Court and times and places of those terms shall be stated by administrative order of the Supreme Court.  The Court Administrator shall act as Clerk of the Supreme Court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-17"><akn:num>Section 17</akn:num><akn:heading>Reporter of decisions; appointment</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Justices of the Supreme Court shall in each even year appoint a reporter of the decisions of the Court and may fill a vacancy in such office.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-18"><akn:num>Section 18</akn:num><akn:heading>Opinions; filing and preservation; copies</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-18_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Each opinion of the Supreme Court shall be signed by one or more of the Justices and filed with the reporter of decisions.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-18_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When a volume of the Vermont Reports has been published, the reporter shall transmit for preservation the original opinions in the cases printed in the volume to the clerk of the general term.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-18_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>On tender of the fees for a certified copy of any opinion, the reporter or clerk shall furnish the certified copy to any person applying for the same.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-18_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The reporter shall forthwith furnish the Commissioner of Labor, free of charge, copies of all opinions filed involving the administration of the labor laws of the State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-20"><akn:num>Section 20</akn:num><akn:heading>Reports of decisions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The reporter shall annually prepare the decisions of the Court for publication, read the proof, and superintend the printing and binding thereof.  All causes decided shall be reported within one year after the decisions are made.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-21"><akn:num>Section 21</akn:num><akn:heading>Court Administrator</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Office of Court Administrator is hereby created.  He or she shall be appointed by and serve at the pleasure of the Supreme Court, which shall fix his or her salary and prescribe his or her duties from time to time.  He or she shall devote full time to his or her official duties to the exclusion of engagement in any other business or profession for profit.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-21a"><akn:num>Section 21a</akn:num><akn:heading>Duties of the Chief Superior Judge</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-21a_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Chief Superior Judge shall assign and specially assign Superior judges, including themselves, and Environmental judges to the Superior Court. All Superior judges except Environmental judges shall be subject to the requirements of rotation as ordered by the Supreme Court. Assignments made pursuant to the rotation schedule shall be subject to the approval of the Supreme Court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-21a_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In making any assignment under this section, the Chief Superior Judge shall give consideration to the experience, temperament, and training of a judge and the needs of the court. In making an assignment to the Environmental Division, the Chief Superior Judge shall give consideration to experience and expertise in environmental and land use law and shall assign or specially assign judges in a manner to provide appropriate attention to all geographic areas of the State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-21a_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In making any assignments to the Environmental Division under this section, the Chief Superior Judge shall regularly assign two judges, at least one of whom shall be an Environmental judge. An Environmental judge may be assigned to other divisions in the Superior Court for a period of time not exceeding two years. When assigned to other divisions in the Superior Court, the Environmental judge shall have all the powers and responsibilities of a Superior judge.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-22"><akn:num>Section 22</akn:num><akn:heading>Designation and special assignment of judicial officers and retired judicial officers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Chief Justice may appoint and assign a retired Justice or judge, with the Justice’s or judge’s consent, or a Superior or Probate judge to a special assignment on the Supreme Court. The Chief Justice may appoint, and the Chief Superior Judge shall assign, an active or retired Justice or a retired judge, with the Justice’s or judge’s consent, to any special assignment in the Superior Court or the Judicial Bureau.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Chief Superior Judge may appoint and assign a judge to any special assignment in the Superior Court. As used in this subdivision, a judge shall include a Superior judge, a Probate judge, a Family Division magistrate, or a judicial hearing officer.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Chief Superior Judge may appoint and assign a member of the Vermont Bar residing within the State of Vermont to serve temporarily as:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>an acting judge in Superior Court;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>an acting magistrate;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>an acting Probate judge; or</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>an acting hearing officer to hear cases in the Judicial Bureau.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Special assignments may be made as a result of the disqualification, disability, or death of a Justice or judge, or because of the vacancy of a judicial office, or because the business of the court requires. When so designated and assigned and in the actual performance of those judicial duties, an appointee shall have all the powers and authority of the assigned judicial office, but not otherwise, and shall retain them until the duties devolving upon him or her are fully performed. A designated and assigned Justice or judge or acting judge shall not be counted in the number of Justices or judges provided by law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Supreme Court shall develop and provide whatever judicial training it deems necessary to enable persons who are specially assigned under this section to carry out their assigned judicial duties.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In making an appointment under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-22_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, the Chief Superior Judge shall apply the criteria and standards for judicial appointments contained in section 601 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-23"><akn:num>Section 23</akn:num><akn:heading>Compensation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>In the performance of judicial duties, the specially assigned judicial officer shall be entitled to a per diem equal to the daily compensation authorized for the judicial position to which he or she is assigned and necessary expenses.  An acting judge in Criminal Division of the Superior Court shall receive $75.00 a day and necessary expenses.  Payment of compensation for special judicial assignments shall not diminish the retirement compensation of retired judicial officers. However, a retired judicial officer shall not receive total annual compensation in excess of the annual salary of a Superior judge.  Active judicial officers shall receive the compensation of their regular judicial office or that of the office to which they are specially assigned, whichever is greater.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-25"><akn:num>Section 25</akn:num><akn:heading>Judicial Branch; furlough days; administrative leave</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-25_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Supreme Court is authorized to declare up to 12 unpaid Judicial Branch furlough days in a fiscal year and on those days may close the courts in the State.  For purposes of implementing a furlough day, the Supreme Court is authorized to reduce on a daily or hourly basis all salaries established by 32 V.S.A. §§ 1003</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-25_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Supreme Court is authorized to pay on an hourly basis all persons whose compensation is established by 32 V.S.A. §§ 1010, 1511, and 1551 and 4 V.S.A. §§ 23, 75, and 356.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-25_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Supreme Court may allow Supreme Court Justices, Superior judges, Environmental judges, magistrates, hearing officers, Probate judges, Superior Court clerks, or any State-compensated employees of the Judicial Branch not covered by a collective bargaining agreement to take an administrative leave of absence without pay, or with pay if the person is called to active duty in support of an extended national or State military operation. These judicial officers and State employees shall be entitled to be compensated in the same manner as Judicial Branch employees covered by a collective bargaining agreement called to active duty. The Court Administrator, at the direction of the Supreme Court, shall include provisions in the personnel rules of the Judiciary to administer these leaves of absence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-26"><akn:num>Section 26</akn:num><akn:heading>Half-time judges</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Of the Superior judge positions authorized by this title, up to two may be shared, each by two half-time judges. Of the magistrate positions authorized by this title, one may be shared by two half-time magistrates. Of the hearing officer positions authorized by this title, one may be shared by two half-time hearing officers. Half-time Superior judges, magistrates, and hearing officers shall be paid proportionally and shall receive the same benefits as State employees who share a job. Half-time Superior judges, magistrates, and hearing officers shall not engage in the active practice of law for remuneration.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-27"><akn:num>Section 27</akn:num><akn:heading>Court Technology Special Fund</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-27_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The acquisition and maintenance of software and hardware needed for case management, electronic filing, an electronic document management system, and the expense of implementation, including training.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-27_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The acquisition and maintenance of electronic audio and video court recording and conferencing equipment.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-27_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The acquisition, maintenance, and support of the Judiciary’s information technology network, including training.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-27a"><akn:num>Section 27a</akn:num><akn:heading>Contracts for Internet service</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Every contract to provide broadband Internet access service, as defined in 3 V.S.A. § 348(d)(1), for the Judicial Branch shall include terms and conditions requiring that the Internet service provider certify that it is in compliance with the consumer protection and net neutrality standards established in 3 V.S.A. § 348.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-27b"><akn:num>Section 27b</akn:num><akn:heading>Electronically filed verified documents</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-27b_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A registered electronic filer in the Judiciary’s electronic document filing system may file any document that would otherwise require the approval or verification of a notary by filing the document with the following language inserted above the signature and date:
“I declare that the above statement is true and accurate to the best of my knowledge and belief. I understand that if the above statement is false, I will be subject to the penalty of perjury.”</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-27b_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A document filed pursuant to subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-27b_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section shall not require the approval or verification of a notary.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-27b_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>This section shall not apply to an affidavit in support of a search warrant application or to an application for a nontestimonial identification order.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-28"><akn:num>Section 28</akn:num><akn:heading>Municipal Ticket Repayment Revolving Fund</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-28_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Municipal Ticket Repayment Revolving Fund is created for the purpose of facilitating the transfer of incorrectly deposited Judicial Bureau payments to the appropriate municipality. A municipality may request a loan from the Municipal Ticket Repayment Revolving Fund in the amount owed another municipality if the municipality requesting the loan:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-28_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>received payments from the Judicial Bureau that were actually owed to the other municipality for penalties collected by the Judicial Bureau for violations of an ordinance within the other municipality; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-28_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>received such payments from the Judicial Bureau between June 30, 2004 and June 30, 2007.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-28_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Court Administrator shall have the authority to approve all loans from the Municipal Ticket Repayment Revolving Fund. To request a loan from the Fund, a municipality shall file an application on a form approved by the Court Administrator by July 1, 2008. The application shall contain the following information:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-28_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>an agreement, signed by both municipalities, defining the amount owed by one municipality to the other; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-28_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a plan for the municipality requesting the loan to repay the Fund by July 1, 2013. The plan may authorize the Court Administrator to withhold Judicial Bureau violation payments to the municipality requesting the loan for deposit into the Fund.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-28_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The maximum loan balance at any time shall be $250,000.00 for one municipality and $400,000.00 for all municipalities. The Court Administrator shall administer the Municipal Ticket Repayment Revolving Fund and shall establish procedures to allocate the available funds fairly and equitably. Upon the recommendation of the Court Administrator, the Secretary of Administration shall approve spending in anticipation of receipts from the Fund up to a maximum of $220,000.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-28_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Nothing in this section shall prohibit the sending or receiving municipality from otherwise agreeing on, or bringing a civil action to resolve, overpayment issues prior to June 30, 2004.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-28_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Upon completion of the agreements authorized by this section, the remaining balance in the Fund shall be deposited in the Court Technology Special Fund pursuant to section 27 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-30"><akn:num>Section 30</akn:num><akn:heading>Superior Court</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-30_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-30_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A Superior Court having statewide jurisdiction is created. The Superior Court shall have the following divisions:
(A) A Civil Division, which shall be a court of record and have jurisdiction over the matters described in section 31 of this title. The Vermont Rules of Civil Procedure shall apply in the Civil Division.
(B) A Criminal Division, which shall be a court of record and have jurisdiction over the matters described in section 32 of this title. The Vermont Rules of Criminal Procedure shall apply to criminal matters in the Criminal Division, and the Vermont Rules of Civil Procedure shall apply to civil matters in the Criminal Division.
(C) A Family Division, which shall be a court of record and have jurisdiction over the matters described in section 33 of this title. The Vermont Rules of Family Procedure shall apply in the Family Division.
(D) An Environmental Division, which shall be a court of record and have jurisdiction over the matters described in section 34 of this title. The Vermont Rules for Environmental Proceedings shall apply in the Environmental Division.
(E) A Probate Division, which shall have jurisdiction over the matters described in section 35 of this title. The Vermont Rules of Probate Procedure shall apply in the Probate Division.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-30_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Supreme Court shall promulgate rules, subject to review by the Legislative Committee on Judicial Rules under 12 V.S.A. chapter 1, that establish criteria for the transfer of cases between divisions.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-30_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Supreme Court shall by rule divide the Superior Court into 14 geographical units that shall follow county lines, except that, subject to the venue requirements of subsection 1001</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-30_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title, the Environmental Division shall be a court of statewide jurisdiction and shall not be otherwise divided into geographical units. The Superior Court shall be held in each unit of the State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-30_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Terms of the Superior Court shall be stated by administrative orders of the Supreme Court. The Court Administrator shall provide appropriate security services for each court in the State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-31"><akn:num>Section 31</akn:num><akn:heading>Jurisdiction; Civil Division</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-31_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>original and exclusive jurisdiction of all original civil actions, except as otherwise provided in sections 2, 32, 33, 34, 35, and 1102 of this title;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-31_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>appellate jurisdiction of causes, civil and criminal, appealable to the court;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-31_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>original jurisdiction, concurrent with the Supreme Court, of proceedings in certiorari, mandamus, prohibition, and quo warranto;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-31_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>exclusive jurisdiction to hear and dispose of any requests to modify or enforce orders in civil cases previously issued by the Superior or District Court other than orders relating to those actions listed in sections 437 and 454 of this title; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-31_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>jurisdiction to hear and dispose of any other matter brought before the court pursuant to law that is not subject to the jurisdiction of another division.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32"><akn:num>Section 32</akn:num><akn:heading>Jurisdiction; Criminal Division</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Criminal Division shall have jurisdiction to try, render judgment, and pass sentence in prosecutions for felonies and misdemeanors.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Criminal Division shall have jurisdiction to try and finally determine prosecutions for violations of bylaws or ordinances of a village, town, or city, except as otherwise provided.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Criminal Division shall have jurisdiction of the following civil actions:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>appeals of final decisions of the Judicial Bureau;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>DUI license suspension hearings filed pursuant to 23 V.S.A. chapter 24;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>extradition proceedings filed pursuant to 13 V.S.A. chapter 159;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-c_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>drug forfeiture proceedings under 18 V.S.A. chapter 84, subchapter 2;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-c_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>fish and wildlife forfeiture proceedings under 10 V.S.A. chapter 109;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-c_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>liquor forfeiture proceedings under 7 V.S.A. chapter 19;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-c_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>hearings relating to refusal to provide a DNA sample pursuant to 20 V.S.A. § 1935;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-c_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>automobile forfeiture and immobilization proceedings under 23 V.S.A. chapters 9 and 13;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-c_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>sex offender proceedings pursuant to 13 V.S.A. §§ 5411</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>and 5411d</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-e_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>restitution modification proceedings pursuant to 13 V.S.A. § 7043</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-e_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>municipal parking violation proceedings pursuant to 24 V.S.A. § 1974a</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>if the municipality has established an administrative procedure enabling a person to contest the violation and the person has exhausted the administrative procedure;</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-e_subsec-12"><akn:num>(12)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>proceedings to enforce 9 V.S.A. chapter 74, relating to energy efficiency standards for appliances and equipment; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-32_subsec-e_subsec-13"><akn:num>(13)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>proceedings to enforce 30 V.S.A. § 53, relating to commercial building energy standards.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33"><akn:num>Section 33</akn:num><akn:heading>Jurisdiction; Family Division</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notwithstanding any other provision of law to the contrary, the Family Division shall have exclusive jurisdiction to hear and dispose of the following proceedings filed or pending on or after October 1, 1990:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All desertion and support proceedings and all parentage actions filed pursuant to 15 V.S.A. chapter 5.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All rights of married women proceedings filed pursuant to 15 V.S.A. chapter 3.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All enforcement of support proceedings filed pursuant to Title 15B.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All annulment and divorce proceedings filed pursuant to 15 V.S.A. chapter 11.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All parent and child proceedings filed pursuant to 15 V.S.A. chapter 15.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Grandparents’ visitation proceedings filed pursuant to 15 V.S.A. chapter 18.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All uniform child custody proceedings filed pursuant to 15 V.S.A. chapter 20.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All juvenile proceedings filed pursuant to 33 V.S.A. chapters 51, 52, and 53, including proceedings involving “youthful offenders” pursuant to 33 V.S.A. § 5281 whether the matter originated in the Criminal or Family Division of the Superior Court, except for a proceeding charging the holder of a commercial driver’s license as defined in 23 V.S.A. § 4103 with an offense or violation listed in 23 V.S.A. § 4116 that would result in the license holder being disqualified from driving a commercial motor vehicle if convicted.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All enforcement of support proceedings filed pursuant to 33 V.S.A. chapter 39.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All guardianship services proceedings for persons with developmental disabilities filed pursuant to 18 V.S.A. chapter 215.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All mental health proceedings filed pursuant to 18 V.S.A. chapters 179, 181, and 185.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-12"><akn:num>(12)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All involuntary sterilization proceedings filed pursuant to 18 V.S.A. chapter 204.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-13"><akn:num>(13)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All care for persons with intellectual disabilities proceedings filed pursuant to 18 V.S.A. chapter 206.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-14"><akn:num>(14)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All abuse prevention proceedings filed pursuant to 15 V.S.A. chapter 21. Any Superior judge may issue orders for emergency relief pursuant to 15 V.S.A. § 1104.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-15"><akn:num>(15)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All abuse and exploitation proceedings filed pursuant to 33 V.S.A. chapter 69, subchapter 2.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-16"><akn:num>(16)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All proceedings relating to the dissolution of a civil union.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-17"><akn:num>(17)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All requests to modify or enforce orders previously issued by the District or Superior Court relating to any of the proceedings identified in subdivisions (1)-</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-16"><akn:num>(16)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-a_subsec-18"><akn:num>(18)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Concurrent with the Probate Division, special immigration judicial determinations regarding the custody and care of children within the meaning of the federal Immigration and Nationality Act (8 U.S.C. § 1101</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-33_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Family Division has jurisdiction to hear and dispose of proceedings involving misdemeanor motor vehicle offenses filed or pending on or after July 1, 2016, pursuant to 33 V.S.A. §§ 5201, 5203, and 5280. The Family Division of the Superior Court shall forward a record of any conviction for violation of a law related to motor vehicle traffic control, other than a parking violation, to the Commissioner of Motor Vehicles pursuant to 23 V.S.A. § 1709.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-34"><akn:num>Section 34</akn:num><akn:heading>Jurisdiction; Environmental Division</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-34_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>jurisdiction of matters arising under 10 V.S.A. chapters 201 and 220;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-34_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>jurisdiction of matters arising under 24 V.S.A. chapter 61, subchapter 12 and chapter 117; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-34_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>original jurisdiction to revoke permits under 10 V.S.A. chapter 151.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35"><akn:num>Section 35</akn:num><akn:heading>Jurisdiction; Probate Division</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the probate of wills;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the settlement of estates;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the administration of trusts pursuant to Title 14A;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>trusts of absent persons’ estates;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>charitable, cemetery, and philanthropic trusts;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the appointment of guardians, and of the powers, duties, and rights of guardians and wards;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>proceedings concerning 18 V.S.A. chapter 231;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>accountings of attorneys-in-fact where no guardian has been appointed and the agent has reason to believe the principal is incompetent;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>adoptions and relinquishment for adoption;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>uniform gifts to minors;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>changes of name;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-12"><akn:num>(12)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>issuance of new birth certificates and amendment of birth certificates;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-13"><akn:num>(13)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>correction or amendment of civil marriage certificates and death certificates;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-14"><akn:num>(14)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>emergency waiver of premarital medical certificates;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-15"><akn:num>(15)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>proceedings relating to cemetery lots;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-16"><akn:num>(16)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>trusts relating to community mausoleums or columbaria;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-17"><akn:num>(17)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>civil actions brought under 18 V.S.A. chapter 107, subchapter 3, relating to disposition of remains;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-18"><akn:num>(18)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>proceedings relating to the conveyance of a homestead interest of a spouse under a legal disability;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-19"><akn:num>(19)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the issuance of declaratory judgments;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-20"><akn:num>(20)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>issuance of certificates of public good authorizing the civil marriage of persons under 16 years of age;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-21"><akn:num>(21)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>appointment of administrators to discharge mortgages held by deceased mortgagees;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-22"><akn:num>(22)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>appointment of trustees for persons confined under sentences of imprisonment;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-23"><akn:num>(23)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>fixation of compensation and expenses of boards of arbitrators of death taxes of Vermont domiciliaries;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-24"><akn:num>(24)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>emancipation of minors proceedings filed pursuant to 12 V.S.A. chapter 217;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-25"><akn:num>(25)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>grandparent visitation proceedings under 15 V.S.A. chapter 18;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-26"><akn:num>(26)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>other matters as provided by law; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-35_subsec-27"><akn:num>(27)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>concurrent with the Family Division, special immigration judicial determinations regarding the custody and care of children within the meaning of the federal Immigration and Nationality Act (8 U.S.C. § 1101(a)</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36"><akn:num>Section 36</akn:num><akn:heading>Composition of the court</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Unless otherwise specified by law, when in session, a Superior Court shall consist of:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For cases in the Civil or Family Division, one presiding Superior judge and two assistant judges, if available.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) For cases in the Family Division, except as provided in subdivision (B) of this subdivision (2), one presiding judicial officer and two assistant judges, if available.
(B) The Family Division shall consist of one presiding judicial officer sitting alone in the following proceedings:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>all juvenile proceedings filed pursuant to 33 V.S.A. chapters 51, 52, and 53, including proceedings involving “youthful offenders” pursuant to 33 V.S.A. § 5281, whether the matter originated in the Criminal or Family Division of the Superior Court;
(ii) all guardianship services proceedings for persons with developmental disabilities filed pursuant to 18 V.S.A. chapter 215;
(iii) all mental health proceedings filed pursuant to 18 V.S.A. chapters 179, 181, and 185;
(iv) all involuntary sterilization proceedings filed pursuant to 18 V.S.A. chapter 204;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36_subsec-v"><akn:num>(v)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>all care for persons with intellectual disabilities proceedings filed pursuant to 18 V.S.A. chapter 206; and
(vi) all proceedings specifically within the jurisdiction of the office of magistrate except child support contempt proceedings held pursuant to a magistrate’s jurisdiction under subdivision 461</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36_subsec-v_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title.
(C) Use of the term “judicial officer” in subdivisions (A) and (B) of this subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36_subsec-v_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>shall not be construed to expand a judicial officer’s subject-matter jurisdiction or conflict with the authority of the Chief Justice or Chief Superior Judge to make special assignments pursuant to section 22 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36_subsec-v_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For cases in the Criminal Division, one Superior judge sitting alone.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36_subsec-v_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For cases in the Probate Division, one Probate judge sitting alone.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36_subsec-v_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For cases in the Environmental Division, one Environmental judge sitting alone.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Questions of law and fact.   In all proceedings, questions of law shall be decided by the presiding judge. In cases not tried before a jury, questions of fact shall be decided by the court. Mixed questions of law and fact shall be deemed to be questions of law. The presiding judge alone shall decide which are questions of law, questions of fact, and mixed questions of law and fact. Written or oral stipulations of fact submitted by the parties shall establish the facts in the submitted stipulation, except that the presiding judge, in the presiding judge’s discretion, may order a hearing on any such stipulated fact. Neither the decision of the presiding judge under this subsection nor participation by an assistant judge in a ruling of law shall be grounds for reversal unless a party makes a timely objection and raises the issue on appeal.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Availability of assistant judges.   If two assistant judges are not available, the court shall consist of one presiding judge and one assistant judge. In the event that court is being held by the presiding judge and one assistant judge and they do not agree on a decision, a mistrial shall be declared. If neither assistant judge is available, the court shall consist of the presiding judge alone, and the unavailability of an assistant judge shall not constitute reversible error.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Method of determining availability.   Before commencing a hearing in any matter in which the court by law may consist of the presiding judge and assistant judges, the assistant judges physically present in the courthouse shall determine whether they are available for the case. If two or more cases are being heard at one time and assistant judges may by law participate in either, each assistant judge may determine in which case he or she will participate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Duty to complete hearing or trial.   After an assistant judge has decided to participate in a hearing or trial, the assistant judge shall not withdraw from the hearing or trial except for cause. However, if the assistant judge is not available for a scheduled hearing or trial or becomes unavailable during trial, the matter may continue without the assistant judge’s participation, and the assistant judge may not return to participate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Emergency relief.   A presiding judge may hear a petition for emergency relief when the court is not sitting and may issue temporary orders as necessary.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-36_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Jury trial.   In order to preserve the right to trial by jury, when issues sounding in law and in equity are presented in the same action, the Supreme Court shall provide by rule for trial by jury, when demanded, of issues sounding in law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-37"><akn:num>Section 37</akn:num><akn:heading>Venue</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-37_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The venue for all actions filed in the Superior Court, whether heard in the Civil, Criminal, Family, Environmental, or Probate Division, shall be as provided in law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-37_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Supreme Court may promulgate venue rules, subject to review by the Legislative Committee on Judicial Rules under 12 V.S.A. chapter 1, which are consistent with the following policies:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-37_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Proceedings involving a case shall be heard in the unit in which the case was brought, subject to the following exceptions:
(A) when the parties have agreed otherwise;
(B) status conferences, minor hearings, or other nonevidentiary proceedings; or
(C) when a change in venue is necessary to ensure access to justice for the parties or required for the fair and efficient administration of justice.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-37_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The electronic filing of cases on a statewide basis should be facilitated, and the Court is authorized to promulgate rules establishing an electronic case-filing system.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-37_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The use of technology to ease travel burdens on citizens and the courts should be promoted. For example, venue requirements should be deemed satisfied for some court proceedings when a person, including a judge, makes an appearance via video technology, even if the judge is not physically present in the same location as the person making the appearance.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-37_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) Subject to subdivision (B) of this subdivision (4), in proceedings involving the termination of parental rights, the Supreme Court is authorized to designate a region of no more than four counties in which the venue for specified types of cases in the region shall be the region as a whole, irrespective of the county in which the venue would lie for the case under the governing statute. A designation under this subdivision shall be made by rule and shall be reviewed by the Legislative Committee on Judicial Rules pursuant to 12 V.S.A. § 1.
(B) A region designated pursuant to subdivision (A) of this subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-37_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>shall not include Grand Isle or Essex County for purposes of permitting termination of parental rights proceedings originating in Grand Isle or Essex County to be heard in other counties or regions unless all parties consent. This subdivision shall not preclude termination of parental rights proceedings originating in other counties from being heard in Grand Isle or Essex County.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-38"><akn:num>Section 38</akn:num><akn:heading>Section 38 repealed effective July 1, 2025. Judicial Masters</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-38_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Chief Superior Judge may appoint a licensed Vermont lawyer who has been engaged in the practice of law in Vermont for at least the last five years to serve as a Judicial Master. The Judicial Master shall be an employee of the Judiciary and be subject to the Code of Judicial Conduct. A Judicial Master shall not engage in the active practice of law for remuneration while serving in this position. In making this appointment, the Administrative Judge shall apply the criteria and standards for judicial appointments contained in section 601 of this title. The Judicial Master may hear and decide the following matters as designated by the Administrative Judge:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-38_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In the Criminal Division of the Superior Court, proceedings in treatment court dockets, as approved by the presiding judge, to ensure compliance with court orders, including attendance and participation with a treatment plan, imposition of sanctions and incentives, including incarceration in the course of the program and dismissal from the program due to noncompliance; the Master shall not have authority to accept pleas or to impose sentences, to hear motions to suppress, or to dismiss for lack of a prima facie case.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-38_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In the Family Division of the Superior Court, in juvenile proceedings, as approved by the presiding judge, to ensure compliance with existing court orders, including attendance and participation in substance abuse, mental health, and other court-ordered counseling; compliance with and modification of parent-child contact; to act as the administrative body to conduct permanency hearings pursuant to 33 V.S.A. § 5321</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-38_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>unless a contested permanency hearing becomes necessary; and to provide case management of juvenile proceedings; the Master shall not have the authority to hear temporary care hearings, requests for juvenile protective orders, or hearings on the merits or to conduct disposition hearings.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-38_subsec-g_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In the Family Division of the Superior Court, proceedings, with the approval of the presiding judge, to ensure compliance with existing court orders relating to parent-child contact; to act as a Master pursuant to Rule 53 of the Vermont Rules of Civil Procedure where no order has been made pursuant to 32 V.S.A. § 1758</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-38_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Judicial Master may be appointed to serve as an acting judge pursuant to subsection 22</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-38_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title in any matter in which he or she has not previously acted as a Judicial Master.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-38_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The decision of a Judicial Master under this section shall have the same effect as a decision of a Superior judge, except when acting as a Master pursuant to subdivision </akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-38_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-39"><akn:num>Section 39</akn:num><akn:heading>Capital budget requests; county courthouses</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-39_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>On or before October 1 each year, any county requesting capital funds for its courthouse, or court operations, shall submit a request to the Court Administrator.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-39_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Court Administrator shall evaluate requests based on the following criteria:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-39_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>whether the funding request relates to an emergency that will affect the court operations and the administration of justice;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-39_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>whether there is a State-owned courthouse in the county that could absorb court activities in lieu of this capital investment;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-39_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>whether the county consistently has invested in major maintenance in the courthouse;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-39_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>whether the request relates to a State-mandated function;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-39_subsec-b_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>whether the request diverts resources of other current Judiciary capital priorities;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-39_subsec-b_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>whether the request is consistent with the long-term capital needs of the Judiciary, including providing court services adapted to modern needs and requirements; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-39_subsec-b_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>any other criteria as deemed appropriate by the Court Administrator.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-39_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Based on the criteria described in subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-39_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, the Court Administrator shall make a recommendation to the Commissioner of Buildings and General Services regarding whether the county’s request should be included as part of the Judiciary’s request for capital funding in the Governor’s annual proposed capital budget request.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-39_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>On or before January 15 of each year, the Court Administrator shall advise the House Committee on Corrections and Institutions and the Senate Committee on Institutions of all county requests received and the Court Administrator’s recommendations for the proposed capital budget request.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-40"><akn:num>Section 40</akn:num><akn:heading>Report on temporary employees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-40_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the total number of individuals employed by the Judiciary Department on a temporary basis who have worked in excess of 1,280 hours in the prior calendar year, excluding employees identified in 3 V.S.A. § 1011</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-40_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the total number of temporary positions in which one or more individuals have been employed for a combined total of more than 1,280 hours, excluding positions filled by employees identified in 3 V.S.A. § 1011</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-40_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the total number of hours worked by each temporary employee identified pursuant to subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-40_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-40_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the total number of years during which each temporary employee identified pursuant to subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-1_section-40_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section has worked for the Judiciary Department.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-3"><akn:num>Chapter 3</akn:num><akn:heading>Superior Judges and Superior Courts</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-71"><akn:num>Section 71</akn:num><akn:heading>Appointment and term of Superior judges</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-71_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There shall be 34 Superior judges, whose term of office shall, except in the case of an appointment to fill a vacancy or unexpired term, begin on April 1 in the year of their appointment or retention and continue for six years.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-71_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A Superior judge may file in the Office of the Secretary of State, on or before September 1 of the year preceding the expiration of the term for which the Superior judge was appointed or retained, a declaration that the Superior judge will be a candidate for retention. However, a Superior judge appointed and having taken the oath of office after September 1 of the year preceding the expiration of the term of office shall automatically be a candidate for retention without filing notice. When a judge files such a declaration, the judge’s name shall be submitted to the General Assembly for a vote on retention. The General Assembly shall vote upon one ballot on the question “Shall the following Superior judges be retained in office?” The names of the judges shall be listed followed by “Yes  _______________  No  _______________  .” If a majority of those voting on the question vote against retention, upon expiration of the term of office, a vacancy shall exist that shall be filled by appointment in accordance with the Constitution and chapter 15 of this title; if the majority vote is in favor of retention, the judge shall, unless removed for cause, remain in office for another term and, at its end, shall be eligible for retention in office in the manner prescribed pursuant to this subsection.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-71_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Court Administrator shall notify the Secretary of State whenever a Superior judge is appointed and takes the oath of office after September 1 of the year preceding the expiration of the term of office to which the judge has succeeded, thereby resulting in automatic notification of an intention to continue in office. Whenever a Superior judge files a declaration under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-71_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section or notification occurs automatically, the Secretary of State shall notify the President of the Senate, the Speaker of the House, the Office of Legislative Counsel, and the Office of Legislative Operations forthwith.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-71_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A Superior judge shall remain in office until a successor is appointed and qualified, unless sooner removed for cause or unless he or she resigns.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-71_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Supreme Court shall designate one of the Superior judges to serve as Chief Superior Judge. The Chief Superior Judge shall serve at the pleasure of the Supreme Court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-72"><akn:num>Section 72</akn:num><akn:heading>Disqualification</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A Superior judge shall not be an officer in a railroad, banking, or insurance corporation in this State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-73"><akn:num>Section 73</akn:num><akn:heading>Assignment</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-73_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In accordance with the direction of the Supreme Court, the Chief Superior Judge shall assign the Superior judges among the units and divisions of the Superior Court. The Chief Superior Judge shall assign a presiding judge to each unit and may assign a judge to preside in more than one unit. In a case where a Superior judge is disqualified or unable to attend any term of court or part thereof to which the Superior Judge has been assigned, the Chief Superior Judge may assign another Superior judge to act as judge at that term or part thereof for that period during which the assigned judge is disqualified or unable to attend. If during a term of the Superior Court the court in a unit is unable to complete all or part of the work before it in a reasonable time, the Chief Superior Judge, with the approval of the Supreme Court, may modify judge assignments to reduce delays in that unit. The court shall publish the judicial rotation schedule in electronic format and distribute it electronically to attorneys licensed in Vermont.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-73_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Pursuant to section 21a of this title, the Chief Superior Judge shall assign Superior judges to hear and determine Family Court matters. The Chief Superior Judge shall ensure that such hearings are held promptly. Any contested divorce case that has been pending for more than one year shall be advanced for prompt hearing upon the request of any party.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-73_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>As necessary to ensure the efficient operation of the Superior Court, the presiding judge of the unit may specially assign a Superior judge assigned to a division in the unit, including the presiding judge, to preside over one or more cases in a different division. As the Chief Superior Judge determines necessary for the operation of the Superior Court throughout the State, and with the approval of the Supreme Court, the Chief Superior Judge may additionally assign for a specified period of time a Superior judge to preside over a particular type of case, or over a particular type of motion or other judicial proceeding, in all or part of the units in the State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-75"><akn:num>Section 75</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers of Justice or Superior judge after expiration of term or vacation of office</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Whenever the term of office of a Justice, Superior judge, Environmental judge, magistrate, or hearing officer expires or he or she otherwise vacates the office, the Justice, judge, magistrate, or hearing officer shall have the same authority to conclude causes he or she has partly or fully heard that he or she would have had if remaining in that office.  The Justice, judge, magistrate, or hearing officer may make and sign findings and orders for judgments or decrees in causes pending before him or her, may make interlocutory orders and decrees, and shall be paid compensation commensurate with that paid specially assigned judicial officers as provided by section 23 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-111"><akn:num>Section 111</akn:num><akn:heading>Superior court sessions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-111_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When the business of a Superior Court cannot otherwise be disposed of with reasonable dispatch, by direction of the Chief Superior Judge, there may be held additional sessions of that Superior Court simultaneously with the regular session consisting of a presiding judge and one or more assistant judges, if available.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-111_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A Superior Court may be temporarily recessed or adjourned from the place designated for holding a regular term or session to another place having adequate facilities when the regular facilities at the designated courthouse are not adequate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-111_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Chief Superior Judge may assign assistant judges, with their consent, to a special assignment in a court where they have jurisdiction in another county when assistant judges of that county are unavailable or the business of the courts so requires.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-115"><akn:num>Section 115</akn:num><akn:heading>Stated terms of Superior Court</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-3_section-115_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title, a judge who at the end of a term is no longer assigned to a unit shall have no further responsibility for cases in that unit.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-5"><akn:num>Chapter 5</akn:num><akn:heading>Court of Chancery</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-5_section-219"><akn:num>Section 219</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers of chancellor</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The powers and jurisdiction of the courts that were previously vested in the courts of chancery are vested in the Superior Court. Superior, Environmental, and Probate judges have the powers of a chancellor in passing upon all civil matters that may come before them.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-7"><akn:num>Chapter 7</akn:num><akn:heading>Probate Courts</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-272"><akn:num>Section 272</akn:num><akn:heading>Probate districts; Probate judges</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-272_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There shall be one Probate district in each county, which shall be designated by the name of the county. Each Probate district shall elect one Probate judge.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-272_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>To hold the position of Probate judge, a person shall be admitted by the Supreme Court to practice law. This subsection shall not apply to any person who holds the office of Probate judge on July 1, 2010.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-272_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Chief Superior Judge may specially assign a Probate judge to hear a case in a geographical district other than the district for which the Probate judge was elected.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-278"><akn:num>Section 278</akn:num><akn:heading>Authorization of assistant judges</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-278_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An assistant judge or a candidate for the office of assistant judge may also seek election to the office of Probate judge and if otherwise qualified and elected to both offices, may serve both as an assistant judge and as Probate judge.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-278_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In the event a probate matter arises in the Superior Court over which an assistant judge is also the Probate judge who presides, or has presided, over the same or related probate matter in the Probate Court, the assistant judge shall be disqualified from hearing and deciding the probate matter in the Superior Court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-278_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In the event a probate matter arises in the Probate Court over which a Probate judge is also an assistant judge who presides, or has presided, over the same or related probate matter in the Superior Court, the Probate judge shall be disqualified from hearing and deciding the probate matter in the Probate Court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-311a"><akn:num>Section 311a</akn:num><akn:heading>Venue generally</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-311a_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>in the district where the petitioner resides; or
(ii) if a decedent’s estate, a guardian or person under guardianship, or trust governed by Title 14 is the subject of the proceeding, in any district where venue lies for a proceeding thereon.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-311a_subsec-i_subsec-27"><akn:num>(27)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-311a_subsec-i_subsec-28"><akn:num>(28)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Appointment of a trustee for a person confined under a sentence of imprisonment: in the district or unit in which the person resided at the time of sentence or in the district or unit in which the sentence was imposed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-311a_subsec-i_subsec-29"><akn:num>(29)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Proceedings concerning 18 V.S.A. chapter 231: in the district where the principal resides or in the district where the principal is a patient admitted to a health care facility.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-311a_subsec-i_subsec-30"><akn:num>(30)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Proceedings under 18 V.S.A. chapter 107, subchapter 3: in the district where the decedent resided at the time of death or where the remains are currently located.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-312"><akn:num>Section 312</akn:num><akn:heading>Resident’s estate; settlement</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>If an inhabitant of this State dies, his or her will shall be proved, or letters of administration granted and his or her estate settled in the Probate Court of the district in which he or she resided at the time of his or her death.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-313"><akn:num>Section 313</akn:num><akn:heading>Nonresident’s estate; settlement</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>If a person resided out of the State at the time of his or her death, his or her will shall be allowed and recorded, and letters testamentary or of administration shall be granted in the Probate Court of any district in which he or she had estate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-354"><akn:num>Section 354</akn:num><akn:heading>Disqualification of judge or register; penalty</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A judge or register shall not act as guardian, executor, administrator, trustee, or in any other fiduciary capacity or as attorney in any probate matter pending in any court in the State while holding either office. A judge or register who violates a provision of this section shall be imprisoned not more than six months or fined not more than $500.00, or both.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-355"><akn:num>Section 355</akn:num><akn:heading>Disqualification or disability of judge</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When a Probate judge is incapacitated for the duties of office by absence, removal from the district, resignation, sickness, death, or otherwise or if the judge or the judge’s spouse or child is heir or legatee under a will filed in the judge’s district, or if the judge is executor or administrator of the estate of a deceased person in his or her district, or is interested as a creditor or otherwise in a question to be decided by the court, he or she shall not act as judge. The judge’s duties shall be performed by a Superior judge assigned by the presiding judge of the unit.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-356"><akn:num>Section 356</akn:num><akn:heading>Authority of judge after end of term</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-356_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A Probate judge whose term of office has expired, or who has vacated such office, shall have authority to act in the capacity of Probate judge to conclude causes and proceedings partly or fully heard before the judge as Probate judge as fully and effectively as he or she could if he or she remained in such office. He or she may make, sign, and enter findings, decisions, orders, and decrees in causes or proceedings so pending before him or her as Probate judge, and all such acts so performed by the judge shall have as full force and effect as they would have had if he or she had remained in office.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-356_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The jurisdiction conferred by subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-356_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section shall not be exercised if the presiding judge of the unit determines that the successor to the Probate judge will assume jurisdiction for all or part of the cases.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-356_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A Probate judge who exercises the jurisdiction conferred by subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-356_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section shall receive compensation at a rate fixed by the Court Administrator.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-357"><akn:num>Section 357</akn:num><akn:heading>Registers of Probate</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Superior Court clerk or court operations manager, in consultation with the Probate judge, and following the approval of the Court Administrator, shall hire a register of probate for each unit. The Probate judge may request that the Court Administrator designate one or more staff persons as additional registers.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-362"><akn:num>Section 362</akn:num><akn:heading>Oaths</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A Probate judge or register may administer oaths.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-363"><akn:num>Section 363</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-363_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A Probate judge may issue warrants, subpoenas, and processes in conformity with the law necessary to compel the attendance of witnesses or to produce books, papers, documents, or tangible things, or to carry into effect the orders, sentences, or decrees of the Probate Court or the powers granted it by law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-363_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A Probate judge may appoint not more than three masters to report on a particular issue or to do or perform particular acts or to receive and report evidence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-364"><akn:num>Section 364</akn:num><akn:heading>Commitment to enforce orders</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>If a person does not comply with an order, sentence, or decree of the Probate Division of the Superior Court in a proceeding formerly within the jurisdiction of the Probate Court, the court may issue a warrant committing the person to the custody of the Commissioner of Corrections until compliance is given.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-369"><akn:num>Section 369</akn:num><akn:heading>Nonresident’s estate; notice to Commissioner of Taxes; information to banks</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-369_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When an executor or administrator is appointed to administer within this State an estate of a deceased person who resided in another state or country at the time of his or her death, the judge who issued the appointment shall forthwith notify the Commissioner of Taxes in writing of the appointment, giving the name and residence of the deceased person at the time of his or her death, the name and residence of the executor or administrator, the date of his or her appointment, and the court making the appointment.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-7_section-369_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commissioner shall keep a full record in each case and upon inquiry made of him or her by any savings bank or savings institution in the State shall at once notify the bank or institution whether, as shown by his or her record, an executor or administrator has been appointed by any court in the State to administer the estate of the deceased person named in the inquiry. If there has been such an appointment, the Commissioner shall furnish the information required by this subsection to the bank or institution forthwith.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-9"><akn:num>Chapter 9</akn:num><akn:heading>District Court</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-10"><akn:num>Chapter 10</akn:num><akn:heading>Family Court</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-455"><akn:num>Section 455</akn:num><akn:heading>Transfer of Probate proceedings</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-455_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any guardianship action filed in the Probate Division of the Superior Court pursuant to 14 V.S.A. chapter 111, subchapter 2, article 1 and any adoption action filed in the Probate Division pursuant to Title 15A may be transferred to the Family Division of the Superior Court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-455_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In an adoption action filed in the Probate Division pursuant to Title 15A, the Family Division shall order the transfer of the proceeding on motion of a party or on its own motion if it finds that the identity of the parties, issues, and evidence are so similar in nature to the parties, issues, and evidence in a proceeding pending in the Family Division that transfer of the probate action to the Family Division would expedite resolution of the issues or would best serve the interests of justice.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-457"><akn:num>Section 457</akn:num><akn:heading>Participation and availability of assistant judges</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-457_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Application.   This section shall apply in all proceedings in which the Family Court consists of one presiding judge and two assistant judges.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-457_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Questions of law and fact.   In all proceedings, questions of law shall be decided by the presiding judge. Mixed questions of law and fact shall be deemed to be questions of law. The presiding judge alone shall decide which are questions of law, questions of fact, and mixed questions of law and fact. Written or oral stipulations of fact submitted by the parties shall establish the facts in the submitted stipulation, except that the presiding judge, in the presiding judge’s discretion, may order a hearing on any stipulated fact. Neither the decision of the presiding judge under this subsection nor participation by an assistant judge in a ruling of law shall be grounds for reversal unless a party makes a timely objection and raises the issue on appeal.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-457_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Availability of assistant judges.   If two assistant judges are not available, the court shall consist of one presiding judge and one assistant judge.  If neither assistant judge is available, the court shall consist of the presiding judge alone, and the unavailability of an assistant judge shall not constitute reversible error.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-457_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Mistrial.   In the event that court is being held by the presiding judge and one assistant judge, and they do not agree on a decision, a mistrial shall be declared.  If the case is retried, the court shall consist of the presiding judge alone or the presiding judge and two assistant judges.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-457_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Method of determining availability.   Before commencing a hearing in any matter in which the court by law may consist of the presiding judge and assistant judges, the assistant judges shall determine whether they are available for the case.  A schedule of proceedings in Family Court in which the assistant judges by law may participate shall be made available sufficiently in advance to give assistant judges reasonable opportunity to determine in which cases they will participate.  If two or more cases are being heard at one time, and assistant judges may by law participate in either, each assistant judge may determine in which case he or she will participate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-457_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Duty to complete hearing or trial.   After an assistant judge has decided to participate in a hearing or trial, the assistant judge shall not withdraw from the hearing or trial except for cause. However, if an assistant judge is not available for a scheduled hearing or trial or becomes unavailable during trial, the matter may continue without that assistant judge’s participation, and the assistant judge may not return to participate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-457_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Emergency relief.   A presiding judge may hear a petition for emergency relief when the court is not sitting and may issue temporary orders as necessary.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-458"><akn:num>Section 458</akn:num><akn:heading>Venue</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The place of trial in the Family Division of the Superior Court shall be in the county in which one of the parties resides if one party resides within the State.  If no party resides within the State, the place of trial may be in any county.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-459"><akn:num>Section 459</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers of assistant judges</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Nothing in this chapter shall be construed to restrict the constitutional powers of assistant judges.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461"><akn:num>Section 461</akn:num><akn:heading>Office of magistrate; jurisdiction; selection; term</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The office of magistrate is created within the Family Division of the Superior Court. Except as provided in section 463 of this title, the office of magistrate shall have nonexclusive jurisdiction to hear and dispose of the following cases and proceedings:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Proceedings for the establishment, modification, and enforcement of child support, including contempt proceedings instituted against an obligated party for the limited purpose of enforcing a child support order.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Cases arising under the Uniform Interstate Family Support Act.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Child support in parentage cases after parentage has been determined.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Cases arising under 33 V.S.A. § 5116, when delegated by a presiding judge of the Superior Court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Proceedings to establish, modify, or enforce temporary orders for spousal maintenance in accordance with 15 V.S.A. §§ 594a and 752.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-a_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Proceedings to modify or enforce temporary or final parent-child contact orders issued pursuant to this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-a_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Proceedings to establish parentage.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-a_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Proceedings to establish temporary parental rights and responsibilities and parent-child contact.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A magistrate shall be an attorney admitted to practice in Vermont with at least four years of general law practice. Magistrates shall be nominated, appointed, and confirmed in the manner of Superior judges.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Terms of office of magistrates, except in the case of an appointment to fill a vacancy or unexpired term, shall be for a term of six years from and including April 1 in the year of the magistrate’s appointment or retention. A magistrate shall remain in office until a successor is appointed and qualified, unless sooner removed for cause or unless he or she resigns.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A magistrate may file in the office of the Secretary of State, on or before September 1 of the year preceding the expiration of the term for which the magistrate was appointed or retained, a declaration that the magistrate will be a candidate to succeed themself. However, a magistrate appointed and having taken the oath of office after September 1 of the year preceding the expiration of the term of office shall automatically be a candidate for retention without filing notice. When a magistrate files such a declaration, the magistrate’s name shall be submitted to the General Assembly for a vote on retention. The General Assembly shall vote upon one ballot on the question: “Shall the following magistrates be retained in office?” The names of the magistrates shall be listed followed by “Yes____ No____.” If a majority of those voting on the question vote against retaining a magistrate in office, upon the expiration of the term, a vacancy shall exist that shall be filled in accordance with the Constitution and chapter 15 of this title. If the majority vote is in favor of retention, the magistrate shall, unless removed for cause, remain in office for another term and, at its end, shall be eligible for retention in office in the manner prescribed pursuant to this subdivision.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Court Administrator shall notify the Secretary of State whenever a magistrate is appointed and takes the oath of office after September 1 of the year preceding the expiration of the term of office to which the magistrate has succeeded, thereby resulting in automatic notification of an intention to continue in office. Whenever a magistrate files a declaration under subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection or when notification occurs automatically, the Secretary of State shall notify the President of the Senate, the Speaker of the House, the Office of Legislative Counsel, and the Office of Legislative Operations forthwith.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Magistrates shall be exempt employees of the Judicial Branch, subject to the Code of Judicial Conduct, and, except as provided in section 26 of this title, shall devote full time to their duties. The Supreme Court shall prescribe training requirements for magistrates.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A magistrate shall have received training on the subject of parent-child contact before being assigned to hear and determine motions filed pursuant to subdivision </akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-e_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461a"><akn:num>Section 461a</akn:num><akn:heading>Essex County; powers of assistant judges and magistrates in Family Court proceedings</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461a_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notwithstanding any other provision of law to the contrary, an assistant judge of Essex County who has satisfactorily completed the training provided by the Vermont Supreme Court pursuant to Sec. 20 of Act No. 221 of the 1990 (Adj. Sess.), or a similar course of training that has been approved by the Supreme Court, shall act as a magistrate and hear and dispose of proceedings for the establishment, modification, and enforcement of child support and establishment of parentage in all cases filed or pending in the Family Division of the Superior Court in Essex County.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461a_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Chief Superior Judge may appoint and may specially assign a magistrate to serve as the presiding judge in the Family Division of the Superior Court in Essex County.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461a_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>No Vermont Family Court action filed or pending in Essex County, except for temporary abuse prevention proceedings and juvenile proceedings under Title 33, shall be heard at or transferred to the Family Division in another unit of the Superior Court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461c"><akn:num>Section 461c</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers of assistant judges in divorce proceedings</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461c_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notwithstanding any other provision of law to the contrary, an assistant judge may elect to hear and determine a complaint or action that seeks a divorce, legal separation, or civil union dissolution in cases where a final stipulation of the parties has been filed with the court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461c_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When an assistant judge elects to hear such cases, the clerk shall set it for hearing before the assistant judge if available.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-461c_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Prior to hearing an uncontested domestic matter, an assistant judge shall sit with a Superior judge on domestic proceedings for a minimum of 100 hours, satisfactorily complete a minimum of 30 hours of training on subjects relevant to domestic proceedings and the Code of Judicial Conduct, and conduct a minimum of three uncontested domestic hearings with a Superior judge who shall, in the Superior judge’s sole discretion, certify to the Chief Superior Judge that the assistant judge is qualified to preside over matters under this section. Upon application of an assistant judge, some or all of these requirements may be waived by the Chief Superior Judge based on equivalent experience. The requirements set forth in this subsection shall only apply to assistant judges who elect to conduct uncontested final hearings in domestic cases after July 1, 2010. An assistant judge already conducting hearings under this section as of July 1, 2010 shall be deemed to have complied with these requirements.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-462"><akn:num>Section 462</akn:num><akn:heading>Findings; orders; stipulations</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-462_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The magistrate shall make findings of fact, conclusions, and a decision and shall issue an order. An order issued by a magistrate may be enforced by the Family Division of the Superior Court in the unit in which the magistrate hearing was held.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-462_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A magistrate may issue an order based on a stipulation regarding any preliminary matter necessary to issue a child support order.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-462_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If the stipulation of the parties regarding child support includes matters other than preliminary matters necessary to issue a child support order, the stipulation may be accepted and approved by the magistrate in respect to those preliminary matters and signed by the magistrate as an order of the Family Division of the Superior Court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-462_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A magistrate shall issue an order for child support based upon the actual physical living arrangements of the children during the prior three months if the parties have not stipulated concerning parental rights and responsibilities. If parental rights and responsibilities are contested, the Family Division of the Superior Court shall make an order allocating parental rights and responsibilities.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-463"><akn:num>Section 463</akn:num><akn:heading>Jurisdiction of Family Division of Superior Court over child support</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-463_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The support matter is so intrinsically tied to an action that must be heard by a judge that hearing before a magistrate would unduly delay the proceedings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-463_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The identity of the parties, issues, and evidence are so similar in nature that consolidation with an already scheduled matter would in fact expedite resolution of the support issue.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-463_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A material legal issue must be resolved for which there is no legal precedent.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-463_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Such good and substantial cause as the court may find, consistent with the principle that support cases shall be heard in a timely manner.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-464"><akn:num>Section 464</akn:num><akn:heading>Representation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-464_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any person or other legal entity, including the State, shall be entitled but not required to be represented by an attorney before a magistrate. Nonattorney employees of the Office of Child Support who have been duly qualified by the Office of Child Support may sign complaints and motions and may participate in child support hearings before a magistrate, including those arising under 33 V.S.A. § 5116 subject to the conditions in subsections</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-464_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-464_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section. This participation shall not be considered the unauthorized practice of law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-464_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Participation in a proceeding shall consist of:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-464_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>presentation of current and material evidence relative to both parents’ income and resources;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-464_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>computation of parental support obligations based upon child support guidelines, and recommendations for any deviations from that amount after consideration of the best interests of the child;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-464_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>relevant supporting documentation and legal justification for the recommendation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-464_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A current roster of qualified Office of Child Support staff shall be furnished to the court by the Office of Child Support. Such staff may be denied the right to participate in child support proceedings upon notice to the Office of Child Support from the Court Administrator. The notice shall indicate the basis for the decision.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-465"><akn:num>Section 465</akn:num><akn:heading>Appeals</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>An appeal from a decision of a magistrate shall be on the record to the Family Division of the Superior Court.  At the request of a party, the Family Court shall hear additional evidence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-466"><akn:num>Section 466</akn:num><akn:heading>Procedure</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-466_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A proceeding before a magistrate shall, in cases involving child support, be initiated by the filing of a petition.  If a proceeding for divorce, annulment, or separation has been commenced before the Family Division of the Superior Court, the magistrate shall have jurisdiction to determine a temporary amount of child support on the basis of the complaint or petition filed in the Family Division of the Superior Court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-466_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A magistrate hearing shall be conducted according to rules adopted by the Supreme Court, subject to review by the Judicial Rules Committee.  The rules shall include postjudgment procedures and deadlines for the establishment of support orders which comply with the requirements of federal law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-466_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Vermont Rules of Evidence shall apply to magistrate proceedings, except that evidence not admissible under those Rules may be admitted if it is of a type commonly relied upon by reasonably prudent persons in the conduct of their affairs and is not precluded by statute or privilege.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-466_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Witnesses shall be sworn.  Hearings shall be electronically recorded.  The magistrate shall assist the parties in developing relevant and reliable evidence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-466_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Family Division of the Superior Court clerk shall provide for personal service or shall mail to the respondent, at one or more of the addresses supplied by the respondent, by certified mail, return receipt requested and delivery restricted to the addressee, the expense being paid by the petitioner, a notice signed by the clerk.  If acceptance of service is refused, the clerk may serve the notice on the respondent by sending it to the respondent by ordinary first-class mail and by certifying that such service has been made. In the alternative, the clerk may provide for mail service as provided in Rule  4</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-466_subsec-l"><akn:num>(l)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of the Vermont Rules of Civil Procedure.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-466_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When an obligor is referred to an employment services program, the magistrate may require the program to file periodic written reports with the court regarding the obligor’s progress and cooperation with the program requirements. Such reports shall be admissible in an enforcement or contempt proceeding without the appearance of a witness from the program unless there is a dispute with respect to the authenticity of the report or the obligor disputes the facts set forth in the report concerning the obligor’s performance and the facts in dispute are relevant to the determination of the issues before the court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-467"><akn:num>Section 467</akn:num><akn:heading>Forms; Office of Child Support; IV-D services</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-467_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Court Administrator shall prepare and make available to the public forms for proceeding before a magistrate, including forms for the filing of an action, responding to a petition and filing motions.  The purpose of the standardized forms is to make the magistrate hearing accessible to all parties in a dispute without the assistance of counsel.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-467_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The form for filing a petition with the magistrate shall include provision for the petitioner to request IV-D services from the Office of Child Support established in 33 V.S.A. § 4101. If the petitioner requests IV-D services, the court shall immediately notify the Office of Child Support.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-467_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Court Administrator and the Office of Child Support shall jointly prepare and make available to the public a booklet describing the services available to both custodial and noncustodial parents and the judicial procedure applicable to child support and parentage cases.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-10_section-467_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Court Administrator and the Office of Child Support shall prepare a standardized child support order.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-11"><akn:num>Chapter 11</akn:num><akn:heading>Justices of the Peace</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-11_section-491"><akn:num>Section 491</akn:num><akn:heading>Qualification of justice of the peace—Filing of oath and certificate</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Before entering upon his or her duties, each justice shall deposit with the town clerk a copy of his or her official oath, signed by himself or herself, with a certificate of the magistrate or notary public administering the same.  The Secretary of State shall provide oath forms for this purpose. The term of office of justices of the peace shall be two years, and shall commence on the first day of February next after their election.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-11_section-492"><akn:num>Section 492</akn:num><akn:heading>Penalty</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When a justice willfully neglects to make such deposit with the town clerk, he or she may be fined not more than $100.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-11_section-500"><akn:num>Section 500</akn:num><akn:heading>Expiration of term of office; certified copies of records</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>After the expiration of his or her term of office and while residing in the same county, a justice may make and certify copies of the records of his or her official business.  Such copies shall have the same validity as though made and certified while he or she was in office.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-13"><akn:num>Chapter 13</akn:num><akn:heading>Judicial Council</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-15"><akn:num>Chapter 15</akn:num><akn:heading>Judicial Nominations and Appointments</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601"><akn:num>Section 601</akn:num><akn:heading>Judicial Nominating Board created; composition</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Judicial Nominating Board is created for the nomination of Supreme Court Justices, Superior judges, magistrates, and the Chair and members of the Public Utility Commission.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Board shall consist of 11 members who shall be selected as follows:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Governor shall appoint two members who are not attorneys at law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Senate shall elect three of its members, not all of whom shall be members of the same party, and only one of whom may be an attorney at law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The House shall elect three of its members, not all of whom shall be members of the same party, and only one of whom may be an attorney at law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Attorneys at law admitted to practice before the Supreme Court of Vermont, and residing in the State, shall elect three of their number as members of the Board. The Supreme Court shall regulate the manner of their nomination and election.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-b_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The members of the Board shall serve for terms of two years. All appointments or elections shall be between January 1 and February 1 of each odd-numbered year, except to fill a vacancy. A House vacancy that occurs when the General Assembly is adjourned shall be filled by the Speaker of the House and a Senate vacancy that occurs when the General Assembly is adjourned shall be filled by the Senate Committee on Committees. Members shall serve until their successors are elected or appointed. Members shall serve no more than three consecutive terms in any capacity.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-b_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The members shall elect their own chair, who will serve for a term of two years.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Legislative members of the Board shall be entitled to per diem compensation and reimbursement for expenses in accordance with 2 V.S.A. § 23. Members of the Board who are not otherwise compensated by their employer shall be entitled to per diem compensation and reimbursement for expenses in the same manner as board members are compensated under 32 V.S.A. § 1010. All compensation and reimbursement shall be paid from the legislative appropriation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Judicial Nominating Board shall adopt rules under 3 V.S.A. chapter 25 that shall establish criteria and standards for the nomination of candidates for Justices of the Supreme Court, Superior judges, magistrates, and the Chair and members of the Public Utility Commission based on the attributes identified in subsection 602</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title. The application form shall not be included in the rules and may be developed and periodically revised at the discretion of the Board.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A quorum of the Board shall consist of eight members.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Board is authorized to use the staff and services of appropriate State agencies and departments as necessary to conduct investigations of applicants. The Office of Legislative Counsel shall assist the Board for the purpose of rulemaking.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Except as provided in subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-h"><akn:num>(h)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, proceedings of the Board, including the names of candidates considered by the Board and information about any candidate submitted by the Court Administrator or by any other source, shall be confidential.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-h"><akn:num>(h)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The following shall be public:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-h_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>operating procedures of the Board;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-h_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>standard application forms and any other forms used by the Board, provided they do not contain personal information about a candidate or confidential proceedings;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-h_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>all proceedings of the Board prior to the Board’s receipt of the first candidate’s completed application; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-601_subsec-h_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>at the time the Board sends the names of the candidates to the Governor, the total number of applicants for the vacancy and the total number of candidates sent to the Governor.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602"><akn:num>Section 602</akn:num><akn:heading>Duties; Justices, judges, magistrates, and the Chair of the Public Utility Commission</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Prior to submitting to the Governor the names of candidates for Justices of the Supreme Court, Superior Court judges, magistrates, and the Chair of the Public Utility Commission, the Judicial Nominating Board shall submit to the Court Administrator a list of all candidates, and he or she shall disclose to the Board information solely about professional disciplinary action taken or pending concerning any candidate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>From the list of candidates, the Judicial Nominating Board shall select by majority vote, provided that a quorum is present, well-qualified candidates for the position to be filled.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Whenever a vacancy occurs in the office of a Supreme Court Justice, a Superior Court judge, magistrate, or Chair of the Public Utility Commission, or when an incumbent does not declare that he or she will be a candidate to succeed himself or herself, the Board shall submit to the Governor the names of as many persons as it deems well qualified to be appointed to the office.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A candidate for judge or Justice shall be a Vermont resident and an experienced lawyer who has practiced law in Vermont for a minimum of ten years, with at least five years immediately preceding his or her application to the Board. The Board may make exceptions to the five-year requirement for absences from practice for reasons including family, military, academic, or medical leave.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A candidate for magistrate shall be a Vermont resident and an experienced lawyer who has practiced law in Vermont for at least five years immediately preceding his or her application to the Board.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A candidate for Chair of the Public Utility Commission shall not be required to be an attorney; however if the candidate is admitted to practice law in Vermont, the Judicial Nominating Board shall submit the candidate’s name to the Court Administrator, and he or she shall disclose to the Board information solely about professional disciplinary action taken or pending concerning the candidate. If a candidate is not admitted to practice law in Vermont, but practices a profession requiring licensure, certification, or other professional regulation by the State, the Judicial Nominating Board shall submit the candidate’s name to the State professional regulatory entity and that entity shall disclose to the Board any professional disciplinary action taken or pending concerning the candidate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A candidate shall possess the following attributes:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Integrity.   A candidate shall possess a record and reputation for excellent character and integrity.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Legal knowledge and ability.   A candidate shall possess a high degree of knowledge of established legal principles and procedures and have demonstrated a high degree of ability to interpret and apply the law to specific factual situations.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-d_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Judicial temperament.   A candidate shall possess an appropriate judicial temperament.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-d_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Impartiality.   A candidate shall exhibit an ability to make judicial determinations in a manner free of bias.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-d_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Communication capability.   A candidate shall possess demonstrated oral and written capacities, with reasonable accommodations, required by the position.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-d_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Financial integrity.   A candidate shall possess demonstrated financial probity.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-d_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Work ethic.   A candidate shall demonstrate diligence.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-d_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Administrative capabilities.   A candidate shall demonstrate management and organizational skills or experience required by the position.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-d_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Courtroom experience.   For Superior Court, a candidate shall have sufficient trial or other comparable experience that ensures knowledge of the Vermont Rules of Evidence and courtroom procedure. For the Environmental Division of the Superior Court, a candidate shall have experience in environmental and zoning law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602_subsec-d_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Other.   A candidate shall possess other attributes the Board deems relevant as identified through its rules.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602a"><akn:num>Section 602a</akn:num><akn:heading>Duties; Public Utility Commission members</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602a_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In accordance with 30 V.S.A. § 3, whenever a vacancy occurs for a member position on the Public Utility Commission, the Governor shall submit at least five names of potential nominees to the Judicial Nominating Board for review. The Judicial Nominating Board shall submit to the Governor the names of candidates it deems well qualified. The Judicial Nominating Board shall submit to the Governor a summary of the qualifications and experience of each candidate whose name is submitted to the Governor, together with any further information relevant to the matter. Vacancies for the position of Chair of the Public Utility Commission shall follow the procedure set forth in section 602 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602a_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A candidate for the position of member of the Public Utility Commission shall not be required to be an attorney; however, if the candidate is admitted to practice law in Vermont, the Judicial Nominating Board shall submit the candidate’s name to the Court Administrator, and he or she shall disclose to the Board information solely about professional disciplinary action taken or pending concerning the candidate. If a candidate is not admitted to practice law in Vermont, but practices a profession requiring licensure, certification, or other professional regulation by the State, the Judicial Nominating Board shall submit the candidate’s name to the State professional regulatory entity and that entity shall disclose to the Board any professional disciplinary action taken or pending concerning the candidate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602a_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A candidate shall possess the attributes provided in subsection 602</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-602a_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-603"><akn:num>Section 603</akn:num><akn:heading>Appointment of Justices, judges, magistrates, Public Utility Commission Chair, and members</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Whenever the Governor appoints a Supreme Court Justice, a Superior Judge, a magistrate, the Chair of the Public Utility Commission, or a member of the Public Utility Commission, he or she shall select from the list of names of qualified persons submitted by the Judicial Nominating Board pursuant to law. The names of candidates submitted and not selected shall remain confidential.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-605"><akn:num>Section 605</akn:num><akn:heading>Political activity by judges prohibited</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Superior judges shall not make any contribution to or hold any office in a political party or organization or take part in any political campaign.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-607"><akn:num>Section 607</akn:num><akn:heading>Joint Committee on Judicial Retention; creation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-607_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There is created the Joint Committee on Judicial Retention composed of four members of the House of Representatives appointed by the Speaker of the House and four members of the Senate appointed by the Committee on Committees of the Senate.  The appointments shall be made, if practicable, within seven days of the convening of each biennial session of the General Assembly.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-607_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee shall endeavor to hold its organizational meeting within seven days of its appointment and shall elect a chair from among its membership and adopt rules of procedure consistent with the rules of the Senate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-607_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Committee may use the staff and services of the Office of Legislative Counsel and the Office of Legislative Operations to, in addition to other duties, obtain information on the performance of a judge or Justice by soliciting comments from members of the Vermont Bar and the public.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-608"><akn:num>Section 608</akn:num><akn:heading>Functions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-608_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Declarations submitted to the General Assembly by a Supreme Court Justice under subsection 4</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-608_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title, by a Superior Court judge under subsection 71</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-608_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title, or by a magistrate under subsection 461</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-608_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title shall be referred immediately to the Joint Committee on Judicial Retention.  The declarations shall be accompanied by a supporting statement by the judge, the Justice, or the magistrate seeking retention.  In the case of a Superior Court judge or magistrate, the declaration shall also be accompanied by information on the next succeeding rotation schedule for the judge seeking retention.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-608_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Joint Committee responsible for the recommendation of retention shall review the candidacies of those Justices, Superior judges, and magistrates desiring to succeed themselves.  In conducting its review, the Committee shall evaluate judicial performance, including such factors as integrity, judicial temperament, impartiality, health, diligence, legal knowledge and ability, and administrative and communicative skills.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-608_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For the purpose of receiving information and hearing testimony, the Joint Committee responsible for the recommendation of retention shall hold hearings that, if possible, shall not commence until the General Assembly is in session.  Information obtained under subsection 607</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-608_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title shall be confidential until the Committee commences its hearings under this subsection.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-608_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A judge, a Justice, or a magistrate seeking retention has the right to present oral or written testimony to the Committee relative to his or her retention, may be represented by counsel, and may present witnesses to testify in his or her behalf.  Copies of written comments received by the Committee shall be forwarded to the judge, the Justice, or the magistrate.  A judge, a Justice, or a magistrate seeking retention has the right to a reasonable time period to prepare and present to the Committee a response to any testimony or written complaint adverse to his or her retention and has the right to be present during any public hearing conducted by the Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-608_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>On or before the tenth Thursday after the convening of each biennial and adjourned session, the Committee shall report to the General Assembly its recommendation whether the candidates should continue in office, with any amplifying information that it may deem appropriate, in order that the General Assembly may discharge its obligation under Chapter II § 34 of the Constitution of the State of Vermont.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-608_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In the performance of its official functions, the Joint Committee on Judicial Retention may by a majority vote of its membership issue subpoenas to compel the attendance of witnesses to testify under oath and to produce documents.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-608_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The votes on retention under subsections 4</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-608_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title shall be conducted in one joint assembly of the General Assembly, except that in the event that the Joint Committee reports to the General Assembly that it is not able to make its recommendation on a particular Justice, judge, or magistrate under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-608_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section on or before the date set for such joint assembly, the vote on such individual or individuals shall be deferred to a subsequent joint assembly, and separate ballots shall be used despite any other statutory provisions relating to the votes on retention.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-609"><akn:num>Section 609</akn:num><akn:heading>Judicial retirement</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-609_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Justices of the Supreme Court and judges of all subordinate courts shall be required to retire at the end of the calendar year in which they attain 90 years of age.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-15_section-609_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>This section shall not limit the Supreme Court’s power to establish procedures for taking appropriate action to remove or suspend or restrict the services of an individual Justice or judge of any age.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-17"><akn:num>Chapter 17</akn:num><akn:heading>Clerks of Court; Court and Other Records and Accounts</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-651"><akn:num>Section 651</akn:num><akn:heading>Clerks of courts</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Court Administrator shall act as clerk of the Supreme Court as provided in section 8 of this title. The Court Administrator shall appoint a Superior Court clerk for each unit. The Court Administrator may appoint the same person to be clerk in more than one unit. With approval of the Court Administrator, the clerk shall hire office staff. The clerk shall have the powers and responsibilities formerly held by the clerk of the district court or the family court and may delegate specific powers and responsibilities to assigned staff. Unless so designated by the assistant judges of a specific county, with the approval of the Court Administrator, a Superior Court clerk shall not also serve as a county clerk.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-657"><akn:num>Section 657</akn:num><akn:heading>Transcribing damaged records</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When records in the Office of the Superior Court Clerk become faded, defaced, torn, or otherwise injured, so as to endanger the permanent legibility or proper preservation of the same, the Court Administrator may direct the court clerk to provide suitable books and transcribe such records into the books provided. At the end of a transcript of record so made, the clerk shall certify under official signature and the seal of the court that the same is a true transcript of the original record. Such transcript or a duly certified copy of the transcript shall be entitled to the same faith and credit and have the same force as the original record. The expense of making such transcript shall be paid by the State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-659"><akn:num>Section 659</akn:num><akn:heading>Preservation of court records</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-659_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Supreme Court by administrative order may provide for permanent preservation of all court records by any photographic or electronic or comparable process in accordance with standards that shall be no less protective of the records than the standards established by the Vermont State Archives and Records Administration programs that take into account the quality and security of the records and ready access to the record of any cause so recorded.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-659_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>After preservation in accordance with subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-659_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, the Supreme Court by administrative order may provide for the disposition of original court records by destruction or, in cases where the original court record may have historical or intrinsic value, by transfer to the archives of the Secretary of State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-691"><akn:num>Section 691</akn:num><akn:heading>Clerks and assistants; appointment; compensation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-691_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Superior Court clerk, with the approval of the Court Administrator, may hire and remove staff for the Superior Court subject to the terms of any applicable collective bargaining agreement. The clerks and staff shall be State employees and shall be entitled to all fringe benefits and compensation accorded classified State employees who are similarly situated, subject to any applicable statutory limits, unless covered by a collective bargaining agreement that sets forth the terms and conditions of employment negotiated pursuant to the provisions of 3 V.S.A. chapter 28.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-691_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A staff person for the Superior Court may also serve as the county clerk if the Court Administrator approves of such service with the concurrence of the assistant judges. If a Superior Court staff person serves as county clerk pursuant to this subsection, the Court Administrator and the assistant judges shall enter into a memorandum of understanding with respect to the duties, work schedule, and compensation of the person serving.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-691_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>With respect to counties where the assistant judges have elected to offer passport processing services, the Court Administrator and the assistant judges shall enter into a memorandum of understanding providing for the acceptance and processing of U.S. passport applications. The memorandum may provide for performance of passport acceptance and processing duties by the court clerk, county clerk, a Superior Court staff person serving as county clerk pursuant to subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-691_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, or any other court or county employee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-692"><akn:num>Section 692</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers of clerk in absence of judge</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-692_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the clerk may continue a cause;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-692_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the clerk may set conditions of release in noncapital criminal cases prior to trial as provided by law or by rule promulgated by the Supreme Court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-731"><akn:num>Section 731</akn:num><akn:heading>English language</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Writs, processes, complaints, informations, indictments, pleas, answers, and entries in the courts, except technical terms, shall be in the English language.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-732"><akn:num>Section 732</akn:num><akn:heading>Lost document or record</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When a court document, record, or file in an action pending in court is lost, mislaid, or destroyed, the court may order a duplicate document, record, or file to be filed under such conditions as the court prescribes. A duplicate document or record shall have the same validity and may be used in evidence in the same manner as the original document, record, or file.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-733"><akn:num>Section 733</akn:num><akn:heading>Preservation of attachment liens</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When real or personal estate is attached on such writ, the plaintiff may procure from the clerk of the town in which the estate was attached a certified copy of the writ, complaint and officer’s return thereon, and cause the same to be filed in such court.  The same proceedings shall thereupon be had, and the estate so attached held to respond to the judgment in the action, as though the original writ, complaint, and return were in court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-739"><akn:num>Section 739</akn:num><akn:heading>Record certified by successor in office</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When a recording officer has made a record but has omitted to make an official certificate thereof, any person subsequently holding the office may make such certificate.  Such certificate shall be as valid as if made by the officer who made the record, but shall not affect any intervening right.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-740"><akn:num>Section 740</akn:num><akn:heading>Court records; dockets; certified copies</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Supreme Court by administrative order or directive shall provide for the preparation, maintenance, recording, indexing, docketing, preservation, and storage of all court records and the provision, subject to confidentiality requirements of law or court rules, of certified copies of those records to persons requesting them.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-741"><akn:num>Section 741</akn:num><akn:heading>Payment by credit card</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-741_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-741_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If any such card draft is not paid by the bank or other company or is charged back to the court or bureau, any record of payment made by the court or bureau honoring the card shall be void. The obligation of the person to pay the court costs, fee, penalty, surcharge, or fine shall continue as an outstanding obligation as if no payment had been made.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-17_section-741_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Card account numbers, while in the possession of the court or bureau, are confidential.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-19"><akn:num>Chapter 19</akn:num><akn:heading>Stenographic Reporters</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-19_section-794"><akn:num>Section 794</akn:num><akn:heading>Oath; correctness of reports and copies</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Upon appointment, a stenographic reporter shall be sworn before entering upon his or her duties and shall be responsible for the correctness of his or her reports and certified copies thereof made by him or her or under his or her direction.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-19_section-795"><akn:num>Section 795</akn:num><akn:heading>Filing of copies of transcripts</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When directed by the presiding judge of a Superior Court so to do and within the time prescribed by such judge, such stenographic reporter shall file with the clerk thereof certified copies of the evidence and proceedings in a cause heard by it.  Such copies shall be verbatim transcripts of the evidence and proceedings and be a part of the files of such court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-19_section-796"><akn:num>Section 796</akn:num><akn:heading>Transcripts for quasi-judicial proceedings</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A stenographic reporter shall furnish a verbatim and certified transcript of the evidence and proceedings in every hearing before a commission, department, or other quasi-judicial proceeding reported by him or her to the presiding officer within 20 days after the termination of such hearing.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-19_section-798"><akn:num>Section 798</akn:num><akn:heading>Probative force of transcripts</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>All transcripts of evidence or proceedings in a cause or hearing tried in Superior Court or before an auditor, referee, or commissioner, ordered to be reported by a Probate or Superior judge, and made by or under the direction of the reporter and duly certified by him or her to be a verbatim transcript of the verbatim stenographic notes of such evidence or proceedings, shall be received as evidence in any action, civil or criminal, if relevant to the action.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-19_section-799"><akn:num>Section 799</akn:num><akn:heading>Probate Division reporters</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Upon request of a Probate judge, the Superior Court clerk shall appoint and assign a staff member to make a verbatim report of the proceeding in the Probate Division.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-19_section-801"><akn:num>Section 801</akn:num><akn:heading>Hearings before commissions and quasi-judicial tribunals</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>In hearings before a commission, department, or other quasi-judicial proceedings, such tribunal shall hire stenographic reporters for the purpose of making verbatim reports of the proceedings when one of the parties so requests in writing.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-19_section-802"><akn:num>Section 802</akn:num><akn:heading>Approval of accounts</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The presiding officer of a State department, commission, board, or other agency shall approve the accounts of the stenographer or reporter in the proceeding referred to in sections 797 and 801 of this title and shall forward the same to the Commissioner of Finance and Management for payment.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-19_section-803"><akn:num>Section 803</akn:num><akn:heading>Electronic recording equipment</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-19_section-803_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Subject to any rules prescribed by the Supreme Court pursuant to law, electronic sound or sound and video recording equipment may be used for the recording of any Superior Court or Judicial Bureau proceeding; testimony, objections, rulings, exceptions, arraignments, pleas, sentences, statements, and remarks made by any attorney or judge; oral instructions given by the judge; and any other judicial proceedings to the same extent as any recording by a stenographer or reporter permitted or required under existing statutes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-19_section-803_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For the purpose of operating recording equipment, the judge may appoint or designate the official reporter of that court, a special reporter, the clerk of the court, any staff of the court, the court officer, or any other designated court personnel. The person operating recording equipment shall subscribe to an oath that the operator will well and truly operate it to record all matters and proceedings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-19_section-803_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The court may then designate the person operating the equipment or any other competent person to read the recording and to transcribe it into typewriting.  The person transcribing the recording shall subscribe to an oath that it has truly and correctly been transcribed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-19_section-803_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The transcript may be used for all purposes for which transcripts are now received and accepted under existing statutes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-21"><akn:num>Chapter 21</akn:num><akn:heading>Commissioners in Other States and Foreign Countries</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-21_section-851"><akn:num>Section 851</akn:num><akn:heading>Appointment and powers of commissioners</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Governor may appoint commissioners in other states and in foreign countries who shall hold office for five years unless sooner removed by him or her. They may take depositions, affidavits, and testimony to be used in any proceedings in Superior Court; administer oaths; and take the acknowledgment of deeds and other instruments to be used or recorded in this State, and their acts in other states or foreign countries shall have the same force as though performed by a justice or master in this State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-21_section-852"><akn:num>Section 852</akn:num><akn:heading>Oath and bond</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Before entering upon his or her duties, each commissioner shall take and subscribe an oath of office before a magistrate of his or her locality and execute a bond to this State with sureties to the satisfaction of the Governor in the sum of $500.00, conditioned for the faithful performance of his or her duties.  The bond shall be kept in the office of the Secretary of State, and an action may be maintained against any or all signers thereof, in the name of the State, for the benefit of a person injured by the act or neglect of the commissioner.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-23"><akn:num>Chapter 23</akn:num><akn:heading>Attorneys</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-23_section-901"><akn:num>Section 901</akn:num><akn:heading>Rules for admission of attorneys</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Justices of the Supreme Court shall make, adopt, and publish and may alter or amend rules regulating the admission of attorneys to the practice of law before the courts of this State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-23_section-902"><akn:num>Section 902</akn:num><akn:heading>Board of Bar Examiners</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Board of Bar Examiners shall consist of 11 voting members whose term of office shall be for four years and until a successor is appointed. Two members of the Board shall be laypersons not admitted to practice law in this or any other state. The Supreme Court shall annually appoint not more than four members of the Board on October 1. Vacancies on the Board may be filled by the Court. The Commissioner of Finance and Management shall issue his or her warrant for the expenses of each member of the Board when approved by the Court Administrator.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-23_section-906"><akn:num>Section 906</akn:num><akn:heading>Conflicting appointments; excuse from attending by Chief Superior Judge</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When an attorney is required to attend more than one trial, hearing, or other proceeding before a court or commission having judicial or quasi-judicial functions, or both, at times that conflict so that the attorney cannot reasonably attend each appointment, the attorney may request the Chief Superior Judge to designate which appointment the attorney shall attend. The Chief Superior Judge shall designate the appointment the attorney shall attend and shall notify the presiding magistrate of each court and commission of the Justice’s or judge’s decision. The attorney shall be excused from attending at that time any proceedings other than the one designated by the Chief Superior Judge, and the other proceedings shall be rescheduled.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-23_section-907"><akn:num>Section 907</akn:num><akn:heading>Licensing and renewal fees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Supreme Court may by rule impose a fee on applicants for admission to the bar on motion and on applicants for admission to the bar by examination. The Court may also impose an annual fee on lawyers admitted to the bar of the Supreme Court as a condition of being licensed to practice law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-23_section-908"><akn:num>Section 908</akn:num><akn:heading>Attorneys’ Admission, Licensing, and Professional Responsibility Special Fund</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>There is established the Attorneys’ Admission, Licensing, and Professional Responsibility Special Fund that shall be managed in accordance with 32 V.S.A. chapter 7, subchapter 5. Fees collected for licensing of attorneys, administration of the bar examination, admitting attorneys to practice in Vermont, and administration of mandatory continuing legal education shall be deposited and credited to this Fund. This Fund shall be available to the Judicial Branch to offset the cost of operating the Professional Responsibility Board, the Board of Bar Examiners, the Judicial Conduct Board, the Committee on Character and Fitness, the mandatory continuing legal education program for attorneys and, at the discretion of the Supreme Court, to make grants for access to justice programs or to the Vermont Bar Foundation to be used to support legal services for the disadvantaged.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-25"><akn:num>Chapter 25</akn:num><akn:heading>Jury Commission</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-952"><akn:num>Section 952</akn:num><akn:heading>Rules of Court Administrator</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-952_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Court Administrator, subject to the approval of the Supreme Court, shall make rules regarding the qualifications, lists, and selection of all jurors and prepare questionnaires for prospective jurors. Each Superior Court clerk shall, in conformity with the rules, prepare a list of jurors from residents of its unit. The rules shall be designed to ensure that the list of jurors prepared by the Superior Court clerk shall be representative of the citizens of its unit in terms of age, sex, occupation, economic status, and geographical distribution.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-952_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Rules adopted under this section shall be consistent with the provisions of this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-953"><akn:num>Section 953</akn:num><akn:heading>Sources of names</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-953_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The clerk, in order to ascertain names of persons eligible as jurors, may consult the latest census enumeration; the latest published city, town, or village telephone or other directory; the listers’ records; the elections records; and any other general source of names.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-953_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notwithstanding any law to the contrary, the Court Administrator may obtain the names, addresses, and dates of birth of persons that are contained in the records of the Department of Motor Vehicles, the Department of Labor, the Department of Taxes, the Department of Health, and the Department for Children and Families. The Court Administrator may also obtain the names of voters from the Secretary of State. After the names have been obtained, the Court Administrator shall compile them and provide the names, addresses, and dates of birth to the clerk in a form that will not reveal the source of the names. The clerk shall include the names provided by the Court Administrator in the list of potential jurors.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-953_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There shall be continuous research for persons qualified and liable for jury service, in order to obtain as many prospective jurors as necessary and in order to limit as many prospective jurors as necessary and in order to limit as much as possible repetition of jury service.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-953_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>No person’s name shall be placed on venire to serve in any State court of the State of Vermont more than once in any two-year period.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-953_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All public officers shall, on request, furnish the clerk or the Court Administrator without charge any information it may require to enable it to select eligible persons, ascertain their qualifications, or determine the number needed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-954"><akn:num>Section 954</akn:num><akn:heading>Deposit of list</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Prior to the first day of July in each biennial year, the clerk shall prepare and file a current master list of jurors and certify its completion and filing to the Court Administrator. The current master lists shall contain the number of names necessary adequately to serve the needs of the courts involved for a two-year period beginning July 1.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-955"><akn:num>Section 955</akn:num><akn:heading>Questionnaire</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The clerk shall send a jury questionnaire prepared by the Court Administrator to each person selected. When returned, it shall be retained in the Office of the Superior Court Clerk. Pursuant to section 952 of this title, the Court Administrator shall promulgate rules governing the inspection and availability of the juror questionnaires and the information contained in them.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-956"><akn:num>Section 956</akn:num><akn:heading>Contents of list</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Names may be added or dropped from the jury list in accordance with rules issued by the Court Administrator under section 952 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-957"><akn:num>Section 957</akn:num><akn:heading>Drawing and summoning jurors</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The manner of drawing and summoning jurors from the lists provided shall be in accordance with the rules of the court in which they are called to serve and all applicable statutes, including section 952 of this title, requiring that the panel shall be representative of the citizens of the unit in terms of age, sex, occupation, economic status, and geographical distribution.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-958"><akn:num>Section 958</akn:num><akn:heading>Nonappearance; penalty</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A juror who does not appear after being summoned, and does not submit an excuse satisfactory to the court in which the juror was summoned to appear, shall be assessed a civil penalty by the presiding judge of not more than $200.00. The prospective juror may be excused from paying the assessment for good cause shown or in the interests of justice.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-959"><akn:num>Section 959</akn:num><akn:heading>Grand jurors; venire</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The clerk, as directed by the judges of each Superior Court, shall summon 18 judicious persons within the unit to appear at any stated or special term of that court to serve as grand jurors of the unit. The clerk of the court shall issue a venire accordingly.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-961"><akn:num>Section 961</akn:num><akn:heading>Failure to return form; misrepresentation; penalties</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-961_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any person who fails to return a completed questionnaire within 14 days of its receipt may be summoned by the Superior Court clerk to appear forthwith before the clerk to fill out a jury questionnaire. Any person so summoned who fails to appear as directed shall be ordered forthwith by the presiding judge to appear and show cause for his or her failure to comply with the summons. Any person who fails to appear pursuant to such order or who fails to show good cause for noncompliance may be found in contempt of court and shall be subject to the penalties for contempt.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-961_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any person who willfully misrepresents a material fact on the jury questionnaire form for the purpose of avoiding or securing service as a juror may be fined not more than $50.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-962"><akn:num>Section 962</akn:num><akn:heading>Qualifications; excuse from service</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-962_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A person shall be qualified for jury service if the person:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-962_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>is a citizen of the United States who has attained the age of majority;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-962_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>resides within the geographical jurisdiction of the court in which called to serve;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-962_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>is able to read, write, understand, and speak the English language;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-962_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>is capable, by reason of mental or physical condition, to render satisfactory jury service; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-962_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>has not served a term of imprisonment in this State after conviction of a felony.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-962_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>No person shall be automatically excused from jury service; however, the presiding judge may excuse a person for all or part of the two-year period upon individual request showing undue hardship on the prospective juror or the employer.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-25_section-963"><akn:num>Section 963</akn:num><akn:heading>Term of service</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A person summoned to petit jury service shall not appear before the court for jury selection more than three times in any two-year period of time and shall be required to appear at the courthouse to serve as a juror on the date of trial no more than three times in that two-year period.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-27"><akn:num>Chapter 27</akn:num><akn:heading>Environmental Court</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1001"><akn:num>Section 1001</akn:num><akn:heading>Environmental Division</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1001_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Environmental Division shall consist of two judges, each sitting alone.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1001_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Two Environmental judges shall be appointed to hear matters in the Environmental Division and to hear other matters in the Superior Court when so assigned by the Chief Superior Judge pursuant to subsection 21a</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1001_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1001_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An Environmental judge shall be an attorney admitted to practice before the Vermont Supreme Court. An Environmental judge shall be nominated, appointed, confirmed, paid, and retained and shall receive all benefits in the manner of a Superior judge.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1001_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An Environmental judge shall be appointed on April 1 for a term of six years or the unexpired portion thereof.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1001_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Evidentiary proceedings in the Environmental Division shall be held in the county in which all or a portion of the land that is the subject of the appeal is located or where the violation is alleged to have occurred, unless the parties agree to another location; provided, however, that the Environmental judge shall offer expeditious evidentiary hearings so that no such proceedings are moved to another county to obtain an earlier hearing. Unless otherwise ordered by the court, all nonevidentiary hearings may be conducted by telephone or video conferencing using an audio or video record. If a party objects to a telephone hearing, the court may require a personal appearance for good cause.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1001_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1001_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Supreme Court may enact rules and develop procedures consistent with this chapter to govern the operation of the Environmental Division and proceedings in it. In adopting these rules, the Supreme Court shall ensure that the rules provide for:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1001_subsec-g_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>expeditious proceedings that give due consideration to the needs of pro se litigants;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1001_subsec-g_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the ability of the judge to hold pretrial conferences by telephone;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1001_subsec-g_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the use of scheduling orders under the Vermont Rules of Civil Procedure in order to limit discovery to that which is necessary for a full and fair determination of the proceeding; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1001_subsec-g_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the appropriate use of site visits by the presiding judge to assist the court in rendering a decision.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1002"><akn:num>Section 1002</akn:num><akn:heading>Conduct of hearings</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Hearings before the Environmental Division shall be conducted in an impartial manner subject to rules of the Supreme Court providing for a summary, expedited proceeding.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1003"><akn:num>Section 1003</akn:num><akn:heading>Evidence</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1003_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Irrelevant, immaterial, or unduly repetitious evidence shall be excluded.  The Vermont Rules of Evidence shall be followed, except that evidence not admissible under the Rules of Evidence may be admitted if it is of a type commonly relied upon by reasonably prudent persons in the conduct of their affairs.  Objections to evidentiary offers may be made and shall be noted in the record.  Subject to these requirements, when a hearing will be expedited and the interests of the parties will not be prejudiced substantially, any part of the evidence may be received in written form.  Documentary evidence may be received in the form of copies or excerpts if the original is not readily available.  Upon request, parties shall be given an opportunity to compare the copy with the original.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1003_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notice may be taken of judicially cognizable facts.  In addition, notice may be taken of generally recognized technical or scientific facts within the agency’s specialized knowledge.  Parties shall be notified either before or during the hearing, or by reference in preliminary reports or otherwise, of the material noticed, including any staff memoranda or data, and they shall be afforded an opportunity to contest the material so noticed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1004"><akn:num>Section 1004</akn:num><akn:heading>Access to information</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1004_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In connection with any proceedings under 10 V.S.A. chapter 201, each party shall provide all other parties with all written statements and information in the possession, custody, or control of the party relative to the violation, including any technical studies, tests and reports, maps, architectural and engineering plans and specifications, drawings, graphs, charts, photographs, and other data compilations from which information can be obtained, the names and addresses of the party’s witnesses, and any other information that the Environmental Division deems necessary, in its sole discretion, to a fair and full determination of the proceeding.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-27_section-1004_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>No other discovery or depositions, written interrogatories, or requests to admit shall be permitted except that which is necessary for a full and fair determination of the proceeding.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-04_chapter-29"><akn:num>Chapter 29</akn:num><akn:heading>Judicial Bureau</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102"><akn:num>Section 1102</akn:num><akn:heading>Judicial Bureau; jurisdiction</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Judicial Bureau is created within the Judicial Branch under the supervision of the Supreme Court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Judicial Bureau shall have jurisdiction of the following matters:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Traffic violations alleged to have been committed on or after July 1, 1990.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Civil ordinance violations alleged to have been committed on or after July 1, 1994.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Minor fish and wildlife violations alleged to have been committed on or after September 1, 1996.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 7 V.S.A. § 1005</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 7 V.S.A. § 1007, relating to furnishing tobacco products to a person under 21 years of age.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 24 V.S.A. § 2201, relating to littering, burning of solid waste, and illegal dumping.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 16 V.S.A. chapter 9, subchapter 5, relating to hazing.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 20 V.S.A. §§ 2056a, 2056b, and 2056c, relating to unauthorized disclosure of criminal record information.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 7 V.S.A. § 656, relating to illegal possession of alcoholic beverages.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations under 7 V.S.A. § 658</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 18 V.S.A. § 4234b</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-12"><akn:num>(12)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 13 V.S.A. § 352(3), (4), and (9), relating to cruelty to animals, and 13 V.S.A. § 355</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-13"><akn:num>(13)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 18 V.S.A. § 4249, relating to the introduction of tobacco or tobacco products into a correctional facility.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-14"><akn:num>(14)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 21 V.S.A. chapter 5, subchapter 1, relating to conditions for employment.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-15"><akn:num>(15)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 9 V.S.A. § 3023</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-16"><akn:num>(16)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 18 V.S.A. chapter 38 that are subject to civil penalties pursuant to subsection 1760a</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-17"><akn:num>(17)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-18"><akn:num>(18)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 23 V.S.A. § 3327</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-19"><akn:num>(19)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-20"><akn:num>(20)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 21 V.S.A. § 692</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-21"><akn:num>(21)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of State or municipal rental housing health and safety laws when the amount of the cumulative penalties imposed pursuant to 18 V.S.A. § 603 is $800.00 or less.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-22"><akn:num>(22)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 10 V.S.A. § 1266b, relating to the application of fertilizer to nonagricultural turf.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-23"><akn:num>(23)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 18 V.S.A. § 1513, relating to minors using tanning facilities.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-24"><akn:num>(24)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 18 V.S.A. §§ 4230a and 4230b, relating to possession of cannabis.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-25"><akn:num>(25)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 9 V.S.A. chapter 97A that are subject to civil penalties pursuant to 9 V.S.A. § 3890</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-26"><akn:num>(26)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 9 V.S.A. § 4191, relating to the solicitation or acceptance of a fee to remove a booking photograph from the Internet.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-27"><akn:num>(27)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 10 V.S.A. § 1454</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-28"><akn:num>(28)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 20 V.S.A. § 4625, relating to the use of drones near correctional facilities.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-29"><akn:num>(29)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 10 V.S.A. chapter 21, relating to the prohibition of outdoor advertising.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-b_subsec-30"><akn:num>(30)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Violations of 13 V.S.A. § 7611, relating to the unauthorized disclosure of sealed criminal history record information.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Judicial Bureau shall not have jurisdiction over municipal parking violations.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1102_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Three hearing officers appointed by the Court Administrator shall determine waiver penalties to be imposed for violations within the Judicial Bureau’s jurisdiction, except municipalities shall adopt full and waiver penalties for civil ordinance violations pursuant to 24 V.S.A. § 1979. For purposes of municipal violations, the issuing law enforcement officer shall indicate the appropriate full and waiver penalty on the complaint.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1103"><akn:num>Section 1103</akn:num><akn:heading>Venue</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Venue for violation hearings in the Judicial Bureau shall be in the unit of the Superior Court where the violation is alleged to have occurred.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1104"><akn:num>Section 1104</akn:num><akn:heading>Appointment of hearing officers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Chief Superior Judge shall appoint members of the Vermont Bar to serve as hearing officers to hear cases. Hearing officers shall be subject to the Code of Judicial Conduct.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1105"><akn:num>Section 1105</akn:num><akn:heading>Answer to complaint; default</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1105_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A violation shall be charged upon a summons and complaint form approved and distributed by the Court Administrator. The complaint shall be signed by the issuing officer or by the State’s Attorney. The original shall be filed with the Judicial Bureau; a copy shall be retained by the issuing officer or State’s Attorney, and two copies shall be given to the defendant. The Judicial Bureau may, consistent with rules adopted by the Supreme Court pursuant to 12 V.S.A. § 1, accept electronic signatures on any document, including the signatures of issuing officers, State’s Attorneys, and notaries public. The complaint shall include a statement of rights, instructions, notice that a defendant may request a hearing or accept the penalties without a hearing, notice of the fee for failure to answer within 21 days, and other notices as the Court Administrator deems appropriate. The Court Administrator, in consultation with appropriate law enforcement agencies, may approve a single form for charging all violations or may approve two or more forms as necessary to administer the operations of the Judicial Bureau.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1105_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A person who is charged with a violation shall have 21 days from the date the complaint is issued to request a hearing or to state that he or she will accept the penalties without a hearing. The Judicial Bureau shall assess against a defendant a fee of $20.00 for failure to answer a complaint within the time allowed. The fee shall be assessed in the default judgment and deposited in the Court Technology Special Fund established pursuant to section 27 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1105_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A person who accepts the penalties may so indicate and sign the complaint. The Bureau shall accept the admission or statement that the allegations are not contested and accept payment of the waiver penalty.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1105_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If the person sends in the amount of the waiver penalty without signing the complaint, the Bureau shall accept the payment indicating that payment was made and that the allegations were not contested.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1105_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A person who denies the allegations or who wishes to have a hearing on the complaint for any other reason may so indicate and sign the complaint. Upon receipt, the Bureau shall schedule a hearing.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1105_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If a person fails to appear or answer a complaint, the Bureau shall enter a default judgment against the person. However, no default judgment shall be entered until the filing of a declaration by the issuing officer or State’s Attorney, under penalty of perjury, setting forth facts showing that the defendant is not a person in military service as defined in 50 U.S.C. § 3911 (Servicemembers Civil Relief Act definitions), except upon order of the hearing officer in accordance with the Act. The Bureau shall mail a notice to the person that a default judgment has been entered. A default judgment may be set aside by the hearing officer for good cause shown.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1105_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All Judicial Bureau judgments shall contain a notice of tax setoff pursuant to 32 V.S.A. § 5941.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1106"><akn:num>Section 1106</akn:num><akn:heading>Hearing</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1106_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Bureau shall notify the person charged and the issuing officer of the time and place for the hearing.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1106_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The hearing shall be held before a hearing officer and conducted in an impartial manner. The hearing officer may, by subpoena, compel the attendance and testimony of witnesses and the production of books and records. All witnesses shall be sworn. The burden of proof shall be on the State or municipality to prove the allegations by clear and convincing evidence. As used in this section, “clear and convincing evidence” means evidence that establishes that the truth of the facts asserted is highly probable. Certified copies of records supplied by the Department of Motor Vehicles or the Agency of Natural Resources and presented by the issuing officer or other person shall be admissible without testimony by a representative of the Department of Motor Vehicles or the Agency of Natural Resources.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1106_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The hearing officer shall make findings that shall be stated on the record or, if more time is needed, made in writing at a later date. The hearing officer may make a finding that the person has committed a lesser included violation. If the hearing officer finds that the defendant committed a violation, the hearing officer shall consider evidence of ability to pay, if offered by the defendant, prior to imposing a penalty.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1106_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A law enforcement officer may void or amend a complaint issued by that officer by so marking the complaint and returning it to the Bureau, regardless of whether the amended complaint is a lesser included violation. At the hearing, a law enforcement officer may void or amend a complaint issued by that officer in the discretion of that officer.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1106_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A State’s Attorney may dismiss or amend a complaint.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1106_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Supreme Court shall establish rules for the conduct of hearings under this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1107"><akn:num>Section 1107</akn:num><akn:heading>Appeals</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1107_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A decision of the hearing officer may be appealed to the Criminal Division of the Superior Court. The proceeding before the Criminal Division of the Superior Court shall be on the record or, at the option of the defendant, de novo. The defendant shall have the right to trial by jury. An appeal shall stay payment of a penalty and the imposition of points.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1107_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1107_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If a decision is appealed, the State’s Attorney of the county in which the violation occurred shall represent the State, and the State’s Attorney, municipal attorney, or other designee of the legislative body of the municipality shall represent the municipality.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1107_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>No appeal as of right exists to the Supreme Court. On motion made to the Supreme Court by a party, the Supreme Court may allow an appeal to be taken to it from the Criminal Division of the Superior Court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1108"><akn:num>Section 1108</akn:num><akn:heading>Judicial Bureau violations; jurisdiction of assistant judges</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1108_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Subject to the limits of this section and notwithstanding any provision of law to the contrary, an assistant judge sitting alone shall have the same jurisdiction, powers, and duties to hear and decide matters within the jurisdiction of the Judicial Bureau under section 1102 of this title as a hearing officer has under the provisions of this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1108_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1108_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An assistant judge who elects to hear and decide matters in the Judicial Bureau shall:
(A) [Repealed.]
(B) have successfully completed at least 40 hours of training, which shall be provided by the Court Administrator; and
(C) annually complete eight hours of continuing education supervised by the Court Administrator.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1108_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The training and education required by this subsection shall be developed by the Court Administrator in consultation with the Association of Assistant Judges. Law clerk assistance shall be available to the assistant judges.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1108_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Chief Superior Judge may assign or direct assignment of an assistant judge with the assistant judge’s consent to hear matters in the Judicial Bureau within the county in which the assistant judge presides or in a county other than the county in which the assistant judge presides if the assistant judge has elected to hear and decide such matters.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109"><akn:num>Section 1109</akn:num><akn:heading>Remedies for failure to pay; contempt</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Definitions.   As used in this section:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Amount due” means all financial assessments contained in a Judicial Bureau judgment, including penalties, fines, surcharges, court costs, and any other assessment authorized by law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Designated collection agency” means a collection agency designated by the Court Administrator.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Late fees; suspensions for nonpayment of certain traffic violation judgments.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A Judicial Bureau judgment shall provide notice that a $30.00 fee shall be assessed for failure to pay within 30 days. If the defendant fails to pay the amount due within 30 days, the fee shall be added to the judgment amount and deposited in the Court Technology Special Fund established pursuant to section 27 of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) In the case of a judgment on a traffic violation for which the imposition of points against the person’s driving record is authorized by law, the judgment shall contain a notice that failure to pay or otherwise satisfy the amount due within 30 days of the notice will result in suspension of the person’s operator’s license or privilege to operate and that payment plan options are available. If the defendant fails to pay the amount due within 30 days of the notice, or by a later date as determined by a Judicial Bureau clerk or hearing officer, and the case is not pending on appeal, the Judicial Bureau shall provide electronic notice thereof to the Commissioner of Motor Vehicles. After 20 days from the date of receiving the electronic notice, the Commissioner shall suspend the person’s operator’s license or privilege to operate for a period of 30 days or until the amount due is satisfied, whichever is earlier.
(B) At minimum, the Judicial Bureau shall offer a payment plan option that allows a person to avoid a suspension of his or her license or privilege to operate by paying no more than $30.00 per traffic violation judgment per month and not to exceed $100.00 per month if the person has four or more outstanding judgments.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Civil contempt proceedings.   If an amount due remains unpaid for 75 days after the Judicial Bureau provides the defendant with a notice of judgment, the Judicial Bureau may initiate civil contempt proceedings pursuant to this subsection.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notice of hearing.   The Judicial Bureau shall provide notice by first-class mail sent to the defendant’s last known address that a contempt hearing will be held pursuant to this subsection and that failure to appear at the contempt hearing may result in the sanctions listed in subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subsection.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Failure to appear.   If the defendant fails to appear at the contempt hearing, the hearing officer may direct the clerk of the Judicial Bureau to do one or more of the following:
(A) cause the matter to be reported to one or more designated collection agencies; or
(B) refer the matter to the Criminal Division of the Superior Court for contempt proceedings.
(C) [Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-c_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) Hearing.   The hearing shall be conducted in a summary manner. The hearing officer shall examine the defendant and any other witnesses and may require the defendant to produce documents relevant to the defendant’s ability to pay the amount due. The State or municipality shall not be a party except with the permission of the hearing officer. The defendant may be represented by counsel at the defendant’s own expense.
(B) Traffic violations; reduction of amount due.   When the judgment is based upon a traffic violation, the hearing officer may waive the reinstatement fee required pursuant to 23 V.S.A. § 675</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>or reduce the amount due on the basis of the defendant’s driving history, ability to pay, or service to the community; the collateral consequences of the violation; or the interests of justice. The hearing officer’s decision to reduce the amount due shall not be subject to review or appeal except in the case of a violation of rights guaranteed under the Vermont or U.S. Constitution.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Contempt.
(A) The hearing officer may conclude that the defendant is in contempt if the hearing officer states in written findings a factual basis for concluding that:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the defendant knew or reasonably should have known that he or she owed an amount due on a Judicial Bureau judgment;
(ii) the defendant had the ability to pay all or any portion of the amount due; and
(iii) the defendant failed to pay all or any portion of the amount due.
(B) In the contempt order, the hearing officer may do one or more of the following:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Set a date by which the defendant shall pay the amount due.
(ii) Assess an additional penalty not to exceed ten percent of the amount due.
(iii) [Repealed.]
(iv) Recommend that the Criminal Division of the Superior Court incarcerate the defendant until the amount due is paid. If incarceration is recommended pursuant to this subdivision </akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Collections.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If an amount due remains unpaid after the issuance of a notice of judgment, the Court Administrator may authorize the clerk of the Judicial Bureau to refer the matter to a designated collection agency.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Court Administrator or the Court Administrator’s designee is authorized to contract with one or more collection agencies for the purpose of collecting unpaid Judicial Bureau judgments pursuant to 13 V.S.A. § 7171.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For purposes of civil contempt proceedings, venue shall be statewide. No entry or motion fee shall be charged to a defendant who applies for a reduced judgment under subdivision </akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1109_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notwithstanding 32 V.S.A. § 502, the Court Administrator is authorized to contract with a third party to collect fines, penalties, and fees by credit card, debit card, charge card, prepaid card, stored value card, and direct bank account withdrawals or transfers, as authorized by 32 V.S.A. § 583, and to add on and collect, or charge against collections, a processing charge in an amount approved by the Court Administrator.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1110"><akn:num>Section 1110</akn:num><akn:heading>Licenses or governmental contracts</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1110_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>As used in this section, “license” means any license, certification, or registration issued by an agency to conduct a trade or business, including a license to practice a profession or occupation, or a license required to engage in recreational activities, including licenses to hunt, fish, or trap.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1110_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Every applicant for a license shall sign a statement that the applicant is in good standing with respect to any unpaid judgment issued by the Judicial Bureau or Criminal Division of the Superior Court for fines or penalties for a violation or criminal offense. A license may not be issued or renewed without such a statement.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1110_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For the purposes of this section, a person is in good standing with respect to any unpaid judgment issued by the Judicial Bureau or Criminal Division of the Superior Court for fines or penalties for a violation or criminal offense if:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1110_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>60 days or fewer have elapsed since the date a judgment was issued; or</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1110_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the person is in compliance with a repayment plan approved by the judiciary.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1111"><akn:num>Section 1111</akn:num><akn:heading>Civil violation; failure to produce identification</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1111_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A law enforcement officer is authorized to detain a person if:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1111_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the officer has reasonable grounds to believe the person has committed a civil violation of Title 7, 10, 13, 18, or 23; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1111_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the person refuses to identify himself or herself satisfactorily to the officer when requested by the officer.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-04_chapter-29_section-1111_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The person may be detained under this section only until the person identifies himself or herself satisfactorily to the officer or is properly identified. If the officer is unable to obtain the identification information, the person shall forthwith be brought before a judge in the Criminal Division of the Superior Court for that purpose. A person who refuses to identify himself or herself to the court on request shall immediately and without service of an order on the person be subject to civil contempt proceedings pursuant to 12 V.S.A. § 122.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter></akn:title></akn:body></akn:act></akn:akomaNtoso>