<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akn:akomaNtoso xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><akn:act><akn:meta><akn:identification source="#cosilico"><akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-03" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-03" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-05-01" name="release" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#vermont-legislature" /><akn:FRBRcountry value="us-vt" /><akn:FRBRnumber value="03" /><akn:FRBRname value="Vermont Statutes Annotated" /></akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-03/eng@2023-05-01" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-03/eng@2023-05-01" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2023-05-01" name="publication" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /><akn:FRBRlanguage language="eng" /></akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRManifestation><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-03/eng@2023-05-01/akn.xml" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-vt/act/vsa/title-03/eng@2023-05-01/akn.xml" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /></akn:FRBRManifestation></akn:identification><akn:references><akn:TLCOrganization eId="vermont-legislature" href="https://legislature.vermont.gov" showAs="Vermont General Assembly" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico" /></akn:references></akn:meta><akn:body><akn:title eId="title-03"><akn:num>Title 03</akn:num><akn:heading>Executive</akn:heading><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-1"><akn:num>Chapter 1</akn:num><akn:heading>Governor</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-2"><akn:num>Chapter 2</akn:num><akn:heading>Interagency Teams; Children and Adolescents with Severe Emotional Disturbances [Transferred]</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-3"><akn:num>Chapter 3</akn:num><akn:heading>Secretary of Civil and Military Affairs</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-5"><akn:num>Chapter 5</akn:num><akn:heading>Secretary of State</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-7"><akn:num>Chapter 7</akn:num><akn:heading>Attorney General</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-9"><akn:num>Chapter 9</akn:num><akn:heading>Administrative Departments</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-10"><akn:num>Chapter 10</akn:num><akn:heading>Federal Tax Information</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-11"><akn:num>Chapter 11</akn:num><akn:heading>State Officers and Employees Generally</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-13"><akn:num>Chapter 13</akn:num><akn:heading>Classification of State Personnel</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-14"><akn:num>Chapter 14</akn:num><akn:heading>Standards for Contracts Including Privatization Contracts</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-15"><akn:num>Chapter 15</akn:num><akn:heading>Vermont Employees’ Retirement System</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-16"><akn:num>Chapter 16</akn:num><akn:heading>Vermont Employees’ Retirement System</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-16A"><akn:num>Chapter 16A</akn:num><akn:heading>Defined Contribution Retirement Plan</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-17"><akn:num>Chapter 17</akn:num><akn:heading>Vermont State Police and Motor Vehicle Inspectors’ Retirement System</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-17"><akn:num>Chapter 17</akn:num><akn:heading>Vermont Pension Investment Commission</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-19"><akn:num>Chapter 19</akn:num><akn:heading>Social Security for State and Municipal Employees</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-21"><akn:num>Chapter 21</akn:num><akn:heading>Insurance Benefits</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-22"><akn:num>Chapter 22</akn:num><akn:heading>Deferred Compensation Programs</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-23"><akn:num>Chapter 23</akn:num><akn:heading>Rules, Regulations, and Executive Orders</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-25"><akn:num>Chapter 25</akn:num><akn:heading>Administrative Procedure</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-27"><akn:num>Chapter 27</akn:num><akn:heading>State Employees Labor Relations Act</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-28"><akn:num>Chapter 28</akn:num><akn:heading>Judiciary Employees Labor Relations Act</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-29"><akn:num>Chapter 29</akn:num><akn:heading>Claims Against State Employees</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-31"><akn:num>Chapter 31</akn:num><akn:heading>Governmental Ethics</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-1"><akn:num>Chapter 1</akn:num><akn:heading>Governor</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-1"><akn:num>Section 1</akn:num><akn:heading>Vacancy, absence from State</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-1_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When there is a vacancy in the Offices of Governor and Lieutenant Governor, the Speaker of the House of Representatives shall act as Governor.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-1_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When the Governor is absent from the State, the Lieutenant Governor shall act for him or her, and when both the Governor and Lieutenant Governor are absent from the State, the Speaker of the House shall act as Governor.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-2"><akn:num>Section 2</akn:num><akn:heading>Agencies and boards in Governor’s office</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-2_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>State Claims Commission</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-2_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Emergency Board</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-2_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All agencies which involve or concern interstate relationships including:
(A) Connecticut River Flood Control Commission
(B) New England Board of Higher Education
(C) [Repealed.]
(D) Lake Champlain Bridge Commission
(E) Tri-State Regional Medical Needs Board
(F) Committee on Tri-State Institutional Matters
(G) Uniform Laws Commission
(H) New England Interstate Water Pollution Control Commission
(I) Interstate Commission on Lake Champlain Basin
(J) Northeastern Forest Fire Protection Commission</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-2_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All interdepartmental agencies including:
(A) Interdepartmental Mental Health Council
(B) Traffic Committee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-3"><akn:num>Section 3</akn:num><akn:heading>Executive clerk and messenger</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>At the beginning of his or her term, the Governor shall appoint an executive clerk and an executive messenger for the term of two years to serve him or her when the General Assembly is in session and may remove them at pleasure.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-4"><akn:num>Section 4</akn:num><akn:heading>Correspondence</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-4_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The official correspondence of the Governor is the property of the State. Upon retiring from office, he or she shall cause such correspondence and an itemized list thereof to be deposited with the Secretary of State. The Secretary of State shall preserve these records in accordance with professional archival practices recommended by the State Archivist.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-4_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In the discretion of the Secretary of State, such correspondence and list, in whole or in part, may be microfilmed or otherwise reformatted in accordance with archival principles. In the discretion of the Secretary of State the originals of those papers that are actually reformatted may be disposed of.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-5"><akn:num>Section 5</akn:num><akn:heading>Counsel</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Governor may employ counsel in behalf of the State in any State department or office, when, in his or her judgment, the protection of the rights and interests of the State demands it.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-6"><akn:num>Section 6</akn:num><akn:heading>Certificates of election</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Governor shall furnish certificates of election to the Senators and Representatives elected to represent this State in Congress.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-7"><akn:num>Section 7</akn:num><akn:heading>Delegates</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Whenever in his or her judgment it is for the best interest of the State, the Governor may appoint a delegate to attend any convention, conference, or meeting without the State, as a representative of this State or any department thereof.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-8"><akn:num>Section 8</akn:num><akn:heading>Inspection of State institutions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Governor shall have power, in his or her discretion, to visit and inspect any State institution or to appoint a visitor to make such inspection and report to him or her.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-9"><akn:num>Section 9</akn:num><akn:heading>Rewards</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Governor may offer a suitable reward, not exceeding the sum of $1,000.00 in any case, to be paid to a person or persons who, in consequence of such offer, apprehends or secures a person who has escaped from any institution in this State in which he or she was lawfully confined and, when requested by the Attorney General, may offer such a reward for information leading to the arrest and conviction of any person who has committed a felony in this State.  The Commissioner of Finance and Management shall issue his or her warrant for the amount of such reward in favor of the person whom the Governor certifies to be entitled to the same.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-10"><akn:num>Section 10</akn:num><akn:heading>Authority to delegate functions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>When by provisions of any laws enumerated in section 13 of this title the Governor is required to approve any act, appointment, employment, or decision done or made by any other officer of the State Government or by any board, commission, or agency of the State government, as a condition to such act, appointment, employment, or decision becoming effective, the power and duty of the Governor as regards such approval may be delegated by him or her to any of the duly elected State officers or to any officer appointed by the Governor, or appointed by the Governor and with consent of the Senate or appointed with the approval of the Governor and with the consent of the Senate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-11"><akn:num>Section 11</akn:num><akn:heading>Method of delegating; responsibility of Governor</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The delegating of duties herein authorized shall be in writing and shall specify with particularity the cases in which it is to apply.  It shall become effective only when an executed duplicate copy of the delegation is filed in the Office of the Secretary of State.  Such delegation may be revoked at any time by the Governor, and such revocation shall be in writing and likewise filed as the original delegation.  The delegation of a particular function shall not prevent the Governor from acting in a case thereunder, and in any such instance, the delegation shall be of no effect.  Nothing contained herein shall relieve the Governor of his or her responsibility for the acts of any officer designated by him or her under the authority of sections 10-13 of this title to perform any function.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-12"><akn:num>Section 12</akn:num><akn:heading>Scope</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Sections 10-13 of this title shall be interpreted as applying only in cases in which the Governor’s duty is approval of a prior act, appointment, employment, or decision done or made by another officer or by a board, commission, or agency, and shall not be interpreted as applying in cases in which the act, appointment, employment, or decision is required to be done or made initially by the Governor but shall not include approval of rules or regulations.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-13"><akn:num>Section 13</akn:num><akn:heading>Application</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Sections 10-13 of this title shall apply only to the following sections: 202, 207 and 631 of this title; 4 V.S.A. § 852; 6 V.S.A. §§ 3, 4, 982, 1141 and 2922; 10 V.S.A. §§ 53, 54 and 4149; 20 V.S.A. §§ 1484, 1874(a), 1875, 2221, 2271 and 2273; 21 V.S.A. § 1104; 22 V.S.A. § 282; 23 V.S.A. § 103; 29 V.S.A. §§ 3 and 1104; and 32 V.S.A. §§ 3104 and 3105.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-14"><akn:num>Section 14</akn:num><akn:heading>Federal Highway Safety Act; powers of Governor and political subdivision</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-14_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Governor shall be responsible for the administration of the State’s Highway Safety Program, and may cooperate with and contract with State and federal agencies and political subdivisions, and public and private organizations, in order to effectuate the purposes of the National Highway Safety Act of 1966 and any amendments thereto, to the end that federal monies available for such purposes may be obtained.  The Governor may designate an appropriate agency of the State through which the State’s Highway Safety Program may be administered.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-14_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Governor shall provide for the receipt, allocation, and disbursement of federal monies received pursuant to this section, in accordance with such State and federal laws and regulations as may be applicable.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-14_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Towns, cities, emergency medical services districts, municipalities, and other political subdivisions are authorized to administer local highway safety programs approved by the Governor as part of the State’s Highway Safety Program, and to receive funds available for the foregoing purposes subject to applicable laws and regulations and the approval of the Governor.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-17"><akn:num>Section 17</akn:num><akn:heading>Federal funding cuts; transfer of personnel</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>To enable the Governor to respond effectively to cuts in federal spending and in the interests of efficiency, he or she may, with the approval of the General Assembly or the Joint Fiscal Committee if the General Assembly is not in session, temporarily transfer positions among the departments and agencies of the Executive Branch of government; provided, however, that no transfer may be made under this section which substantially affects the functioning of a program or policy which has been approved or adopted by the General Assembly.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-18"><akn:num>Section 18</akn:num><akn:heading>Spouse abuse programs; eligibility</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-18_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There is hereby created the Spouse Abuse Program.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-18_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Vermont Center for Crime Victim Services shall be authorized to award grants for the Spouse Abuse Program. Awards shall be made by the Center to spouse abuse programs established for the purpose of providing shelter, protection, or support for battered or abused spouses. The Center shall, insofar as possible, award grants to provide reasonable geographic distribution of funds around the State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-18_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-18_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In order to receive funds under this section, each participating program shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-18_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Receive some funding from one or more local, municipal, or county source, public or private.  Contributions in kind, whether material, commodities, transportation, or office space, may be evaluated and counted as part of this requirement.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-18_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Reapply annually for continued funding as necessary.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-18_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Duties and functions of the Center.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-18_subsec-e_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Center shall adopt rules under chapter 25 of this title pursuant to which interested local programs may apply for funding.  Any local agency or organization may apply to participate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-18_subsec-e_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Center shall establish minimum standards for eligibility for State funds awarded through the provisions of this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-21"><akn:num>Section 21</akn:num><akn:heading>Sexual Assault Victims Program</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-21_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Sexual Assault Victims Program is hereby established.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-21_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Vermont Center for Crime Victim Services is authorized to award grants for a sexual assault victims program. Awards shall be made by the Center to a sexual assault victims program established for the purpose of providing emergency services, counseling, and support for victims of sexual assault. The Center shall, insofar as possible, award grants to provide reasonable geographic distribution of funds around the State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-21_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-21_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In order to receive funds under this section, each participating program shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-21_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Receive some funding from one or more local, municipal, or county source, public or private.  Contributions in kind, whether material, commodities, transportation, volunteer services, or office space, may be evaluated and counted as part of this requirement.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-21_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Reapply annually for continued funding as necessary.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-21_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Duties and functions of the Center.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-21_subsec-e_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Center shall adopt rules under chapter 25 of this title pursuant to which interested local programs may apply for funding. Any local agency or organization may apply to participate.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-21_subsec-e_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Center shall establish minimum standards for eligibility for State funds awarded through the provisions of this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23"><akn:num>Section 23</akn:num><akn:heading>The Commission on International Trade</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Definitions.   For the purposes of this section: “International Trade Agreement” means a trade agreement between the federal government and a foreign country. International Trade Agreement does not include a trade agreement between the State and a foreign country to which the federal government is not a party.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Membership.   There is created a Commission on International Trade and State Sovereignty consisting of:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Chair of the House Committee on Commerce or his or her designee;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Chair of the Senate Committee on Economic Development, Housing and General Affairs or his or her designee;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a representative of a nonprofit environmental organization, appointed by the Governor from a list provided by the Vermont Natural Resources Council;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a representative of organized labor, appointed by the Governor from a list provided by Vermont AFL-CIO, Vermont NEA, and the Vermont State Employees’ Association;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-b_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Secretary of Commerce and Community Development or his or her designee;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-b_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Attorney General or his or her designee;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-b_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a representative of an exporting Vermont business, appointed by the Governor;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-b_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a representative of a Vermont business actively involved in international trade, appointed by the Governor;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-b_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the Secretary of Agriculture, Food and Markets or his or her designee; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-b_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>a representative of a Vermont chamber of commerce, appointed by the Governor.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Powers and duties.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Commission shall conduct an annual assessment of the legal and economic impacts of International Trade Agreements on State and local laws, State sovereignty, and the business environment.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>It shall provide a mechanism for citizens and legislators to voice their concerns, which it shall use to make policy recommendations to the General Assembly, to the Governor, to Vermont’s congressional delegation, or to the trade representatives of the United States government. Recommendations shall be designed to protect Vermont’s job and business environment, and State sovereignty from any negative impacts of trade agreements.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>It may recommend legislation or preferred practices and shall work with interested groups in other states to develop means to resolve the conflicting goals and tension inherent in the relationship between international trade and State sovereignty.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-c_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>As provided for in 9 V.S.A. chapter 111A, the Commission shall consider and develop formal recommendations with respect to how the State should best respond to challenges and opportunities posed by a particular International Agreement.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Reporting.   The Commission shall submit an annual report, which shall be prepared by the Secretary of Commerce and Community Development, to the House Committee on Commerce and Economic Development, the Senate Committee on Economic Development, Housing and General Affairs, the Governor, and Vermont’s congressional delegation. The report shall contain information acquired pursuant to activities carried out under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section. The provisions of 2 V.S.A. § 20</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(expiration of required reports) shall not apply to the report to be made under this subsection.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Staff services.   The Commission shall be entitled to staff services of the Agency of Commerce and Community Development, the Office of Legislative Counsel, the Office of Legislative Operations, and the Joint Fiscal Office.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Per diem.   For attendance at a meeting when the General Assembly is not in session, legislative members of the Commission shall be entitled to the same per diem compensation and reimbursement for actual and necessary expenses as provided members of standing committees under 2 V.S.A. § 23. Except for members employed by the State, members of the Commission shall be entitled to the same per diem compensation as provided under 32 V.S.A. § 1010</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-1_section-23_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>and mileage reimbursement as provided under 32 V.S.A. § 1267.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-2"><akn:num>Chapter 2</akn:num><akn:heading>Interagency Teams; Children and Adolescents with Severe Emotional Disturbances [Transferred]</akn:heading></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-3"><akn:num>Chapter 3</akn:num><akn:heading>Secretary of Civil and Military Affairs</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-3_section-51"><akn:num>Section 51</akn:num><akn:heading>Seal</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of Civil and Military Affairs shall have a seal of office upon which shall be the words: EXECUTIVE DEPARTMENT.  VERMONT.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-3_section-52"><akn:num>Section 52</akn:num><akn:heading>Records</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary shall keep a full and complete record of official acts of the Executive Department in books to be furnished for that purpose and such record books, except those in actual use, shall be kept in the State House.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-3_section-53"><akn:num>Section 53</akn:num><akn:heading>Copies</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary shall make copies of records in his or her office, attested under his or her seal, for the fees provided by law, and full faith and credit shall be given to such copies.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter><akn:chapter eId="title-03_chapter-5"><akn:num>Chapter 5</akn:num><akn:heading>Secretary of State</akn:heading><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-101"><akn:num>Section 101</akn:num><akn:heading>Commission; office</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of State shall be commissioned by the Governor and shall keep an office open for the transaction of business.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-102"><akn:num>Section 102</akn:num><akn:heading>Seal</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary shall have a seal of office, with the same device as the State Seal, and around the Seal the words: SECRETARY OF STATE.  VERMONT.  Full faith and credit shall be given to certified copies and attestations under his or her Seal.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-102a"><akn:num>Section 102a</akn:num><akn:heading>Facsimile signature of Secretary of State</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>A facsimile of the signature of the Secretary of State imprinted by or at his or her direction upon any certification issued under Title 11 or 11A, upon any attestation required of the Secretary by law or upon any certification of official documents or records of which the Secretary is custodian shall have the same validity as the Secretary of State’s written signature.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-103"><akn:num>Section 103</akn:num><akn:heading>Documents required to be filed</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-103_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All deeds, contracts of sale, leases, and other documents or copies of same conveying land or an interest therein to the State, except for transportation rights-of-way, leases, and conveyances, shall be filed in the Office of the Secretary of State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-103_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All deeds, contracts of sale, leases, and other documents conveying land or an interest in land from the State as grantor, except for transportation rights-of-way, leases, and conveyances, shall be made out in duplicate by the authorized agent of the State. The original shall be delivered to the grantee and the duplicate copy, so marked, shall be filed in the Office of the Secretary of State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-103_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of State shall also record the State Treasurer’s bonds and other documents required to be recorded in the Secretary of State’s office and give copies of the same upon tender of the Secretary of State’s legal fees.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-104"><akn:num>Section 104</akn:num><akn:heading>Preparation and publication of acts and resolutions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>After an act or resolution has been passed by both Houses of the General Assembly, signed by the presiding officers of both Houses and by the Governor, it shall be delivered to the custody of the Secretary of State.  The Secretary shall cause the act or resolution to be reproduced in form suitable to be submitted to the printer designated in 29 V.S.A. § 1115. Before submission to the printer, the Secretary shall correct obvious typographical errors and assign a public law number to each act or resolution.  The Secretary shall cause a suitable index and reference tables to be prepared.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-106"><akn:num>Section 106</akn:num><akn:heading>Acts and resolutions of the General Assembly</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>After the original acts and resolutions of the General Assembly are delivered to the Secretary pursuant to section 104 of this title, the Secretary shall cause a copy of the acts and resolutions to be prepared and printed and the original acts and resolutions to be preserved as State archival records pursuant to 3 V.S.A. § 117.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-107"><akn:num>Section 107</akn:num><akn:heading>Legislative clerk</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-107_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>to prepare a copy of the acts and resolutions for printing;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-107_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>to keep a register of lobbyists;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-107_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>to prepare and distribute certified copies of resolutions as directed by the General Assembly;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-107_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>to prepare index and tables of laws for the acts and resolves;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-107_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>to prepare a legislative directory containing appropriate matter by December 1 of each odd numbered year; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-107_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>such other legislative duties as the Secretary shall assign.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-108"><akn:num>Section 108</akn:num><akn:heading>Compilations, indices, bulletins, and circulars</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary shall cause to be prepared and printed such compilations of the different chapters of the Vermont Statutes Annotated, and amendments thereto or laws affecting the subject matter thereof, as may be necessary for the purpose of distribution, exchange, or for the use of the respective State officers, commissioners, departments, and citizens of the State.  The Secretary may cause such compilations to be provided with the proper indices.  He or she shall also cause bulletins or circulars to be prepared and printed relating to statistical and other matters of public nature on file or recorded in his or her office, and may employ necessary assistance for the preparation of such compilations, indices, bulletins, and circulars.  The expense of such preparation and publication of such compilations, indices, bulletins, and circulars shall be paid by the State, and the Commissioner of Finance and Management shall issue his or her warrants for such expenses when the accounts therefor have been duly approved by the Secretary.  All accounts for printing shall also be approved by the Commissioner of Buildings and General Services before the Commissioner of Finance and Management issues such warrants.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-109"><akn:num>Section 109</akn:num><akn:heading>Laws and journals</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary shall procure one copy of the printed journal of each House of the General Assembly at each session thereof, one copy of the laws passed at such session, one copy of this and all subsequent revisions of the laws, immediately after the same are printed and published, and deposit the same in his or her office, which, with such laws and journals and revisions of the laws as are now in his or her office, shall be kept therein and shall not be taken therefrom unless by authority of law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-110"><akn:num>Section 110</akn:num><akn:heading>Surveyor General’s papers</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>All books, papers and records of the Surveyor General which are in the possession of the State or may come into its possession shall be in the custody of the Secretary of State, and copies thereof duly certified by such officer shall be evidence in court and have the same force as the original.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-111"><akn:num>Section 111</akn:num><akn:heading>Township charters</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-111_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary shall procure from the proper sources authenticated copies of such original charters of townships in this State as were not granted by the General Assembly.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-111_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Copies of original charters of townships deposited in the Secretary of State’s office shall be valid records of such charters, and such record or copies thereof duly certified by the Secretary of State shall be competent evidence of such original charters in Court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-112"><akn:num>Section 112</akn:num><akn:heading>Statements and communications to General Assembly</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary shall make such statements and communications to the General Assembly as may be required by it.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-113"><akn:num>Section 113</akn:num><akn:heading>Record by photostatic or photographic method</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of State may record by photostatic or photographic method any instrument, paper, or document required by law to be recorded by him or her, and he or she may give photostatic or photographic copies of the same, required by law to be filed or recorded with him or her, upon tender of his or her legal fees. Such copies, duly certified by him or her, shall be competent evidence in court and have the same force as the originals thereof would have had, if produced in court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-116a"><akn:num>Section 116a</akn:num><akn:heading>Section 116a effective January 1, 2023. State boards and commissions registry</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-116a_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-116a_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Vermont State Archives and Records Administration shall maintain and make available on its website a registry of State boards and commissions and shall update that registry when changes are made that affect the information provided in the registry.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-116a_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) The registry shall include the names of the members of each State board and commission, their term length and expiration, and their appointing authority.
(B) Each State board and commission shall be responsible for providing to the Vermont State Archives and Records Administration this registry information and any updates to it in a manner prescribed by the State Archivist.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-116a_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The registry shall track the dates of the initial creation of State boards and commissions created by State law and of any amendments to those laws for the purpose of the intended five-year expiration of those State boards and commissions described in subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-116a_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-116a_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-116a_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>It is the intent of the General Assembly that, except for State boards and commissions required by interstate compact and except as otherwise provided by law, a State board or commission created by State law shall cease to exist after five years from the date of its initial creation, five years from the last date that the statutory or session law containing the State board or commission was amended, or on January 1, 2025, whichever date is latest.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-116a_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) In each biennial session beginning in the year 2025, the Office of Legislative Counsel, in consultation with the Vermont State Archives and Records Administration and based on the registry’s date tracking described in subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-116a_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, shall prepare for the General Assembly’s review a list of the State boards and commissions subject to expiration under this subsection.
(B) A State board or commission shall only expire pursuant to legislative enactment.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-116a_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>As used in this section, “State board or commission” means a professional or occupational licensing board or commission, advisory board or commission, appeals board, promotional board, interstate board, supervisory board or council, or any other similar entity that:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-116a_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>is created by State law, by federal law and contains State appointees, or by executive order;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-116a_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>is established as or is attached to an Executive Branch entity;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-116a_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>has statewide jurisdiction or carries out a State function; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-116a_subsec-c_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>is not composed of members appointed exclusively by regional, county, or municipal entities.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117"><akn:num>Section 117</akn:num><akn:heading>Vermont State Archives and Records Administration</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>As used in this chapter:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Records and information management” means the efficient and systematic control of the creation, receipt, maintenance, use, and disposition of public records, including the processes for capturing and maintaining evidence of, and information about, public agency business activities and transactions in the form of public records.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Archives” or “archival records” means public records that have continuing legal, administrative, or informational value.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Appraisal” means the identification, classification, and analysis of all public records, regardless of physical form or characteristics, to determine their value and ultimate disposition, based upon their legal, administrative, or informational value.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Public record” or “public document” has the same meaning as set forth in 1 V.S.A. § 317.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Public agency” has the same meaning as set forth in 1 V.S.A. § 317.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-a_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Record schedule” means a policy issued by the Vermont State Archives and Records Administration and approved by the State Archivist governing the life cycle management, retention, and disposition of public records.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There is created within the Office of the Secretary of State the Vermont State Archives and Records Administration, which is charged with administering a Statewide Records and Information Management Program for all public agencies in accordance with generally accepted record-keeping principles and industry standards and best practices.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Services of the Statewide Records and Information Management Program shall include:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>providing assistance to public agencies in establishing, maintaining, and implementing active and continuing internal records and information management programs for the effective management of records produced or acquired in the course of public agency business;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>ensuring that low-cost, secure repositories and systems for public records, regardless of format, are available at an enterprise or statewide level and managed and operated in a manner that supports compliance with generally accepted record-keeping principles, industry standards, best practices, the Public Records Act, this section, and, where applicable, section 218 of this title;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>developing, issuing, and maintaining statewide records and information management standards and information governance frameworks;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-c_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>performing formal appraisals of public records and issuing record schedules accordingly;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-c_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>operating a Records Center to hold inactive analog State public records in accordance with record schedules;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-c_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>accepting land records submitted on microfilm by municipal and county clerks for storage in the Records Center;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-c_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>taking legal custody of State archival records, regardless of format, in accordance with record schedules; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-c_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>arranging, describing, and preserving archival records in accordance with archival principles and best practices, and promoting their use by government officials and the public.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The State Archivist may appoint an advisory committee to provide assistance and support for the State Archives and Records Administration.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary may adopt rules consistent with this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There shall be the Director of the Vermont State Archives and Records Administration who shall have the title of “State Archivist,” who shall be qualified by education and professional experience to perform the duties of the position, and who shall simultaneously serve as Chief Records Officer. The State Archivist shall be a classified position within the Office of the Secretary of State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In fulfilling the duties as Director of the Vermont State Archives and Records Administration, the State Archivist shall:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-g_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>issue policies, standards, guidelines, and procedures necessary to carry out the provisions of this section;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-g_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>administer and maintain the Statewide Records and Information Management Program for the efficient and systematic control of public records;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-g_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>approve record schedules governing the life cycle management, retention, and disposition of public records;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-g_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>receive grants, gifts, aid, or assistance, of any kind, from any source, public or private, for the purpose of managing, preserving, or promoting public records; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-g_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>serve as chair of the Vermont Historical Records Advisory Board pursuant to 36 C.F.R. part 1206 for the purposes of improving public access to, and engagement with, Vermont historical records and encouraging and facilitating collaborative efforts among Vermont historical records repositories.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-h"><akn:num>(h)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-j"><akn:num>(j)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-k"><akn:num>(k)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There is hereby created the Public Records Special Fund. The Fund shall be administered as a special fund pursuant to 32 V.S.A. chapter 7, subchapter 5. The purpose of the Fund is to support improved management of public records by State agencies. The Fund shall consist of receipts from other government agencies for the provision of Records and Information Management Program services by the Vermont State Archives and Records Administration in the Office of the Secretary of State. The Fund shall be available to the Office of the Secretary of State and shall be expended for the purposes of activities authorized by subsection 117</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-117_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-118"><akn:num>Section 118</akn:num><akn:heading>Collection and disposition of revenue</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-118_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>There is hereby created a Secretary of State Services Fund. The Fund shall be used to provide appropriations for the operations of the Office of the Secretary of State, with the exception of those operations provided for in chapter 5, subchapter 3 of this title. The Fund shall be administered as a special fund pursuant to 32 V.S.A. chapter 7, subchapter 5. At the end of each fiscal year, the unobligated balance in this Fund shall be transferred to the General Fund.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-118_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>All revenues collected by the Secretary of State shall be deposited into the Secretary of State Services Fund except for the following revenues:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-118_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>any revenues collected by the Office of Professional Regulation set forth in chapter 5, subchapter 3 of this title; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-118_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>any revenues collected pursuant to subsection 117</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-118_subsec-k"><akn:num>(k)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-121"><akn:num>Section 121</akn:num><akn:heading>Definitions</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-121_subsec-j"><akn:num>(j)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this subchapter or the Director in advisor professions. Notwithstanding statutory language to the contrary, this subchapter shall apply to all those boards.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-121_subsec-j_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) “License” includes any certification, registration, permit, commission, or other official authorization to undertake a regulated activity.
(B) “Licensee” includes any person to whom a license has been issued by a board or the Director.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-121_subsec-j_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>“Office” means the Office of Professional Regulation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122"><akn:num>Section 122</akn:num><akn:heading>Office of Professional Regulation</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Board of Architects</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Barbers and Cosmetologists</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Board of Chiropractic</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Board of Allied Mental Health Practitioners</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Board of Dental Examiners</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Funeral Service</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Board of Professional Engineering</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Board of Land Surveyors</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Board of Nursing</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Nursing Home Administrators</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-12"><akn:num>(12)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Opticians</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-13"><akn:num>(13)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Board of Optometry</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-14"><akn:num>(14)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Board of Osteopathic Physicians and Surgeons</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-15"><akn:num>(15)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Board of Pharmacy</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-16"><akn:num>(16)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Physical Therapists</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-17"><akn:num>(17)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Radiologic Technology</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-18"><akn:num>(18)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Private Investigative and Security Services</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-19"><akn:num>(19)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Board of Public Accountancy</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-20"><akn:num>(20)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Board of Veterinary Medicine</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-21"><akn:num>(21)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Motor Vehicle Racing</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-22"><akn:num>(22)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Boxing</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-23"><akn:num>(23)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Board of Psychological Examiners</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-24"><akn:num>(24)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Real Estate Commission</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-25"><akn:num>(25)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Clinical Social Workers</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-26"><akn:num>(26)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Acupuncturists</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-27"><akn:num>(27)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Tattooists and Body Piercers</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-28"><akn:num>(28)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Audiologists and Hearing Aid Dispensers</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-29"><akn:num>(29)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Real Estate Appraisers</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-30"><akn:num>(30)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Auctioneers</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-31"><akn:num>(31)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Occupational Therapists</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-32"><akn:num>(32)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Dietitians</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-33"><akn:num>(33)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Respiratory Care Practitioners</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-34"><akn:num>(34)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Psychoanalysts</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-35"><akn:num>(35)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Foresters</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-36"><akn:num>(36)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>[Repealed.]</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-37"><akn:num>(37)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Naturopathic Physicians</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-38"><akn:num>(38)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Athletic Trainers</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-39"><akn:num>(39)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Midwifery</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-40"><akn:num>(40)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Electrology</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-41"><akn:num>(41)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Speech-Language Pathologists</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-42"><akn:num>(42)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Landscape Architects</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-43"><akn:num>(43)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Property Inspectors</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-44"><akn:num>(44)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Applied Behavior Analysts</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-45"><akn:num>(45)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Alcohol and Drug Abuse Counselors</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-46"><akn:num>(46)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Potable Water Supply and Wastewater System Designers</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-47"><akn:num>(47)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Pollution Abatement Facility Operators</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-48"><akn:num>(48)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notaries Public</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-49"><akn:num>(49)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Massage Therapists, Bodyworkers, and Touch Professionals</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-50"><akn:num>(50)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Well Drillers</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-122_subsec-51"><akn:num>(51)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Residential Contractors</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123"><akn:num>Section 123</akn:num><akn:heading>Duties of office</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Office shall provide administrative, secretarial, financial, investigatory, inspection, and legal services to the boards. The services provided by the Office shall include:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Sending, receiving, and processing applications for licenses.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Issuing, recording, renewing, and reinstating all licenses as ordered by the boards, an appellate officer, the Director, an administrative law officer, or a court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Revoking or suspending licenses as ordered by the boards, the Director, an administrative law officer, or a court.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Keeping all files and records of the boards, including minutes of meetings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Compiling and maintaining a current register of all licensees.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-a_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Compiling and maintaining statistical information for each board, including the number of applications received; the number of licenses, certificates, registrations, and permits issued, renewed, and reinstated; examination results; the number and disposition of inspections and complaints; and the number of board meetings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-a_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Collecting and depositing all fees into the Professional Regulatory Fee Fund.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-a_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Arranging payment of all expenses incurred by the boards within the limits of the funds appropriated to them.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-a_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Standardizing, to the extent feasible and with the advice of the boards, all applications, licenses, and other related forms and procedures, and adopting uniform procedural rules governing the investigatory and disciplinary process for all boards set forth in section 122 of this chapter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-a_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notifying the public and board members of all meetings and examinations to be held by the boards and arranging for places for those meetings and examinations.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-a_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Assisting the boards in developing rules consistent with the principles set forth in 26 V.S.A. chapter 57. Notwithstanding any provision of law to the contrary, the Secretary of State shall serve as the adopting authority for those rules.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-a_subsec-12"><akn:num>(12)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>With the assistance of the boards, establishing a schedule of license renewal and termination dates so as to distribute the renewal work in the Office as effectively as possible.
(A) Licenses may be issued and renewed according to that schedule for periods of up to two years.
(B) A person whose initial license is issued within 90 days prior to the set renewal date shall not be required to renew the license until the end of the first full biennial licensing period following initial licensure.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-a_subsec-13"><akn:num>(13)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>To the extent that resources permit, providing other administrative services that are necessary or desirable for the efficient operation of the boards.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Director shall consult with each board and prepare a consolidated budget for the Office. The consolidated budget shall also contain funds deemed to be required by the Director for the administration of this chapter. The Director shall submit the consolidated budget to the Secretary of State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Director may purchase examination materials and contract with examination providers to administer examinations.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Director may adopt procedures for the effective administration of this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Secretary of State shall contract with and appoint one or more attorneys licensed to practice in this State to serve as administrative law officers under subsection 129</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-j"><akn:num>(j)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title or appellate officers under section 130a of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Classified State employees who are employed as investigators by the Secretary of State who have successfully met the standards of training for a Level III law enforcement officer under 20 V.S.A. chapter 151 shall have the same powers as sheriffs in criminal matters and the enforcement of the law and in serving criminal process, and shall have all the immunities and matters of defense now available or hereafter made available to sheriffs in a suit brought against them in consequence for acts done in the course of their employment.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-g_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Office shall establish uniform procedures applicable to all of the professions and boards set forth in section 122 of this chapter, providing for:
(A) appropriate recognition of education, training, or service completed by a member of the U.S. Armed Forces toward the requirements of professional licensure; and
(B) expedited issuance of a professional license to a person who is licensed in good standing in another regulatory jurisdiction; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>whose spouse is a member of the U.S. Armed Forces and who has been subject to a military transfer to Vermont; and
(ii) who left employment to accompany his or her spouse to Vermont.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-i_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Director may evaluate specific military credentials to determine equivalency to credentials required for professions attached to the Office. The determinations shall be adopted through written policy that shall be posted on the Office’s website.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-i_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Director may evaluate apprenticeship programs recognized or administered by the Vermont Department of Labor, Agency of Education, or U.S. Department of Labor to determine equivalency to credentials required for professions attached to the Office. The determinations shall be adopted through written policy that shall be posted on the Office’s website.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-h"><akn:num>(h)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notwithstanding any provision of Title 26 of the Vermont Statutes Annotated to the contrary, the Office, on behalf of the Director or a board, may use electronic mail to send notices and reminders that would otherwise be sent by mail, except certified mail, and may use online services to elicit information and sworn attestations that would otherwise be obtained on a paper form.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-i_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Director shall actively monitor the actions of boards attached to the Office and shall ensure that all board actions pursued or decided are lawful, consistent with State policy, reasonably calculated to protect the public, and not an undue restraint of trade.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-i_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>If the Director finds an exercise of board authority or discretion does not meet those standards, the Director may, except in the case of disciplinary actions:
(A) provide written notice to the board explaining the perceived inconsistency, which notice shall have the effect of staying that action and implementing any alternative prescribed by the Director;
(B) schedule a public meeting with the board to resolve questions about the action and explore alternatives; and
(C) within 60 days following that meeting, issue a written directive finding that:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the exercise of board authority or discretion is consistent with State policy, in which case the action shall be reinstated;
(ii) the exercise of board authority or discretion is inconsistent with State policy in form, but may be modified to achieve consistency, in which case the board may issue a modified action consistent with the Director’s recommendation; or
(iii) the exercise of board authority or discretion is inconsistent with State policy in purpose, in which case any alternative prescribed by the Director shall stand as the regulatory policy of the State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-j"><akn:num>(j)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-j_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Office may inquire into the criminal background histories of applicants for initial licensure and for license renewal of any Office-issued credential, including a license, certification, registration, or specialty designation for the following professions:
(A) licensed nursing assistants, licensed practical nurses, registered nurses, and advanced practice registered nurses licensed under 26 V.S.A. chapter 28;
(B) private investigators, security guards, and other persons licensed under 26 V.S.A. chapter 59;
(C) real estate appraisers and other persons or business entities licensed under 26 V.S.A. chapter 69; and
(D) osteopathic physicians licensed under 26 V.S.A. chapter 33.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-j_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Prior to acting on an initial or renewal application, the Office may obtain with respect to the applicant a Vermont criminal history record, an out-of-state criminal history record, and a criminal history record from the Federal Bureau of Investigation. Federal Bureau of Investigation background checks shall be fingerprint-supported, and fingerprints so obtained may be retained on file and used to notify the Office of future triggering events. Each applicant shall consent to the release of criminal history records to the Office on forms developed by the Vermont Crime Information Center.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-j_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Applicants subject to background checks shall be notified that a check is required, if fingerprints will be retained on file, and that criminal convictions are not an absolute bar to licensure, and shall be provided such other information as may be required by federal law or regulation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-k"><akn:num>(k)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For any profession attached to it, the Office shall provide a pre-application determination of an individual’s criminal background. This determination shall not be binding on the Office in a future application if the individual violates probation or parole or is convicted of another crime following the determination.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-k_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Office shall initiate this determination upon an individual’s “second chance” determination request. This request shall provide documentation related to the individual’s conviction or convictions, evidence of rehabilitation, and identification of the profession or professions for which the individual seeks licensure.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-k_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The individual shall submit this request online, accompanied by the fee for preapplication determinations set forth in section 125 of this subchapter. If the individual thereafter applies for licensure, this preapplication fee shall be deducted from that license application fee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-k_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Office shall:
(A) process a request within 30 days of receiving a complete request;
(B) assess the nature of the underlying conviction or convictions, the nexus to the profession or professions for which the individual seeks licensure, and the provided evidence of rehabilitation; and
(C) respond to the individual’s request in writing.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-123_subsec-l"><akn:num>(l)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When, by reason of disqualification, resignation, vacancy, or necessary absence, a board is unable to form a quorum or assign one or more members to assist in the investigation and prosecution of complaints or license applications, or to adjudicate a contested case, the Secretary of State may appoint ad hoc members, either as voting members to establish a quorum at a specific meeting or as nonvoting members to assist Office investigators and prosecutors.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-124"><akn:num>Section 124</akn:num><akn:heading>Professional Regulatory Fee Fund</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-124_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Except as otherwise provided in subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-124_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, it is the policy of this State that:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-124_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>the cost of regulating a profession attached to the Office of Professional Regulation should be borne by the profession; and</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-124_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>one profession should not subsidize the cost of regulating another profession.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-124_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Professions regulated by the Director in consultation with advisor appointees shall share the cost of regulating those professions.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-124_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A Professional Regulatory Fee Fund is created. All revenues received by the office shall be deposited into the Fund, credited to the appropriate board or to the professions regulated by the Director as a group, as appropriate, shall be used to offset up to two years of the costs incurred by that board or that group and shall not be used for any purpose other than professional regulation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-124_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>To ensure that revenues derived by the Office are adequate to offset the cost of regulation, the Secretary of State shall review fees from time to time, and present proposed fee changes to the General Assembly.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125"><akn:num>Section 125</akn:num><akn:heading>Fees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In addition to the fees otherwise authorized by law, a board or advisor profession may charge the following fees:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Verification of license, $20.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An examination fee established by the Secretary, which shall be no greater than the costs associated with examinations.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Reinstatement fees for expired licenses pursuant to section 127 (unauthorized practice) of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Continuing, qualifying, or prelicensing education course approval:
(A) Provider, $100.00.
(B) Individual, $25.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A preapplication criminal background determination, $25.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Unless otherwise provided by law, the following fees shall apply to all professions regulated by the Director in consultation with advisor appointees under Title 26:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Application for registration, $75.00, except application for:
(A) Private investigator and security services employees, unarmed registrants, $60.00.
(B) Private investigator and security service employees, transitory permits, $60.00.
(C) Private investigator and security service employees, armed registrants, $120.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Application for licensure or certification, $100.00, except application for:
(A) Barbering or cosmetology schools and shops, $300.00.
[Subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Optician trainee registration, $50.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Biennial renewal, $240.00, except biennial renewal for:
(A) Independent clinical social workers and master’s social workers, $150.00.
(B) Occupational therapists and assistants, $150.00.
(C) Physical therapists and assistants, $150.00.
(D) Optician trainees, $100.00.
(E) Barbers, cosmetologists, nail technicians, and estheticians, $130.00.
(F) Schools of barbering or cosmetology, $300.00.
(G) Funeral directors and embalmers, $280.00.
[Subdivision</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125_subsec-b_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Limited temporary license or work permit, $50.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125_subsec-b_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Radiologic evaluation, $125.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125_subsec-b_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Annual renewal for appraisal management company registration, $300.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notwithstanding any provisions of law to the contrary, a board shall not require payment of renewal fees for years during which a license was lapsed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-125_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Pursuant to qualifications and procedures determined by the Director, the Office shall, upon request, waive application fees to qualified military members and military spouses.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-126"><akn:num>Section 126</akn:num><akn:heading>Agent for process; nonresident licensees</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p>Whenever a person practicing a profession attached to the Office resides outside the borders of the State and fails to appoint an agent for process, the Secretary of State shall be an agent of that person, upon whom any process, notice, or demand may be served.  In the event any process, notice, or demand is served on the Secretary of State, the Secretary shall immediately cause one of the copies thereof to be forwarded by certified mail, addressed to the person at its registered Office.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-127"><akn:num>Section 127</akn:num><akn:heading>Unauthorized practice</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-127_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When the Office receives a complaint of unauthorized practice, the Director shall refer the complaint to Office investigators and prosecutors.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-127_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-127_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A person practicing a regulated profession without authority or an employer permitting such practice may, upon the complaint of the Attorney General or a State’s Attorney or an attorney assigned by the Office of Professional Regulation, be enjoined therefrom by the Superior Court where the violation occurred or the Washington County Superior Court and may be assessed a civil penalty of not more than $5,000.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-127_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) The Attorney General or an attorney assigned by the Office of Professional Regulation may elect to bring an action seeking only a civil penalty of not more than $2,500.00 for practicing or permitting the practice of a regulated profession without authority before the board having regulatory authority over the profession or before an administrative law officer.
(B) Hearings shall be conducted in the same manner as disciplinary hearings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-127_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) A civil penalty imposed by a board or administrative law officer under this subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-127_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>shall be deposited in the Professional Regulatory Fee Fund established in section 124 of this chapter for the purpose of providing education and training for board members and advisor appointees.
(B) The Director shall detail in the annual report receipts and expenses from these civil penalties.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-127_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In addition to other provisions of law, unauthorized practice shall be punishable by a fine of not more than $5,000.00 or imprisonment for not more than one year, or both. Prosecution may occur upon the complaint of the Attorney General or a State’s Attorney or an attorney assigned by the Office of Professional Regulation under this section and shall not act as a bar to civil or administrative proceedings involving the same conduct.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-127_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-127_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A person whose license has expired for not more than one biennial period may reinstate the license by meeting renewal requirements for the profession, paying the profession’s renewal fee, and paying the following nondisciplinary reinstatement penalty:
(A) if reinstatement occurs within 30 days after the expiration date, $100.00; or
(B) if reinstatement occurs more than 30 days after the expiration date, an amount equal to the renewal fee increased by $40.00 for every additional month or fraction of a month, provided the total penalty shall not exceed $1,500.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-127_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Fees assessed under this subsection shall be deposited into the Regulatory Fee Fund and credited to the appropriate fund for the profession of the reinstating licensee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-127_subsec-d_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A licensee seeking reinstatement may submit a petition for relief from the reinstatement penalty, which a board may grant only upon a finding of exceptional circumstances or extreme hardship to the licensee; provided, however, that fees under this subsection shall not be assessed for any period during which a licensee was a member of the U.S. Armed Forces on active duty.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-127_subsec-d_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Practice by a licensee with an expired license that continues for more than two years, or practicing at any time when the licensee knew or should have known the license was expired, may be prosecuted by the State as unauthorized practice under this section or as unprofessional conduct pursuant to subdivision 129a</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-127_subsec-d_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this title.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-127_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A person practicing a licensed profession without authority shall not institute any proceedings in this State for the enforcement of any right or obligation if at the time of the creation of the right or obligation the unlicensed person was acting without authority.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-127_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The provisions of this section shall be in addition to any other remedies or penalties for unauthorized practice established by law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-128"><akn:num>Section 128</akn:num><akn:heading>Disciplinary action to be reported to the Office</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-128_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-128_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Any hospital, clinic, community mental health center, or other health care institution in which a licensee performs professional services shall report to the Office, along with supporting information and evidence, any disciplinary action taken by it or its staff that limits or conditions the licensee’s privilege to practice or leads to suspension or expulsion from the institution.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-128_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The report shall be made within 10 days of the date the disciplinary action was taken, regardless of whether the action is the subject of a pending appeal, and in the case of a licensee who is employed by, or under contract with, a community mental health center, a copy of the report shall also be sent to the Commissioners of Mental Health and of Disabilities, Aging, and Independent Living.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-128_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>This section shall not apply to cases of resignation, separation from service, or changes in privileges that are unrelated to:
(A) a disciplinary or adverse action;
(B) an adverse action report to the National Practitioner Data Bank;
(C) an unexpected adverse outcome in the care or treatment of a patient;
(D) misconduct or allegations of misconduct;
(E) the initiation or process of an action to limit, condition, or suspend a licensee’s privilege to practice in an institution;
(F) an action to expel the licensee from an institution; or
(G) any other action that could lead to an outcome described in subdivisions (A) through (F) of this subdivision (3).</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-128_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Within 30 days of any judgment or settlements involving a claim of professional negligence by a licensee, any insurer of the licensee shall report such information to the Office, regardless of whether the action is the subject of a pending appeal.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-128_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Information provided to the Office under this section shall be confidential unless the Office decides to treat the report as a complaint, in which case the provisions of section 131 of this title shall apply.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-128_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A person who acts in good faith in accord with the provisions of this section shall not be liable for damages in any civil action.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-128_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A person who violates this section shall be subject to a civil penalty of not more than $1,000.00.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129"><akn:num>Section 129</akn:num><akn:heading>Powers of boards or of Director in advisor professions; discipline process</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In addition to any other provisions of law, a board or the Director, in the case of professions that have advisor appointees, may exercise the following powers:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Consistent with other law and State policy, develop administrative rules establishing evidence-based standards of practice appropriate to secure and promote the public health, safety, and welfare; open and fair competition within the marketplace for professional services; interstate mobility of professionals; and public confidence in the integrity of professional services.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Issue subpoenas and administer oaths in connection with any authorized hearing, investigation, or disciplinary proceeding. Subpoenas may be issued ex parte by the chair of the board, the Director, or any attorney representing a party. Depositions may be taken after charges upon due notice to all parties without specific authorization by the board.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Issue warnings or reprimands, suspend, revoke, limit, condition, deny, or prevent renewal of licenses, after disciplinary hearings or, in cases requiring emergency action, immediately suspend, as provided by section 814 of this title. In a case involving noncompliance with a statute or rule relating to administrative duties not related to patient, client, or customer care, a board or hearing officer may determine that ordering a monetary civil penalty does not constitute a finding of unprofessional conduct.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Reinstate or deny reinstatement of a license that has been revoked, suspended, limited, or conditioned.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Discipline any licensee or refuse to license any person who has had a license application denied or a license revoked, suspended, limited, conditioned, or otherwise disciplined by a licensing agency in another jurisdiction for conduct that would constitute unprofessional conduct in this State, or has surrendered a license while under investigation for unprofessional conduct.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-a_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notify relevant State, federal, and local agencies and appropriate bodies in other states of the status of any disciplinary case against an applicant or licensee, provided the board has taken disciplinary action or has served a notice of charges against the person.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-a_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Refuse to accept the return of a license tendered by the subject of a disciplinary investigation or refuse to allow an applicant who is the subject of a disciplinary investigation to withdraw his or her application without permission of the board.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-a_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Adopt rules governing the issuance of licenses to practice, to persons licensed and in good standing to practice in another jurisdiction, that authorize the holder of the license to practice in this State for no more than 10 days or 80 hours in any calendar year upon payment of the required fee.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-a_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For good cause shown, waive fees when a license is required to provide services on a pro bono basis or in accordance with standards established by the board by rule.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-a_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) Issue temporary licenses during a declared state of emergency. The person to be issued a temporary license must be:</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>currently licensed, in good standing, and not subject to disciplinary proceedings in any other jurisdiction; or
(ii) a graduate of an approved education program during a period when licensing examinations are not reasonably available.
(B) The temporary license shall authorize the holder to practice in Vermont until the termination of the declared state of emergency or 90 days, whichever occurs first, provided the licensee remains in good standing, and may be reissued by the board if the declared state of emergency continues longer than 90 days.
(C) Fees shall be waived when a license is required to provide services under this subdivision.</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-i_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Treat as incomplete any license application submitted with a check subsequently returned for insufficient funds or without the personal attestation of the applicant or an authorized officer of an applicant corporation as to the representations therein.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-i_subsec-12"><akn:num>(12)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Waive or modify continuing education requirements for persons on active duty in the U.S. Armed Forces.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-i_subsec-13"><akn:num>(13)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Administer a Vermont statutes and rules examination as a condition of licensure, renewal, or reinstatement.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-i_subsec-14"><akn:num>(14)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Grant an honorary license to those individuals having demonstrated outstanding service to a profession, at the discretion of the board. An honorary license shall not confer the right or privilege to practice the profession in this State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A board or the Director, in the case of professions that have advisor appointees, shall receive complaints from any source, or may investigate without receiving a complaint.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-c_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Boards and administrative law officers sitting in disciplinary cases shall do so impartially and without ex parte knowledge of the case in controversy.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-c_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A State prosecuting attorney assigned by the Office shall be responsible for prosecuting disciplinary cases before boards or administrative law officers.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-c_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Office may assign one or more board members or advisors to assist Office investigators and the prosecutor in relation to the investigation and prosecution of licensing and disciplinary matters. If a board member has served in this capacity, the member shall not participate in ex parte communications with other board members regarding the case and shall not participate in deliberating or deciding the case.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A board or the Director shall notify parties, in writing, of their right to appeal final decisions of the board. A board or the Director shall also notify complainants in writing of the result of any disciplinary investigation made with reference to a complaint brought by them to the board or Director. When a disciplinary investigation results in a stipulation filed with the board, the board or the Director shall provide the complainant with a copy of the stipulation and notice of the stipulation review scheduled before the board. The complainant shall have the right to be heard at the stipulation review.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-e_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>When a board or the Director, in the case of professions that have advisor appointees, intends to deny an application for a license, the board or Director shall send the applicant written notice of the decision by certified mail. The notice shall include a statement of the reasons for the action and shall advise the applicant that the applicant may file a petition within 30 days of the date on which the notice is mailed with the board or the Director for review of its or his or her preliminary decision.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-e_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>At the hearing, the applicant shall bear the burden of proving that the preliminary denial should be reversed and that the license should be granted.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-e_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>After the hearing, the board or Director shall affirm or reverse the preliminary denial, explaining the reasons therefor in writing.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-f_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) The Director may appoint a hearing officer, who shall be an attorney admitted to practice in this State, to conduct a hearing that would otherwise be heard by a board. A hearing officer appointed under this subsection may administer oaths and exercise the powers of the board properly incidental to the conduct of the hearing.
(B) When disciplinary charges are pending concurrently against a single individual or entity, in one profession or multiple, the Director is authorized to order that the matters be consolidated in a single proceeding.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-f_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In board professions, when a hearing is conducted by a hearing officer, the officer shall report findings of fact and conclusions of law to the board. The report shall be made within 60 days of the conclusion of the hearing unless the board grants an extension. The provisions of section 811 of this title regarding proposals for decision shall not apply to the hearing officer report.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-f_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The board may take additional evidence and may accept, reject, or modify the findings and conclusions of the hearing officer. Judgment on the findings shall be rendered by the board.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A board may authorize any of the following:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-g_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Its chair or Office legal counsel to grant continuances of scheduled hearings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-g_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Its chair to grant or deny stays pending appeal.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-g_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An administrative law officer to convene and conduct prehearing conferences and to preside at hearings for the purpose of making procedural and evidentiary rulings. The board may overrule a ruling by an administrative law officer under this subdivision.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-g_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Office staff to grant applications that present no substantial discretionary or factual question and to administer the policies of the board between regular meetings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-h"><akn:num>(h)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-h_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A board member, hearing officer, or administrative law officer having a personal or pecuniary interest or the appearance of a personal or pecuniary interest in the outcome of any board decision shall not participate in deciding the matter.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-h_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) A board member, hearing officer, or administrative law officer whose disqualification is sought shall either disqualify himself or herself or, without ruling on the request for disqualification, refer the request to the Secretary of State, who shall rule on the request.
(B) The ruling of the Secretary of State on a request for disqualification shall be final and shall be subject to review only upon appeal of a final order of a board under section 130a of this title or of an administrative law officer under subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-j"><akn:num>(j)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-i"><akn:num>(i)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A board may consult with the Attorney General or an attorney assigned by the Office of Professional Regulation for the proper conduct of its affairs. The Director may assign Office legal counsel to assist a board in the lawful and orderly conduct of its open meetings and other nondisciplinary business, including making procedural and parliamentary rulings.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-j"><akn:num>(j)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Hearings involving denials of licensure or disciplinary matters concerning persons in professions that have advisor appointees shall be heard by an administrative law officer appointed by the Secretary of State.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-k"><akn:num>(k)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-k_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Whenever completion of certain continuing education requirements is a condition of renewal, the board may require the applicant to develop and complete a specific corrective action plan, to be completed within 90 days.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-k_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A board may grant a temporary renewal license pending the completion of the required continuing education.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-l"><akn:num>(l)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Unless a disciplinary order expressly provides to the contrary, discipline against any license or credential issued by a regulatory body attached to the Office to an individual or entity shall be applicable as a matter of law to all other licenses issued to that licensee by that regulatory body.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129_subsec-m"><akn:num>(m)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In any proceeding under this section that addresses an applicant’s or licensee’s alleged sexual misconduct, evidence of the sexual history of the victim of the alleged sexual misconduct shall neither be subject to discovery nor be admitted into evidence. Neither opinion evidence of nor evidence of the reputation of the victim’s sexual conduct shall be admitted.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a"><akn:num>Section 129a</akn:num><akn:heading>Unprofessional conduct</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In addition to any other provision of law, the following conduct by a licensee constitutes unprofessional conduct. When that conduct is by an applicant or person who later becomes an applicant, it may constitute grounds for denial of a license or other disciplinary action. Any one of the following items or any combination of items, whether the conduct at issue was committed within or outside the State, shall constitute unprofessional conduct:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Fraudulent or deceptive procurement or use of a license.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Advertising that is intended or has a tendency to deceive.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Failing to comply with provisions of federal or State statutes or rules governing the practice of the profession.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Failing to comply with an order of the board or violating any term or condition of a license restricted by the board.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Practicing the profession when medically or psychologically unfit to do so.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Delegating professional responsibilities to a person whom the licensed professional knows, or has reason to know, is not qualified by training, experience, education, or licensing credentials to perform them, or knowingly providing professional supervision or serving as a preceptor to a person who has not been licensed or registered as required by the laws of that person’s profession.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Willfully making or filing false reports or records in the practice of the profession, willfully impeding or obstructing the proper making or filing of reports or records, or willfully failing to file the proper reports or records.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-8"><akn:num>(8)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Failing to make available promptly to a person using professional health care services, that person’s representative, or succeeding health care professionals or institutions, upon written request and direction of the person using professional health care services, copies of that person’s records in the possession or under the control of the licensed practitioner, or failing to notify patients or clients how to obtain their records when a practice closes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-9"><akn:num>(9)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Failing to retain client records for a period of seven years, unless laws specific to the profession allow for a shorter retention period. When other laws or agency rules require retention for a longer period of time, the longer retention period shall apply.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-10"><akn:num>(10)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Conviction of a crime related to the practice of the profession or conviction of a felony, whether or not related to the practice of the profession. If an individual has a conviction of concern, the board or hearing officer shall consider the following in determining whether to deny or discipline a license, certification, or registration to the individual based on the following factors:
(A) the nature and seriousness of the conviction;
(B) the amount of time since the commission of the crime;
(C) the relationship of the crime to the ability, capacity, and fitness required to perform the duties and discharge the responsibilities of the profession; and
(D) evidence of rehabilitation or treatment.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-11"><akn:num>(11)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Failing to report to the Office a conviction of any felony or misdemeanor offense in a Vermont District Court, a Vermont Superior Court, a federal court, or a court outside Vermont within 30 days.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-12"><akn:num>(12)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Exercising undue influence on or taking improper advantage of a person using professional services, or promoting the sale of services or goods in a manner that exploits a person for the financial gain of the practitioner or a third party.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-13"><akn:num>(13)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Performing treatments or providing services that the licensee is not qualified to perform or that are beyond the scope of the licensee’s education, training, capabilities, experience, or scope of practice.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-14"><akn:num>(14)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Failing to report to the Office within 30 days a change of name, e-mail, or mailing address.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-15"><akn:num>(15)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Failing to exercise independent professional judgment in the performance of licensed activities when that judgment is necessary to avoid action repugnant to the obligations of the profession.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-16"><akn:num>(16)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) Impeding an investigation under this chapter or unreasonably failing to reply, cooperate, or produce lawfully requested records in relation to such investigation.
(B) The patient privilege set forth in 12 V.S.A. § 1612 shall not bar the licensee’s obligations under this subsection</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>and a confidentiality agreement entered into in concluding a settlement of a civil claim shall not exempt the licensee from fulfilling his or her obligations under this subdivision (16).</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-17"><akn:num>(17)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Advertising, promoting, or recommending a therapy or treatment in a manner tending to deceive the public or to suggest a degree of reliability or efficacy unsupported by competent evidence and professional judgment.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-18"><akn:num>(18)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Promotion by a treatment provider of the sale of drugs, devices, appliances, or goods provided for a patient or client in such a manner as to exploit the patient or client for the financial gain of the treatment provider, or selling, prescribing, giving away, or administering drugs for other than legal and legitimate therapeutic purposes.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-19"><akn:num>(19)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Willful misrepresentation in treatments or therapies.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-20"><akn:num>(20)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Offering, undertaking, or agreeing to cure or treat a disease or disorder by a secret method, procedure, treatment, or medicine.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-21"><akn:num>(21)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Permitting one’s name or license to be used by a person, group, or corporation when not actually in charge of or responsible for the professional services provided.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-22"><akn:num>(22)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Prescribing, selling, administering, distributing, ordering, or dispensing any drug legally classified as a controlled substance for the licensee’s own use or to an immediate family member as defined by rule.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-23"><akn:num>(23)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For any professional with prescribing authority, signing a blank or undated prescription form or negligently failing to secure electronic means of prescribing.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-24"><akn:num>(24)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For any mental health care provider, use of conversion therapy as defined in 18 V.S.A. § 8351 on a client younger than 18 years of age.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-25"><akn:num>(25)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For providers of clinical care to patients, failing to have in place a plan for responsible disposition of patient health records in the event the licensee should become incapacitated or unexpectedly discontinue practice.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-26"><akn:num>(26)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Sexually harassing or exploiting a patient, client, or consumer, or doing so to a coworker in a manner that threatens the health, safety, or welfare of patients, clients, or consumers; failing to maintain professional boundaries; or violating a patient, client, or consumer’s reasonable expectation of privacy.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-27"><akn:num>(27)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For a health care practitioner, failing to comply with one or more of the notice, disclosure, or advertising requirements in 18 V.S.A. § 4502 for administering stem cell or stem cell-related products not approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-a_subsec-28"><akn:num>(28)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Engaging in conduct of a character likely to deceive, defraud, or harm the public.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Failure to practice competently by reason of any cause on a single occasion or on multiple occasions may constitute unprofessional conduct, whether actual injury to a client, patient, or customer has occurred. Failure to practice competently includes:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>performance of unsafe or unacceptable patient or client care; or</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>failure to conform to the essential standards of acceptable and prevailing practice.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The burden of proof in a disciplinary action shall be on the State to show by a preponderance of the evidence that the person has engaged in unprofessional conduct.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-d_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>After hearing, and upon a finding of unprofessional conduct, a board or an administrative law officer may take disciplinary action against a licensee or applicant, including imposing an administrative penalty not to exceed $5,000.00 for each unprofessional conduct violation.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-d_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) Any money received under this subsection shall be deposited in the Professional Regulatory Fee Fund established in section 124 of this chapter for the purpose of providing education and training for board members and advisor appointees.
(B) The Director shall detail in the annual report receipts and expenses from money received under this subsection.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129a_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>In the case where a standard of unprofessional conduct as set forth in this section conflicts with a standard set forth in a specific board’s statute or rule, the standard that is most protective of the public shall govern.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129b"><akn:num>Section 129b</akn:num><akn:heading>Board member and advisor appointments</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129b_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notwithstanding any provision of law to the contrary relating to terms of office and appointments for members of boards attached to the Office of Professional Regulation, all board members appointed by the Governor shall be appointed for staggered five-year terms and shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor. Appointments under this section shall not be subject to the advice and consent of the Senate. The Governor may remove any member of a board as provided in section 2004 of this title. Vacancies created other than by expiration of a term shall be filled in the same manner that the initial appointment was made for the unexpired portion of the term. Terms shall begin on January 1 of the year of appointment and run through December 31 of the last year of the term. The Governor may request nominations from any source but shall not be bound to select board members from among the persons nominated. As provided in section 2004 of this title, board members shall hold office and serve until a successor has been appointed.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129b_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Board members shall not serve more than two consecutive terms. Members appointed to fill a vacancy created before the end of a term shall not be deemed to have served a term for purposes of this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129b_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Boards shall meet annually, in September or the first meeting scheduled thereafter, to elect a chair, vice chair, and secretary.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129b_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Meetings may be called by the chair or shall be called upon the request of any other two board members.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129b_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Meetings shall be warned and conducted in accordance with 1 V.S.A. chapter 5, the Open Meeting Law.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129b_subsec-f"><akn:num>(f)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Notwithstanding any provisions of law to the contrary, board members and advisors for all professions attached to the Office of Professional Regulation shall be entitled to compensation, at a rate provided in 32 V.S.A. § 1010 , for performance of official duties and other duties directly related to the efficient conduct of necessary business of a board or the Office.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129b_subsec-g"><akn:num>(g)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>For advisor professions:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129b_subsec-g_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>Advisors shall be appointed by the Secretary of State and shall serve at the pleasure of the Secretary of State. Advisor appointments shall be subject to the same conditions as those for board members under this section.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-129b_subsec-g_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Office shall warn and conduct an open meeting including advisors, program staff, and interested members of the public:
(A) at least once per year for each profession with 500 or fewer active licensees; and
(B) at least twice per year for each profession with more than 500 active licensees.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130"><akn:num>Section 130</akn:num><akn:heading>Provisional licensure</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Director may issue a 90-day provisional license to an individual who has completed an application for full licensure and:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>whose eligibility for licensure is contingent upon acceptable verification of licensure from another jurisdiction;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>whose eligibility for licensure is contingent upon completion of a background check; or</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130_subsec-a_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>who is an active-duty member of the U.S. Armed Forces assigned to duty in Vermont or the spouse of such a member.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A provisional license shall be based on a voluntary agreement between the applicant and the Office to expedite the applicant’s entry into the workforce, in which the applicant agrees to forgo the procedural rights associated with traditional licensure in exchange for a provisional license pending final determination of the license application.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A provisional license shall only be issued to an applicant who can attest to material facts consistent with the requirements of full licensure, including the applicant’s standing in other U.S. jurisdictions, criminal history, and disciplinary history. An individual to whom a provisional license is issued shall expressly agree that the Office may summarily withdraw the provisional license upon discovery of any inconsistency or inaccuracy in the application materials.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130_subsec-d"><akn:num>(d)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>An individual aggrieved by a denial or summary withdrawal of a provisional license issued under this section shall have as an exclusive remedy the right to have the individual’s application for conventional licensure determined according to the usual process.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130_subsec-e"><akn:num>(e)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The Director may extend a provisional license beyond the initial 90-day period if the reason for issuing the license, as set forth in subdivisions </akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130_subsec-e_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>of this section, has not been resolved.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section><akn:section eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130a"><akn:num>Section 130a</akn:num><akn:heading>Appeals</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130a_subsec-a"><akn:num>(a)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p /><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130a_subsec-a_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A party aggrieved by a final decision of a board or administrative law officer may, within 30 days of the decision, appeal that decision by filing a notice of appeal with the Director who shall assign the case to an appellate officer.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130a_subsec-a_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>(A) The review shall be conducted on the basis of the record created before the board or administrative law officer.
(B) In cases of alleged irregularities in procedure before the board or administrative law officer, not shown in the record, proof on that issue may be taken by the appellate officer.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130a_subsec-b"><akn:num>(b)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>The appellate officer shall not substitute his or her judgment for that of the board or administrative law officer as to the weight of the evidence on questions of fact. The appellate officer may affirm the decision, or may reverse and remand the matter with recommendations if substantial rights of the appellant have been prejudiced because the board’s or administrative law officer’s finding, inferences, conclusions, or decisions are:</akn:p><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130a_subsec-b_subsec-1"><akn:num>(1)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>in violation of constitutional or statutory provisions;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130a_subsec-b_subsec-2"><akn:num>(2)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>in excess of the statutory authority of the board or administrative law officer;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130a_subsec-b_subsec-3"><akn:num>(3)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>made upon unlawful procedure;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130a_subsec-b_subsec-4"><akn:num>(4)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>affected by other error of law;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130a_subsec-b_subsec-5"><akn:num>(5)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>clearly erroneous in view of the evidence on the record as a whole;</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130a_subsec-b_subsec-6"><akn:num>(6)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>arbitrary or capricious; or</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130a_subsec-b_subsec-7"><akn:num>(7)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>characterized by abuse of discretion or clearly unwarranted exercise of discretion.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:subsection><akn:subsection eId="title-03_chapter-5_section-130a_subsec-c"><akn:num>(c)</akn:num><akn:content><akn:p>A party aggrieved by a decision of the appellate officer may appeal to the Supreme Court, which shall review the matter on the basis of the records created before the board or administrative law officer and the appellate officer.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:subsection></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter></akn:title></akn:body></akn:act></akn:akomaNtoso>